<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-03-04T21:31:58+00:00</updated><id>/blog/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Wetiko: Healing the Mind-Virus That Plagues Our World</title><link href="/blog/2023/03/04/wetiko.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wetiko: Healing the Mind-Virus That Plagues Our World" /><published>2023-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2023/03/04/wetiko</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2023/03/04/wetiko.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Epilogue from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57335928-wetiko&quot;&gt;Wetiko: Healing the Mind-Virus That Plagues Our World&lt;/a&gt; by Paul Levy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In times of great social and political upheaval such as we see in the world today, whatever has been suppressed by the prevailing agreed upon attitudes builds up in—and disturbs—the collective unconscious, accumulating enormous energy that needs to be channeled somewhere. If these contents of the activated unconscious remain suppressed, however, there is a great danger that the unconscious will get into the driver’s seat of our vehicle. There it will, so to speak—destructively, instead of constructively—act out in the world what has been blocked from healthy expression and thereby rendered unconscious. Then we will be truly dreaming a nightmare, as we see in the converging world crises that are engulfing us at this current moment in history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes humanity is not saved from a crisis by the products of our conscious intellect, but rather the saving grace comes from something being revealed to us that emerges unexpectedly as a result of the crisis. Revelations—which can be likened to timeless treasures waiting to be discovered in time—come in many forms and in many ways. Sometimes they first emerge seemingly outside of ourselves through—or are triggered by—some external event in the world like the coronavirus outbreak. Ultimately speaking, however, the deepest revelation is something that lies hidden within the nature of our soul awaiting discovery. We have to reveal it out of and from within ourselves, which is a self-sanctifying act needing no outside validation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Awakening Treasures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are treasures buried within us, concealed within our unconscious. These hidden gems are like precious jewels or diamonds in the rough that are encoded within the fabric of the unconscious psyche. They can be conceived of as existing in a higher dimension relative to our conscious mind, and as such, are typically invisible to our intellect. These treasures, having lain buried and dormant in the collective unconscious of our species from time immemorial, are typically awakened in times of great need and duress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the time is ripe, our intuition—due to its connection to our unconscious—divines and begins to “see” the heretofore formless revelation that is gestating in the alchemical cauldron of the unconscious. Our task then becomes how to bring forth and creatively express the revelation in a form that helps it come to fruition as we realize it more clearly within ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential revelation can be conceived of as an innovative force of nature alive in the unconscious. This force is thirsting to incarnate both within our minds and into our world. As if a living entity gestating in the womb of the collective unconscious of humanity, this soon to be revelation will draft a suitably creative person—someone who is sensitive to and resonates with the potential revelation—to become the instrument through which the newborn revelation clothes itself. In this, it takes on a particular individualized form and enters into our third-dimensional world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our spirit, the sentient presence that animates us, is by its very nature creative. The very center of our being is an unknown creative energy that forges us in its likeness, one way or another (with our cooperation or not). As human beings we are a creative force thirsting for conscious realization. Our creativity isn’t as a mere hobby, a sideline, something that we should just indulge in on our days off. The creative spirit is an essential part of our being, the life-giving oxygen for our soul. Creative expression is not merely the embellishment of the forms of life, but the very dynamic of the life force itself taking new forms. The mysterious secret of our being can only be realized via participating in the creative act itself. Knowing is an act of creation in itself; if we want to know creativity, we have to be creative. There are no holy scriptures for this creative activity—we are left to our own devices. Being creative means to partake in our innate godlike spiritual freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can conceive of the creative instinct as a timeless, living impulse implanted in the human psyche that moves through the generations. The inspired individual participates within their own soul in the same creative process that takes place outside of themselves in nature. The creative person follows an unknown directive, a higher authority, what Jung would call the Self, the wholeness and guiding force of the deeper personality. People who are inspired by the creative spirit are oriented toward the invisible, toward a mysterious something that wants to become visible and reveal itself. The creative artist is giving utterance to the authentic and direct revelation of the numinosum, which raises their function to the level of the sacred. “The creative principle,” Erich Neumann writes, is typically venerated “as the hidden treasure that in humble form conceals [and, I might add, simultaneously reveals] a fragment of the godhead.”1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Listening to the Voice Inside&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wetiko is a “daemonic” energy, which is to say it is a transpersonal energy—beyond the merely personal—that can take over a person (or a group of people). The “daemon” can be envisioned as an indwelling force that can’t be nailed down because of its nomadic nature, taking up residence in those who are receptive to its call. Etymologically speaking, the inner meaning of the word daemon is our guiding spirit, inner voice, internal teacher, muse, spiritual ally, wish-fulfilling genie, and genius. The daemon connects us with our calling, and helps us find our vocation, our mission in life, why we are here on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original meaning of the word vocation has to do with being addressed by a voice. In listening to our inner voice—what Jung calls “the voice of the inner man”—we are at the same time given the sacred responsibility to outwardly speak in the world the voice that is uniquely ours to speak—our true authentic voice. The paradox is that in speaking the voice that is most our own, this voice does not belong to us. Rather it is the voice of all of humanity that resounds in us. The truly creative person, be they poet, writer, dancer, or painter, for instance, is that courageous someone, Jung writes, “voicing aloud what others only dream.”2 In other words, a creative person gives living form to something that exists in the formless and seemingly insubstantial ethers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demonic is the creative in statu nascendi, “not yet realized,” or “made real” by a conscious ego. This is to say that hidden encoded within the darkness of wetiko is our unexpressed creativity. When the creativity that naturally bubbles forth within us is suppressed, however, it feeds the poisonous aspect of wetiko. The malady that our species is collectively suffering from is, in essence, the fact that we are not connecting with, mobilizing, and expressing our creative nature. Once our creativity is repressed, the daemonic aspect of wetiko becomes demonic, our creativity turns back on itself and manifests destructively—be it within ourselves or out in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To have eyes and not see—to be blind—is an unmistakable symptom of an occlusion to the call of the creative spirit. The figure of the artist is the one who opens humanity’s eyes, teaching us how to see. The black-hole aspect of wetiko is a creativity-destroyer by its very nature, so we need to generate and mobilize as much ingenuity as possible in order to contend with it. Paradoxically, wetiko both spurns and spurs our creative impulses. The blazing fire of a soul set aflame with its own destiny, burning with the passion of following its deeper calling, fulfilling its mission in life, puts a stake through the heart of the inner vampiric figure of wetiko. The more we pursue what we love, what gives meaning to our lives, the more we allow our creative nature to express itself and the more we “kill” the inner figure of wetiko.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revelation is not something that the conscious ego could have invented by itself, but can only organically arise out of the tension between a stable consciousness and a charged unconscious. To consciously endure this innate creative tension necessarily involves a state of suffering. Describing the creative individual, Neumann writes, “Only by suffering, perhaps unconsciously, under the poverty of his culture and his time can he arrive at the freshly opening source which is destined to quench the thirst of his time.”3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our own individual suffering of the daemonic energies that pervade and make up the collective unconscious, the spirit within us intimately experiences the profound depths of the woundedness of the collectivity and the time in which we live. Spiritual practitioners and true artists are able to find within their own subjective experience, however, a unique and utterly original response to their wound. As if organs of the collective body politic of humanity, sensitive, spiritually attuned, and creative people are the alchemical retorts in which the poisons, the antidotes, and the psycho-spiritual medicines for the collective are distilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Healing Power of the Creative Spirit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no badge of honor or measure of sanity to adapt to a world gone mad. Instead of trying to adapt to the world’s insanity, a person who is awakening remains open to the world—and open to their wounds—such that a regenerative and curative power arises from within their own dark depths in response. This healing power is the creative spirit. The creative impulse is simultaneously an individual and collective phenomenon, which is to say that when any of us becomes a channel for this spirit, it serves all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A creative person’s healing power lies in their willingness to not cling to fixed ideas—of who they are or of the world at large—but to allow themselves to be shaped and informed by new experiences of the world. Then, in turn, they are able to translate and craft these experiences into novel “art”-iculations. This involves a receptivity to authentically and imaginatively respond to the reciprocal interactions and continual collisions—with the inevitable wounding—between ourselves and the world. The litmus test for our creativity is our inspired response—or lack thereof—to these experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hidden treasure, the great revelation that is hidden within our unconscious—also referred mythically as “The Treasure Hard to Attain”—is the creative spirit itself. When tapped into, this spirit is a seemingly inexhaustible source of inspiration within us that issues forth a stream of revelations like a spring bubbling upward from the depths of our unconscious. This living current—our greatest resource—helps us to connect with our source. Whenever it manifests, this vital spirit appears as a revelation in which we are participating as the instrument through which it incarnates in time and space. Our creativity transforms the world so as to find our place in it. To quote philosopher Martin Heidegger, “A work of art is something new in the world that changes the world to allow itself to exist.”4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our species is desperately in need of the guidance and aid of the boundless creative forces latent within the depths of our unconscious to help us find new ways to resolve the myriad interwoven aspects of our multiple world crises. Creative expression is the zero point at which consciousness and the unconscious momentarily become a generative unity. Only at the point in which the stream of unbridled inspiration emerges from the darkness of the unconscious and enters the light of consciousness, and is thus both at once—darkness and light—is the creative spirit made real in time. As resourceful individuals, it is our job to harness the raw impulses arising from the depths of the unconscious into a form that serves our world. This “creative point,” to again quote Neumann, is “the buried treasure which is the water of life, immortality, fertility, and the after-life all rolled into one.”5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not the conscious ego that will change the world, but rather, sufficient numbers of people who develop a relationship within themselves between their conscious and unconscious parts who then connect with one another—deepening each other’s inspiration in the process. As long as we remain unaware of the contents of our unconscious—therefore not being able to be the conscious architects of our inner landscape—our ability to transform the outer world will be limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that our widespread systemic crises are the result of a deficiency in human consciousness, it becomes obvious that it is only through an expansion of consciousness that we will be able to navigate the tight passage before us. Consciousness can evolve and develop, however, only where it preserves and cultivates a living connection with the creative powers of the unconscious. Just as our view of the world is a decisive factor in shaping the unconscious, the forces activated in the unconscious reciprocally transform our conscious perspectives. In its collective archetypal dimension the unconscious contains the wisdom and experience of untold ages and could serve as a guide par excellence for us during these troubled times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain individuals gifted with particularly strong intuition sense the moving currents taking place in the collective unconscious and are able to translate these changes into communicable language (verbal and/or nonverbal). These original expressions can potentially spread rapidly—going viral—and have such powerful transformative power because parallel changes have been taking place in the unconscious of other people. Contagious in its effects, genuine creative expression emerging at the right moment can “virally” spread via the unconscious of our species in ways that can ignite latent, creative energy lying dormant in the collective unconscious of humanity. This can bring forth and actualize hidden possibilities (both within us and in the world) into the light of conscious awareness, which is a process that has the power to effect real change in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new idea is itself an expression of a creative act. Certain ideas can assist us in remembering something that we had forgotten we had forgotten. A new idea—such as wetiko—can set up a chain reaction in people’s minds that can potentially unleash previously unimagined insight and creativity. As part of their design, mind-expanding ideas are meant to be shared with others so as to fully activate their nonlocal benefit and blessing. These ideas endlessly increase in potency the more they are shared among us. Like a key unlocking a door or like a charm that breaks a spell, a new symbolic idea can unleash the dormant creative spirit imprisoned within us. A revolutionary idea has the potential to catalyze revolutions in thinking; a shift in a single idea can precipitate a shift into a new epoch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creativity of the unconscious psyche—which is an agency in a state of never-ending re-creation and re-formation—continually transforms our experience of reality as well as itself. As an artist of life, we are what Neumann refers to as a “bearer of the divine miracle,” actively and endlessly participating in re-creating ourselves anew, revealing ourselves—to ourselves—through the bringing forth of our gifts to the world. Only in these acts do we actualize our wholeness. Acting out of our wholeness is like kryptonite to the seeming superpowers of wetiko. In being creative we not only find refuge from the dangers of wetiko, but we discover the true revelation that is none other than ourselves. Each new act of creativity brings with it an element of self-discovery. We must create in order to know ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When human beings are deprived of their freedom and power of expression, however, they will unconsciously express themselves in the drive for power. This only feeds the will to power of the demonic and destructive shadow, with the baneful consequences we see in the world today. Being oppressed in our expression, instead of stopping us cold, however, can potentially—if we so choose—fuel our creative fire, forging in us an “inner necessity” to connect with the living primal generative spirit that lives within us. The authentic creative spirit—if it’s the real thing—can’t be discouraged or kept down for long, for then it wouldn’t be creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Artists as Molders of the Collective Unconscious&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote poet Allen Ginsberg, “The warfare’s psychic now. Whoever controls the language, the images, controls the race.” Instruments of war in the hands of generals are extremely dangerous. In the same way, nothing is more dangerous and potentially world-transforming than implements of creative expression in the hands of artists. They are the molders of the unconscious psychic life of humanity, the mythmakers of their age. It is the artists—and we are all artists—who are the healers of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than letting our perceptions be managed and manipulated by the powers that be and their propaganda organs, we as sovereign beings can connect with our own perceptions and create our own unique and authentic experience of the world and a refreshed experience of ourselves. What a radical—and truly liberating—idea!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healing wetiko entails each of us becoming an empiricist—there is no getting around this. In this we must simply inquire directly into the nature of our present moment experience, without giving credence to what any outer authority is telling us is true. Ultimately speaking, we ourselves are the arbiters of our own experience. By our very nature, we are interpreters of our experience and generators of meaning. This is a process that affects our experience of both ourselves and of the universe at large. Realizing our own creative agency is where we find ourselves, which is the beginning of the cure for wetiko as well as the cure itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we creatively express our nature, it is nature itself that is doing the talking. Then there’s nothing to do but listen and respond in kind to our unique and individual call.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Epilogue from the book by Paul Levy</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond Privacy: The Seven Darknesses of Lunarpunk</title><link href="/blog/2022/09/30/beyond-privacy-the-seven-darknesses-of-lunarpunk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Privacy: The Seven Darknesses of Lunarpunk" /><published>2022-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2022/09/30/beyond-privacy-the-seven-darknesses-of-lunarpunk</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022/09/30/beyond-privacy-the-seven-darknesses-of-lunarpunk.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You darkness from which I come,&lt;br&gt;
I love you more than all the fires&lt;br&gt;
that fence out the world,&lt;br&gt;
for the fire makes a circle&lt;br&gt;
for everyone&lt;br&gt;
so that no one sees you anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But darkness holds it all:&lt;br&gt;
the shape and the flame,&lt;br&gt;
the animal and myself,&lt;br&gt;
how it holds them,&lt;br&gt;
all powers, all sight –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and it is possible: its great strength&lt;br&gt;
is breaking into my body.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have faith in the night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Rainer Maria Rilke&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunk first rose to the attention of the web3 community via the essay &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.egirlcapital.com/writings/107533289&quot;&gt;Lunarpunk and the Dark Side of the Cycle&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lunar_mining&quot;&gt;@lunar_mining&lt;/a&gt; in February 2022. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a note there that lunarpunk is &amp;quot;the solar shadow-self&amp;quot;, the author goes on to define lunarpunk overwhelmingly in terms of privacy, anonymity and a &amp;quot;conflict between crypto and existing power structures&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this piece I seek a broader notion of lunarpunk, returning to the idea of the &amp;quot;solar shadow-self&amp;quot; and exploring lunarpunk in its most general form as &lt;em&gt;the dark side of solarpunk&lt;/em&gt;, a complementary opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I identify privacy/anonymity as just one of Seven Darknesses of Lunarpunk, each with an associated &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/age-of-awareness/psychotechnology-and-the-multi-state-future-of-humanity-37a31a506022&quot;&gt;(psycho)technology&lt;/a&gt;: the Darknesses of &lt;strong&gt;Privacy, Attention, Suffering, Eros, Plants, Soul and Light&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks understand that there is nothing inherently bad or wrong about the dark, and to speak of darkness is not to suggest the &lt;em&gt;sinister&lt;/em&gt;. Rather, the commonality between the tools, techniques and technologies featured here is an association with &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;unconscious, the shadow&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;the taboo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of Privacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key technology: cryptography, as explored in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.egirlcapital.com/writings/107533289&quot;&gt;Lunarpunk and the Dark Side of the Cycle&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lunar_mining&quot;&gt;@lunar_mining&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Strong cryptography can resist an unlimited application of violence. No amount of coercive force will ever solve a math problem.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/16153182-cypherpunks&quot;&gt;Cypherpunks: Freedom and the Future of the Internet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;What’s the most powerful force on earth? In the 1800s, God. In the 1900s, the US military. And by the mid-2000s, encryption.. It doesn’t matter how many nuclear weapons you have; if property or information is secured by cryptography, the state can’t seize it without getting the solution to an equation.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenetworkstate.com/god-state-network&quot;&gt;The Network State&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks are masters of cryptography. They understand how pseudonymity grants not just freedom of speech, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehub.ca/in-the-know/2021-06-10/what-is-the-pseudonymous-economy-balaji-srinivasan/&quot;&gt;freedom after speech&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of Attention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: mastering of submissive/dominant attention, as explored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kasiaurbaniak.com/&quot;&gt;Kasia Urbaniak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;I understood that both the Taoist nuns and dominatrices I most admired were powerful precisely because they could control that conversation under the conversation—and it wasn’t through a self-conscious manipulation of their body language. Instead, they did so with something far more powerful and primal: their attention.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What I had been learning in the desert, in the dojo, and in the dungeon, then, could be summed up this way: the art of attention. Attention dictates where the energy is—the juice, the qi, the life force—in any given interaction. It is how our animal bodies communicate with one another. Language is important; so are physical gestures. But more important than both is where the attention is directed.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/51205436-unbound&quot;&gt;Unbound&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks are masters of attention, both submissive (inward) and dominant (outward). They practise a dominance that has nothing to do with the violent, toxic mimic of power we see so often in the world, and a submission that is never obsequious or subservient. Rather, in both states, they and those around them experience a deep sense of relaxation and flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of Suffering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50915816-existential-kink&quot;&gt;Existential Kink&lt;/a&gt; by Carolyn Elliott&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;One does not become enlightened by imagining figures of light, but by making the darkness conscious… Until you make the unconscious, conscious, it will rule your life and you will call it Fate.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; ― C.G. Jung&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;It&amp;#39;s impossible to desire something without also fearing it a bit, and it&amp;#39;s impossible to fear and dislike something without also desiring it.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50915816-existential-kink&quot;&gt;Existential Kink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks are highly attuned to their fears, aversions and dislikes, and see all of these as an opportunity for growth. They understand the freedom that comes from acknowledgement of the taboo, the disowned and the repressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of Eros&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: harnessing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/RadicalWomenCommunity/posts/pfbid02xdxph6ZhNqzb4omvz2uFUnzxL5Z9eHARmxkxTh68N5exSWY1R5RbYd4yqhMeFRXRl&quot;&gt;Light/Dark Masculine/Feminine&lt;/a&gt; as explored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ista.life/trainings/ista-level-2&quot;&gt;ISTA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;The DARK FEMININE: sensual pleasure, erotic wisdom, emotional fluidity, and naked authenticity. This energy has a sexual sovereignty, the capacity to attract/magnetize, and the willingness to feel everything, even the most apparently ugly, desperate, and suffering parts of life. The shadow expression is manipulation, power games, chaoticness, vengeance, and emotionally explosive. The stunted version is frigidity (rejection or judgment of sensual and sexual pleasure), and emotionally, physically or sexually detached.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rememberyourself.live/a-brief-introduction-to-the-cross/&quot;&gt;A Brief Introduction to The Cross&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks healthily express all four archetypes of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/RadicalWomenCommunity/posts/pfbid02xdxph6ZhNqzb4omvz2uFUnzxL5Z9eHARmxkxTh68N5exSWY1R5RbYd4yqhMeFRXRl&quot;&gt;dark/light masculine/feminine&lt;/a&gt; cross. In particular, they understand the distinction between &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecross.one/initiation-into-the-feminine-for-women&quot;&gt;evil, shadow and darkness&lt;/a&gt; and have harnessed the dark energies for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of Plants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: plant medicine, especially ayahuasca (&amp;quot;vine of death&amp;quot;) as practised by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://niweraoxobo.com/&quot;&gt;Shipibo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Ayahuasca is not a recreational drug taken for entertainment, relaxation, or escapism. The medicine does not allow us to suppress issues and escape reality. In fact, quite the opposite is typically the case. Ayahuasca compels us to face, resolve, and release issues that have been buried throughout our lives.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://templeofthewayoflight.org/integrating-ayahuasca/facing-your-shadow/&quot;&gt;Temple of the Way of Light&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;The fact that Westerners will seek out a foul-tasting jungle medicine in a faraway environment and culture, a medicine that frequently leads to violent purging and can include terrifying visions, is a remarkable paradox.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://templeofthewayoflight.org/integrating-ayahuasca/facing-your-shadow/&quot;&gt;Ralph Metzner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks are intimately familiar with the healing power of plant medicines, particularly those used in &lt;a href=&quot;https://templeofthewayoflight.org/shamanism-ayahuasca/shipibo-energy-healing/&quot;&gt;night-time ceremonies&lt;/a&gt;. They embrace mystery and approach indigenous wisdom with respect and humility, accepting the possibility of mechanisms not yet understood by science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of the Soul&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/books/soulcraft/&quot;&gt;Soulcraft&lt;/a&gt; by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/&quot;&gt;Animas Valley Institute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;In the course of healthy human development, we are each meant to reach this breakpoint, this crisis, this divide beyond which we’re no longer able to decisively define ourselves in terms of social or romantic relationships, or in terms of a job or career, a creative or artistic project, a political affiliation, a theory or philosophical perspective, a religious or ethnic membership, or a transcendental spiritual goal. We are propelled — compelled! — toward an underworld self-definition, a soul-infused experience of meaning and purpose and identity. True for all humans, this is our evolutionary birthright, a necessary passage on the way from psychological adolescence to true adulthood… The mainstream currents of our contemporary cultures neither assert nor deny the existence of an underworld identity; it has simply disappeared from awareness.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/the-realm-of-purpose-least-realized-but-most-essential-in-our-time-of-radical-global-change/&quot;&gt;Bill Plotkin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks are practitioners of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/books/soulcraft/&quot;&gt;Soulcraft&lt;/a&gt;, seeking to become ever more aware of their unique &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/glossary-to-language-of-soul-canyon/#mythopoetic%20identity&quot;&gt;mythopoetic identity&lt;/a&gt; through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/glossary-to-language-of-soul-canyon/#Descent%20to%20Soul&quot;&gt;Descent to Soul&lt;/a&gt;. Soulcraft practices include dreamwork and deep-imagery journeys, solo ceremonies and exercises while wandering on the land, trance dancing and drumming, council work, storytelling, vision fasts, symbolic artwork, soul-oriented poetry, Shadow work, and communicating with birds, trees, the winds, and the land and waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness in Light&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: Meditations on Emptiness and Dependent Arising as explored in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25172403-seeing-that-frees&quot;&gt;Seeing That Frees&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://tasshin.com/blog/rob-burbea-ordinary-guy-werewolf-eternal-wanderer/&quot;&gt;Rob Burbea&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;They are the same thing, but our lazy mind separates darkness from light. To plunge into the light, to find darkness in light, to find Buddha nature in perfect zazen is our way.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/361898.Branching_Streams_Flow_in_the_Darkness&quot;&gt;Shunryu Suzuki Roshi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through meditative practice, lunarpunks approach the understanding that ultimately, there is no separation between darkness and light – rather, they are &amp;#39;dependently arising&amp;#39; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prat%C4%ABtyasamutp%C4%81da&quot;&gt;paṭiccasamuppāda&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every characterisation of lunarpunk in this piece is simply an opinion (mine), an offering – I make no claim to the right to define the term any more than the next &amp;#39;punk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is clear to me, though, is that lunarpunk existed before web3 and exists beyond it. I hope this piece stimulates useful discussions on holistic and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/age-of-awareness/a-metamodern-guide-to-human-development-49fe8d8f0e8f&quot;&gt;developmentally-focused&lt;/a&gt; notions of both solarpunk and lunarpunk in the web3 space and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scienceandnonduality.com/article/david-bohm-implicate-order-and-holomovement&quot;&gt;May we continue to move towards wholeness&lt;/a&gt;, embracing both dark and light 🌓&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;New blog post – Beyond Privacy: The Seven Darknesses of Lunarpunk:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Darkness of Privacy&lt;br&gt;Darkness of Attention&lt;br&gt;Darkness of Suffering&lt;br&gt;Darkness of Eros&lt;br&gt;Darkness of Plants&lt;br&gt;Darkness of the Soul&lt;br&gt;Darkness in Light&lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/MiGa5vHLF1&quot;&gt;https://t.co/MiGa5vHLF1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Stephen Reid ☯️ (@lunarpunk_0x) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lunarpunk_0x/status/1575970584789295104?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;September 30, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Expanding notions of lunarpunk in web3</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Coach maturity: An emerging concept</title><link href="/blog/2022/08/04/coach-maturity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coach maturity: An emerging concept" /><published>2022-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2022/08/04/coach-maturity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022/08/04/coach-maturity.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidclutterbuckpartnership.com/wp-content/uploads/Coach-maturity.pdf&quot;&gt;Professor David Clutterbuck and Professor David Megginson&lt;/a&gt;. Highlights my own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coaching sometimes seems like Keats’ rainbow – the more we try to define it, dissect it, classify it and demystify it, the more we diminish it and lose its essence. One of the concerns both of us have about so much of the coaching literature is that it represents attempts to confine coaching within the partisan wrappings of a particular school, philosophy or approach. Such narrow and sometimes self-serving perspectives seem to us to be completely at odds with the essential ethos of coaching – &lt;mark&gt;enquiring, open, inclusive, subtle and multi-perspective&lt;/mark&gt;. This perspective has been called ‘relational coaching’ by Erik de Haan and colleagues (de Haan, 2008).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we accept and encourage the notion of quality in coaching, even though we may struggle even more in defining what that, too, means. Ingredients in a definition of quality of coaching might be posited to include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The delivery of intended and positive &lt;mark&gt;unintended&lt;/mark&gt; outcomes. &lt;mark&gt;Simply delivering against the initial, presented goal is not necessarily an indicator of quality&lt;/mark&gt;, for a number of reasons:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The goal may be the wrong one&lt;/mark&gt; for the client and or the organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Achieving goal clarity may be the end point&lt;/mark&gt;, not the beginning of the coaching assignment – &lt;mark&gt;many clients need coaching to establish what they want and why, but are self-sufficient in thinking through how they are going to achieve it&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even coaching at a relatively low level of competence can achieve change in the client. &lt;mark&gt;Simply being there and allowing the client to talk things through can be remarkably effective, where the client needs only to structure their own thinking&lt;/mark&gt;. The primary skills required in such cases are attentive listening and knowing when to shut up!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depth of rapport, which may in turn relate to attentiveness, awareness of one’s own values, and authenticity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energy: Observation of coaches in assessment centre ‘real plays’ suggests that &lt;mark&gt;the most effective coaches create simultaneously an intense stillness and an intense energy field&lt;/mark&gt;. &lt;mark&gt;The space between them and the client almost crackles!&lt;/mark&gt; By contrast, the least effective coaches seem to suck energy from the room, dissipating energy as they flail about seeking to “plug in” to the client and his or her issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A systemic approach to the coaching dynamic. The coaching context extends beyond the individual client to the human and organizational systems, in which they operate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Observations about coaches and coaching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our observations of many coaches in and out of action in the context of coach assessment centers suggests that &lt;mark&gt;it may be easier to define what does not define quality&lt;/mark&gt; – for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Having a certificate or diploma&lt;/mark&gt;. At best this is a hygiene factor, indicating that the coach has undergone some form of training in the role. But rigorous assessment shows that &lt;mark&gt;many “certified” coaches are severely lacking in competence&lt;/mark&gt;, while many of the most effective coaches are “naturals”, who bring to the role a mixture of innate intuitiveness and reflection on experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having individual accreditation. The International Coach Federation, the Association for Coaching, the European Mentoring and Coaching Council and others (Brennan and Whybrow, 2010) have set up systems for individual accreditation. This seeks – more directly than certification – to measure something akin to maturity. However it largely shows that the coach is good enough, rather than how far on a personal journey they have travelled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Client satisfaction. Some clients may over-rate the efficacy of their coaches, confusing empathetic conversation (simply having someone listen to them) with transformational dialogue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fee rates. We have found a variation of 15 to 1 in fees charged per hour, but &lt;mark&gt;no significant correlation with quality of coaching delivered&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our reflections to reconcile the spontaneity, dynamism and variety of coaching with the need to maintain standards lead to the conclusion that simplistic classifications are likely to be divisive and of dubious validity. What’s needed is a conceptual framework that reflects the evolution of complexity in coaches’ way of thinking about themselves, their clients and the context, in which they operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A possible solution may lie in the context of maturity. In the sense of the development of human beings, a number of authors have proposed models of the &lt;mark&gt;evolution of maturity&lt;/mark&gt;. These models broadly assume that changes in the structure of thinking about oneself and the world, with which we interact, &lt;mark&gt;evolve slowly and in recognisable, sequential patterns&lt;/mark&gt;; that &lt;mark&gt;higher levels involve a greater degree of awareness about the individual’s environment, and greater complexity in how they interpret their environment&lt;/mark&gt;; that evolving through one level is an essential precursor to the next; that cognitive and socio-emotional responses at earlier levels may remain open and available, even though the individual’s “centre of gravity” is at a higher level; that people evolve at different rates; and that only a small proportion of the population become centred in the highest levels of maturity. These models tend to emphasize either cognitive-reflective processes or ego-development (Bachkirova and Cox, 2007), meaning “the development of self-identity and maturing of interpersonal relationships”. Key authors here include Torbert (1991), Wilber (2000), Cook-Greuter (2004), Beck &amp;amp; Cowan (1996) and Kegan (1992).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Bachkirova and Cox express it: “What is particularly important in relation to development of coaches is that each stage enriches individual capacity for reflection and effective interaction with others. Their ability to notice nuances and details of situations is increasing. The resultant self-awareness gives them a better opportunity to articulate, influence and potentially change these situations.” Otto Laske (2006, 2009), who has built in particular upon Kegan’s approaches, maintains additionally that in a coaching context the relative maturity of the coach and client are significant in the relationship dynamic. Most importantly, if the coach is less cognitively or socio- emotionally mature than the client, this is likely to have a significant and negative impact on the quality of the coaching process. Chandler and Kram (2005) make a similar point with regard to the related activity of mentoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mindsets and models&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our own interpretations of coach maturity are not based on empirical research, but we hope they will stimulate such research and serve as a starting point for debate. Our model derives from observation in a variety of contexts, but particularly within coach assessment centers, where it is possible to benchmark coaches against consistent criteria, and hence to reflect on characteristics and thinking patterns exhibited by coaches of different levels of demonstrated competence. It is important to emphasise here that we are not equating maturity and competence as the same construct. However, it is reasonable to conclude that they are closely related.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The four levels are models-based, process-based, philosophy or discipline-based, and systemic eclectic.&lt;/mark&gt; &lt;mark&gt;Models-based coaches&lt;/mark&gt; are often very new to the field and seek the re-assurance of a closely defined approach that they can take into any situation they might meet. This type of coaching is characterised by mechanistic conversations, where following the model is more important than exploring the client’s world. It is about doing rather than being and tends to be about coaching to the client than coaching with the client; and about the coaching intervention, rather than the coaching relationship. The dangerous myth that a good coach can coach anyone in any situation appears to stem from this very narrow perception of coaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Process-based approaches&lt;/mark&gt; allow for more flexibility. They can be considered as a structured linking of related techniques and models. The coach has a number of specific tools to use in helping the client’s thinking, but the toolbag is still relatively limited. Solutions focus, for example, assumes that the client’s immediate need is to find a solution, but in practice, many clients simply want to build a greater understanding of their situation and/or to come to terms with a problem that is inherently insoluble. Yet there are many coaching situations where the emotional engagement between coach and client provides the most powerful resource for change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Philosophy or discipline based mindsets&lt;/mark&gt; tend to offer a wider still portfolio of responses to client needs, because they operate within a broad set of assumptions about helping and human development. They can still be applied mechanistically, however. What prevents them being so is the coach’s ability to reflect on his or her practice, both while coaching and after each coaching session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The fourth, most liberating mindset is the systemic eclectic.&lt;/mark&gt; These coaches have a very wide array of ways of working and a toolkit amassed from many sources, both within couching and from very different worlds. They have integrated this into a self- aware, personalized way of being with the client. They exhibit an intelligent, sensitive ability to select a broad approach, and within that approach, appropriate tools and techniques, which meet the particular needs of a particular client at a particular time. This relates to what Webb (2008) calls coaching for wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observation of and discussion with a sample of systemic eclectic coaches suggests that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;They have immense calm, because they have confidence in their ability to find the right tool if they need it&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Yet they hardly ever use tools&lt;/mark&gt;. When they do, it is subtly and integrated almost seamlessly into the conversation. Indeed, they allow the conversation to happen, &lt;mark&gt;holding the client in the development of insight and steering with only the lightest, almost imperceptible touches&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They place great importance on understanding a technique, model or process in terms of its origins within an original philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use experimentation and reflexive learning to identify where and how a new technique, model or process fits into their philosophy and framework of helping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They judge new techniques, models and processes on the criterion of “Will this enrich and improve the effectiveness of my potential responses to client needs?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use peers and supervisors to challenge their coaching philosophy and as partners in experimenting with new approaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They take a systemic and holistic view of the client and the client’s environment; and of the coaching relationship; and this makes them more sensitive to nuances of the situation and hence to what approaches they can employ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1: A comparison of the four levels of coaching maturity in coaching conversations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Coaching approach&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Style&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Critical questions&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Models-based&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Control&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;How do I take them where I think they need to go?&lt;br /&gt;How do I adapt my technique or model to this circumstance?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Process-based&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Contain&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;How do I give enough control to the client and still retain a purposeful conversation?&lt;br /&gt;What’s the best way to apply my process in this instance?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philosophy-based&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Facilitate&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;What can I do to help the client do this for themselves?&lt;br /&gt;How do I contextualise the client’s issue within the perspective of my philosophy or discipline?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Systemic eclectic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Enable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Are we both relaxed enough to allow the issue and the solution to emerge in whatever way they will? &lt;br /&gt;Do I need to apply any techniques or processes at all?&lt;br /&gt;If I do, what does the client context tell me about how to select from the wide choice available to me?&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observation in coach assessment centers gave us the basis for proposing an approach, which does more closely parallel other models of maturation. Areas where mature coaches demonstrate that they have reflected deeply include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personal philosophy of coaching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding of the business context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freedom from the tyranny of the question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they use coach supervision and mentoring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they maintain professional development and integrate learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they identify and manage boundaries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their personal journey as a coach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowing what kind of clients and situations they work best with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding what makes a fully functioning individual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding what makes an effective organisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Personal philosophy of coaching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although ontology has developed specific meaning as a genre of coaching practice, in the more generic sense of coaching as “being about being”, mature coaches tend to reflect more deeply on the nature of the interaction between themselves and their clients. Their reflections lead them to an understanding of this interaction that goes far beyond textbook explanations of the coaching process, whether these derive from models-based, process-based or discipline-based approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They integrate their learning from such sources, with reflection on their experiences with clients, to develop and articulate a unique and personal perspective of the coaching dynamic. Some parallels can be drawn here with Kegan’s stages of adult maturity (1992). Absorbing values and beliefs of others – accepted wisdom – whether consciously or unconsciously, is perhaps typical of Kegan’s level three. As they mature, coaches question these “given” beliefs and begin to develop their own, self-authored perspectives, based on their own experience and reasoning. This suggests Kegan’s level four. &lt;mark&gt;Some go a step further, challenging their own self-focused assumptions, embracing uncertainties and letting go of any sense of needing to exert control over the conversation. For example, they may see coaching as a process of shared meaning making, in which the client’s values and perspectives have equal validity to their own.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Understanding the business context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;One of the most pernicious myths about coaching is that coaches need no contextual knowledge of the client’s world.&lt;/mark&gt; Whether born of self-aggrandizement or a mechanistic view of coaching, this is manifestly untrue, on two counts – client safety (and hence ethicality) and efficacy. In sports coaching, it is important to know enough to ensure that the client is not led to adopt behaviors, which might be detrimental to themselves. Similarly in the business world, a coach working with top managers, who has poor knowledge of corporate governance rules, poses a risk both to the client and to him or herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an efficacy perspective, the coach has to have enough contextual knowledge first to demonstrate empathy and build rapport and credibility with the client. Secondly, construct questions that stimulate significant insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coach assessment observations show clearly that the most effective coaches ask questions and make supportive comments that demonstrate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A broad understanding of the client’s world (not necessarily of the client’s specific job role or function)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of the “big themes” affecting the organization and the industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An ability to link day-to-day issues for the client with these big themes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Of course, having too close an understanding of the client’s world also has its downsides. In particular, it leads the coach instinctively to come up with their own answers and suppressing these may divert attention from listening to the client.&lt;/mark&gt; Mature coaches work to give up a directive, “I’ve been there” approach. &lt;mark&gt;It seems, from observation, that the most effective coaches are often those, who have enough knowledge to contextualize questions, yet are able to maintain a deep, curious and constructive naiveté.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Freedom from the tyranny of the question&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systemic eclectic coaches give themselves permission to do less, with resultant great efficacy. In classroom experiments, we have artificially limited the number of times coaches can speak, to only once in every 10 minutes, on average. In almost all cases, coaches’ and coachees’ perception of the quality of the dialogue and, in particular, of the questions asked, is higher than under normal conditions. &lt;mark&gt;Our observation of systemic eclectics is that they are almost miserly with their questions, giving the client maximum time for reflection before they will nudge them gently along in their thinking.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Use of coach supervision or mentoring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although all the major coaching professional bodies require member coaches to have some form of coach supervision or mentoring, remarkably few coaches seem to have developed a mental model that embraces supervision as a core activity in their practice. For many, it appears to be a tick the box requirement, with little proactivity and little practical relevance to their development as coaches. Peer coaching, in particular, can become a collusive, self-congratulatory activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have very little evidence with regard to how coaches at different levels of maturity approach supervision, but we can posit that there might be differences in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they choose their coach supervisor or mentor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The psychological contract they have with their supervisor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they decide what to take to supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they prepare for supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they reflect upon supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they ensure the quality of the supervision they receive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their awareness of specific changes that have happened in them and their practice as a result of coach supervision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We suspect – but do not yet have evidence to support – that &lt;mark&gt;mature coaches would tend to have more developed, more proactive approaches to coach supervision and mentoring.&lt;/mark&gt; Certainly, in assessment centers, more mature coaches tend to give clearer, more specific responses to all of the seven issues above. From comments by systemic eclectics, we glean a number of possible differentiators, which include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sense of needing to be challenged fundamentally by supervision – and hence to &lt;mark&gt;choose supervisors, whose background and perspective is dissimilar to their own&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The use of more than one supervisor, to provide different perspectives and challenges – for example, &lt;mark&gt;one with a strong formal psychological background and one with a deeper business background&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration of supervision and self-supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Personal development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What might a mature approach towards self-development as a coach look like? Based on a small sample of systemic eclectics, they might exhibit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Openness to a wide spectrum of learning opportunities – reading, exploration with peers, supervision, conferences, workshops and so on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-coaching – proposing insightful questions to themselves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Networked learning – building around them a network of peers, who bring different perspectives but a similar dedication to learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engagement with research and/or development of the profession – for example, using writing as a vehicle for self-discovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Boundaries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be a psychologist to recognise phenomena such as projection, dependency or sociopathy. But you do need at least some understanding of psychological and behavioural processes. Assessment centres have, however, revealed some very dangerous coaches, who have little appreciation of boundaries. For example, the coach, who claimed to have done 4000 hours of coaching, but could not think of a single occasion when he had met a boundary issue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Your personal journey as a coach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common to all theories of maturity is a sense of progression. Inherent in the concept of wisdom is the use of reflection to raise awareness of both current and precursor states. Integral to the assessment centre design is a description of the coach’s learning journey – how they make current sense of their evolution towards their current level of practice. &lt;mark&gt;For many, the learning journey appears to have begun and ended with a certificate or other formal recognition as a coach.&lt;/mark&gt; Their practical experience with clients has largely reinforced the “given” knowledge, rather than inspired them to question it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further along the maturity spectrum, we extrapolate, coaches are able to articulate critical shifts in their awareness of themselves as coaches, of the coach-client relationship and of the coaching process. A little further along again, they are able to describe – albeit often with hesitancy – where the journey appears to be taking them. It seems that, as with other maturity models, they are aware that the centre of gravity of their maturity level is shifting and they are searching for client opportunities, insights and pivotal conversations that will assist that movement, even if their vision of where it will take them is still somewhat hazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Knowing who they work best with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;It is arguable that all coaches are better suited to some clients and situations than others.&lt;/mark&gt; Key factors here may be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether transfer (of knowledge/expertise) is an important dynamic in the role&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The client’s perceptions (rightly or wrongly) about the importance of the coach’s background and experience either inside or outside the context of coaching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The depth of psychological/ behavioural competence required to help the client understand their issues and maintain client safety&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The perceived relative status of coach and client.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coaches bring different kinds of life experience, and corporate buyers tend to place a higher value on coaches who have client credibility by virtue of their own experience at senior executive level. (However, assessment center data suggest that a high level of experience in management, when not accompanied by a high level of coaching maturity, represents poor value for money and may sometimes do more harm than good.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conception of a fully functioning person&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many coaches Rogers’ (1961) conception of a fully functioning person may describe the coach’s perception of what it means to be human. Many ex-executives have a much more business–like model. Whatever model one has, it is useful to articulate it, so that clients know where the coach is coming from and the coach realises that views or hints about what the client might do or aspire to, come from a position rather than appearing out of thin air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Making the transition to a system eclectic coach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can and do coaches mature into systemic eclectics? One ingredient is likely to be time. Malcolm Gladwell (2008) summarises research into exceptional performance in a range of activities from business to sport and suggests that it takes 10,000 hours to achieve mastery in any field. Certainly, all the systemic eclectics we have observed have been involved with coaching – or with related disciplines – for a good many years. &lt;mark&gt;But putting in the hours does not automatically create mastery – there has additionally to be an immense amount of reflection, experimentation and adaption of practice.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For systemic eclectics, we observe that the learning they acquire shows them how much more they could learn. It’s like climbing a mountain – the higher you ascend, the bigger and more distant the horizon. Feeling comfortable with this diminishing perspective of one’s own importance and competence relative to what might conceivably be possible, requires a great deal of personal maturity, we suspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is one characteristic of systemic eclectics, which can potentially be learned and used by coaches at any level of maturity – and can possibly speed the transition between levels – it is this ability to savour where you are, to contextualise it and to be able to look both forwards and backwards along the path. Accepting and valuing your current state may be the critical component in achieving the next level of maturity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Defining quality in coaching</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An introduction to platform co-ops</title><link href="/blog/2020/11/22/an-introduction-to-platform-coops.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An introduction to platform co-ops" /><published>2020-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/11/22/an-introduction-to-platform-coops</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/11/22/an-introduction-to-platform-coops.html">&lt;h2&gt;What does &amp;#39;platform&amp;#39; mean here?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The word ‘platform’ is often used to describe &lt;mark&gt;an internet service which brings together suppliers and consumers in an online marketplace&lt;/mark&gt;. But platforms don’t necessarily provide traditional ‘products’; they often facilitate the trade of services, like taxis or temporary accommodation. Most people have heard of Uber and Airbnb, whose platforms have disrupted the minicab and short-term lettings industries while generating enormous profits for their shareholders.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.coop/2016/12/02/introduction-platform-co-ops/&quot;&gt;An introduction to platform co-ops&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Platform capitalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The rise of the platform economy over the last decade promised to boost flexible employment, extra income, and collaborative consumption. Instead, &lt;mark&gt;the ‘disruption’ of the digital economy has removed regulations, increased precariousness of work, and created the conditions for market monopolies dominated by a handful of digital giants&lt;/mark&gt;.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uk.coop/start-new-co-op/support/start-platform-co-op/why-platform-co-ops&quot;&gt;Why platform co-ops?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;More and more people are organising their work and resources through digital platforms. The marketplace for these is dominated by a small number of large corporations: be it Uber drivers, freelancers on TaskRabbit or Amazon’s Mechanical Turk marketplace, home rentals on Airbnb or food deliveries using Deliveroo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These digital platforms offer people unprecedented flexibility and independence. The barriers to entry to becoming a taxi driver, a holiday apartment landlord, or freelance worker are now incredibly low, and it’s never been easier to be a consumer on the other side of these markets. But while these positives are acknowledged, &lt;mark&gt;large platform companies have also been criticised for being exploitative, monopolistic and extractivist&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, this system has been described as &lt;mark&gt;platform capitalism&lt;/mark&gt;. &lt;mark&gt;In this system a large number of consumers and vendors generate profits which accrue to a comparatively small number of people&lt;/mark&gt;… Ordinary users who rely on these platforms typically find they have little control over their personal data and have no say about how they are run. It has led to the formation of monopolies that encourage financial extraction and the monetisation of personal data.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://media.nesta.org.uk/documents/Nesta_Platform_Report_FINAL-WEB_b1qZGj7.pdf&quot;&gt;Platform co-operatives – solving the capital conundrum&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Why we need platform co-operatives in the digital economy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is a platform co-op?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;A platform cooperative, or platform co-op, is &lt;mark&gt;a cooperatively owned, democratically governed business that establishes a computing platform, and uses a website, mobile app or a protocol to facilitate the sale of goods and services&lt;/mark&gt;. Platform cooperatives are an alternative to venture capital-funded platforms insofar as they are owned and governed by those who depend on them most—workers, users, and other relevant stakeholders.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/12/20/8309&quot;&gt;Platform and Data Co-Operatives Amidst European Pandemic Citizenship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;A platform co-op is a &lt;mark&gt;digital platform&lt;/mark&gt; that is designed to provide a service or sell a product, and that is &lt;mark&gt;collectively owned and governed&lt;/mark&gt; by the people who depend on and participate in it.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://media.nesta.org.uk/documents/Nesta_Platform_Report_FINAL-WEB_b1qZGj7.pdf&quot;&gt;Platform co-operatives – solving the capital conundrum&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The origins of platform co-operatives&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Just like traditional co-ops, platform co-ops are organisations that are owned and managed by their members. &lt;mark&gt;While traditional co-ops are normally based around a physical community of members, platform co-ops live online and are normally populated by online communities of members&lt;/mark&gt;.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.coop/2016/12/02/introduction-platform-co-ops/&quot;&gt;An introduction to platform co-ops&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Two types of co-op, as platforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Worker co-ops&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;A workers’ co-op [is] a business owned and managed collectively by its workers for their mutual benefit. It’s organised democratically and fairly by (and only by) its members.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seedsforchange.org.uk/workersco-ops.pdf&quot;&gt;Seeds for Change: How to set up a Workers' Co-op&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Stocksy United: a platform worker co-op where the members are individuals&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stocksy.com/&quot;&gt;Stocksy United&lt;/a&gt; provides curated stock photography and video footage with almost 1000 photographer member-owners, across 63 countries. The members license creative content and receive 50% royalties on standard license sales and 75% on extended license sales – they also receive dividends which equated to $300,000 in 2016 on $10.7m in sales.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Up &amp;amp; Go: a platform worker co-op where the members are organisations (a platform consortia)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.upandgo.coop/&quot;&gt;Up &amp;amp; Go&lt;/a&gt; is a platform that offers on-demand cleaning services at guaranteed fair wages launched by four worker co-operatives, based in New York City. The worker-owned cleaning businesses, which are all majority women owned, earn 95% of the cost of every Up &amp;amp; Go cleaning job. The remaining 5% supports the costs to maintain the platform.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Multi-stakeholder co-ops&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;mark&gt;Multi-stakeholder cooperatives are co-ops that formally allow for governance by representatives of two or more “stakeholder” groups within the same organization, including consumers, producers, workers, volunteers or general community supporters&lt;/mark&gt;. Rather than being organized around a single class of members the way that most cooperatives are, multi-stakeholder cooperatives enjoy a heterogeneous membership base. The common mission that is the central organizing principle of a multi-stakeholder cooperative is also generally broader than the kind of mission statement needed to capture the interests and benefits of only a single stakeholder group, and will often reflect the interdependence of interests of each stakeholder group in its articulation.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;mark&gt;Rather than being organised around a single class of members the way that most co-operatives are, a multi-stakeholder co-operative is any co-op that draws its membership from two or more different classes of stakeholders&lt;/mark&gt;. After two decades of local experimentation, Italy was the first country to adopt a multi-stakeholder statute in 1991. Over 14,000 ‘social co-ops’ now exist across Italy and provide social care, health and educational services to over 5 million people. In Quebec, home to one of the most productive and vibrant co-operative development sectors in the world, multi-stakeholder co-ops are now the fastest growing type of co-op, with more than 50% of all new co-ops opting to register what they refer to as ‘Solidarity Coops.’ The movement is just getting here in the UK, but there are now over 20 multi-stakeholder co-ops who have incorporated using the Somerset Rules.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.p2pfoundation.net/Multi-Stakeholder_Cooperatives&quot;&gt;Multi-Stakeholder Cooperatives - P2P Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;mark&gt;Multi-stakeholder cooperatives present a departure in ownership structure from the more familiar consumer-owned and worker-owned co-ops. Also known as solidarity co-ops, hybrid co-ops or social co-ops, multi-stakeholder cooperatives welcome a variety of groups to become owners, including employees, producers, customers and clients, and community members (including investors).&lt;/mark&gt; These co-ops may appear to operate similarly to corporations, but as Shareable’s David Boiler points out, while they have “a keen focus on profit and loss, social co-ops are committed to meeting social goals such as healthcare, eldercare, social services, and workforce integration for former prisoners. They are able to blend market activity with social services provisioning and democratic participation, all in one swoop.”&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainableconsumption.usdn.org/initiatives-list/multi-stakeholder-cooperatives&quot;&gt;Multi-stakeholder co-operatives - USDN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Multi-stakeholder platform co-ops&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://resonate.is/&quot;&gt;Resonate&lt;/a&gt; is a stream-to-own music platform harnessing blockchain technology. It is a multi-stakeholder co-operative giving democratic control to artists (45%), listeners (35%) and workers (20%). Through its model, it pays up to 2.5 times more revenue to artists than other streaming services.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://equalcare.coop/&quot;&gt;Equal Care Co-op&lt;/a&gt; are building a new, co-owned social care platform that puts care givers and receivers in charge. By incorporating as a multi-stakeholder co-operative, their digital product and accompanying service is owned by and accountable to the communities using and sustaining it. They arrived at the platform co-op model as a response to systemic inequities within the social care system, seeing it as a practical route to centering choice, power and ownership with the two most important people in care – the person giving and the person getting support.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/equal-care.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;table table-bordered text-sm&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
     &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Supported member:&lt;/strong&gt; You are being regularly supported by Equal Care Co-op (whether that's voluntary or paid support)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Advocate member:&lt;/strong&gt; Your relative or friend is being supported by Equal Care Co-op but they cannot be a Member themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;    
     &lt;strong&gt;Investor member: &lt;/strong&gt;You support our aims and have invested in our Community Share Offer.&lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;
     &lt;strong&gt;Worker member: &lt;/strong&gt;You are regularly contributing your labour to Equal Care Co-op, whether that's paid or voluntary work.&lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Somerset Rules: creating multi-stakeholder co-ops in the UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;mark&gt;Launched in 2009, the Somerset Rules were one of the UK’s first set of model rules for a multi-stakeholder co-op, and they’re arguably still the best.&lt;/mark&gt; Packed full of best practice gleaned from decades of co-operative development experience, they’re structured to closely follow co-op principles, written in relatively plain English, and are cleverly drafted to allow for a wide range of different configurations. You can define the percentage of overall control each stakeholder group has. They are also ‘social accounting ready’ and are designed to enable the widest range of options for financing. In 2012 they were fully revised and overhauled and a version for use as a Community Interest Company limited by guarantee was developed.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.p2pfoundation.net/Somerset_Rules&quot;&gt;P2P Foundation: Somerset Rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Check out the latest version at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.somerset.coop/p/somerset-rules-registrations.html&quot;&gt;Somerset Rules registrations&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Graphic guides&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ia601506.us.archive.org/16/items/platform-cooperativism_graphic-individual-letter-size-pages/platform-cooperativism_graphic-individual-letter-size-pages.pdf&quot;&gt;Introduction to platform co-ops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ia601506.us.archive.org/16/items/platform-cooperativism_graphic-individual-letter-size-pages/platform-cooperativism_graphic-individual-letter-size-pages.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/intro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uk.coop/start-new-co-op/support/start-platform-co-op/why-platform-co-ops&quot;&gt;Why platform co-ops?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uk.coop/start-new-co-op/support/start-platform-co-op/why-platform-co-ops&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/unfound.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Prepared as part of the Platform Co-ops Now! course</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Psychedelics and the Living Planet</title><link href="/blog/2020/11/18/psychedelics-and-the-living-planet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Psychedelics and the Living Planet" /><published>2020-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/11/18/psychedelics-and-the-living-planet</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/11/18/psychedelics-and-the-living-planet.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If the self is expanded to include the natural world, behavior leading to destruction of this world will be experienced as self-destruction.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Psychology as if the Whole Earth Mattered, Harvard Center for Psychology and Social Change, 199&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I gave a talk on the topic &lt;strong&gt;Psychedelics and the Living Planet&lt;/strong&gt; to the Cambridge Psychedelic Society. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Oz55NNRzOyNFHH-jz87G9PaPJhfief00rsHE3QsTojM/edit#&quot;&gt;You can check out the notes I used here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Notes from a talk I gave to the Cambridge Psychedelic Society</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Compassion and trust are the ultimate anti-viruses of Wetiko</title><link href="/blog/2020/10/19/searching-for-the-anti-virus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Compassion and trust are the ultimate anti-viruses of Wetiko" /><published>2020-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/10/19/searching-for-the-anti-virus</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/10/19/searching-for-the-anti-virus.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tamera.org/martin-winiecki/&quot;&gt;Martin Winiecki&lt;/a&gt;, first published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kosmosjournal.org/kj_article/searching-for-the-anti-virus-covid-19-as-quantum-phenomenon/&quot;&gt;Kosmos Journal&lt;/a&gt;. Highlights my own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve struggled to make sense of what is going on. My suspicious mind wandered around restlessly, examining all theories and possible explanations, yet I must admit: I don’t know what is happening. I do know this is a crucial moment of choice for humanity. In this essay, I will not suggest or discuss “what is going on.” I rather want to invite you into a realm transcending the dichotomy of “objective reality” vs “subjective thoughts/feelings,” which underlies most theories, predictions and calls to action in this crisis. &lt;mark&gt;Coming from a spiritually-informed holistic worldview, I entertain the possibility that we as humanity – or some deeper part of ourselves, whether conscious or not – have dreamed this moment into existence as a catalyst for our collective evolution.&lt;/mark&gt; If that were true, how might we engage and respond? Covid-19 could actually present an unlikely possibility for collective awakening and far-reaching system change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Neither real nor unreal, but dreamlike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This place is a dream. Only a sleeper considers it real. Then death comes like dawn, and you wake up laughing at what you thought was your grief.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Rumi&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For over a hundred years, physicists and philosophers have tried to wrap their heads around the manifold wonders of quantum physics. Subatomic entities, such as electrons, they saw, behave in awe-striking and magical ways. They do not simply exist “as such,” as fixed and finished entities; they can appear as a wave in one instant or as a particle in another, depending on whether or not they are observed. This is true. &lt;mark&gt;Our perception of the world isn’t just passive, it is creative – it literally in-forms its very being and reality. Quantum physics invites us into a view of reality in which the seeming “objective” reality out there and the “subjective” experience “in here” become inseparably intertwined.&lt;/mark&gt; Just as the characters and events in dreams aren’t separate from the dreamer, the world, according to the great psychoanalyst Carl Jung, is but a living symbol, the embodiment of deeper parts of ourselves, which we collectively dream into existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing reality in this way, how would we make sense of Covid-19?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through spiritual experiences and studies, I’ve learned that &lt;mark&gt;diseases rarely appear for no reason. They often carry deeper messages&lt;/mark&gt;. For example, conflicts, longings, and vital drives our minds suppress may resurface in bodily symptoms. &lt;mark&gt;Healing often occurs in the moment we realize what we have suppressed.&lt;/mark&gt; Such insights have the possibility to make us more whole and may, in fact, change our lives. In this way, we can say the healing antidote – or, in this case, the anti-virus – lies hidden within the disease as the treasure of transformative realization. &lt;mark&gt;If we exclusively fight the symptoms without exploring the deeper root, we might survive the disease but other symptoms are still likely to materialize.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is true for an individual disease may also be true for epidemic or pandemic outbreaks. In his provocative book, Selbstzerstörung aus Verlassenheit [Self-Destruction due to Abandonment], the psychotherapist Franz Renggli ascribes the outbreak of the Great Plague in Christian Europe in the 14th century, which killed 30%–60% of the continent’s population, to an “eruption of mass psychosis.” He writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My psycho- or rather socio-somatic model is psycho-neuro-immunology: neither a bacterium nor a virus is the core problem, but rather the people within a society who have been shaken by a crisis. &lt;mark&gt;If this crisis lasts too long, is too severe or too traumatic, the immune system of the population is slowly weakened and finally collapses.&lt;/mark&gt; The people become vulnerable to illnesses and finally to death. This model is valid for any epidemic and can serve as a key for a new understanding of history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the century preceding the Black Death, he argues, the Catholic Church began advising mothers to separate from their babies during day and night. Children growing up in the 13th and 14th centuries thus suffered a collective trauma of primal abandonment. Renggli shows that regions in which mothers continued to practice close physical contact with their children were spared from the plague. Might we be experiencing something similar right now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;How has the specter of Covid-19 been able to haunt 7.5 billion people and bring the world to a standstill in no time at all? Because the narrative massively resonates with something latent that is both teeming and deeply suppressed in people’s subconscious.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “mental” coronavirus spread earlier, faster and much more powerfully than its biological counterpart. Covid-19 began to make headlines and &lt;mark&gt;people suddenly found an “objective” justification for the fear and despair which had been gathering unconsciously within them for a long time. The feedback loop between the hourly onslaught of fear-inducing headlines in the media and the growing anxious expectations in people’s minds trapped humanity in a vicious neurotic cycle.&lt;/mark&gt; Every new “case” in our neighborhood or region, every cough in the subway, every stranger coming too close doubled-down on an eerie sense of ubiquitous danger. The more we think about illness, the more afraid we are. The more fear we experience, the weaker our immune system gets. The weaker our immune system, the more likely we’ll develop symptoms. Try not to think of a pink elephant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The psycho-spiritual dimension has been proven to have a very concrete effect on the material realm. The astonishingly far-reaching physical impacts of the placebo effect are well documented, and likewise, many studies show how emotional stress, chronic fear and loneliness can dangerously weaken our immune system and corrode our health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Please bear with me. I’m not suggesting Covid-19 is just a hoax, nor am I trying to downplay or deny the tragedy so many people are experiencing.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m suggesting we look at it from a different angle: What if Covid-19 weren’t a danger independent from our minds and souls but, in fact, a quantum phenomenon – &lt;mark&gt;a shared dream character we’ve collectively summoned into existence?&lt;/mark&gt; An embodiment of something buried deeply in the realms of the collective subconscious that we haven’t, so far, been able to comprehend? &lt;mark&gt;A living symbol of a much deeper infection?&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mind viruses and the magic of fear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching back to the oral traditions of several First Nations, Native American scholar Jack D. Forbes writes in Columbus and Other Cannibals, “For several thousands of years human beings have suffered from a plague, a disease worse than leprosy, a sickness worse than malaria, a malady much more terrible than smallpox.” The Algonquin and other Indigenous First Nations identified the mental illness of the white man, upon his arrival to their native homelands in the 15th and 16th centuries, as “&lt;mark&gt;Wetiko&lt;/mark&gt;,” literally translating as cannibalism: &lt;mark&gt;“the consuming of another’s life for [one’s] own private purpose or profit.”&lt;/mark&gt; Forbes concludes by saying, &lt;mark&gt;“This disease is the greatest epidemic sickness known to man.”&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wetiko – often referred to as a mind virus – propagates the deep-seated illusion of seeing oneself desperately confined to the cage of a separated ego. From this perspective of isolation, others appear either as competitors or as prey. In a worldview in which fear is the basic condition, fight and exploitation seem rational, empathy ridiculous and sentimental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;After 5000 years of patriarchy, 500 years of capitalism and 50 years of neoliberalism, Wetiko has come to define nearly every area of our (Western) world and lives.&lt;/mark&gt; The reason we can accept an economic system celebrating the biggest-possible devastation of the natural world as “success” is due to our own infection with the virus. &lt;mark&gt;Wetiko has numbed our hearts, blurring our ability to perceive both the sacredness and the pain of life, both outside and inside ourselves. Innumerable beings are perishing due to this chronic inability to feel empathy.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the compulsive fixation on maximizing artificial values in the economy all the way down to the pandemic of broken and abusive love relationships, &lt;mark&gt;the Wetiko sickness has become so normalized it’s no longer even recognized as such&lt;/mark&gt;. A miserable cult of self-obsession has eroded the social tissue of humanity and desecrated the Earth. As a result, fear is everywhere – fear of abandonment, fear of death, fear of life, fear of sexuality, fear of punishment, fear of the coming collapse… &lt;mark&gt;The benign front of bourgeois decency conceals a psychological basement in which the children of fear roam freely: permanent anger, general mistrust, addiction, depression, boredom, perversion, compulsive consumption and control and the secret or open fascination with violence.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 narrative has been able to infect humanity at such record speed because fear is so deep-seated and unconscious in humanity that we’re no longer aware of what is happening within us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragedy is that the virus operates in the shadows of our consciousness. We infect ourselves and others unknowingly. As Forbes writes, we’re conditioned by the disease through “authoritarian family structures,” “male dominance,” “subjugating women” and “extremely negative attitudes towards sex” – and on an ideological level, through “notions of racial and cultural superiority.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once stuck in this box, we mindlessly perpetuate the disease in our day-to-day interactions, by feeding off and into each other’s blind spots and pain points. As we project what we fear internally onto others or external events, we validate our fear while suppressing where it comes from. We believe danger to be outside of us, so we try to protect ourselves from it and, thereby, often act in ways that perpetuate the very danger we try to protect ourselves from. Jung describes this mechanism as “shadow projection.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the extent we’re unconsciously driven by fear, we become susceptible to manipulation. &lt;mark&gt;When millions of people project their unconscious shadows onto others, they conjure up the very danger everyone is trying to escape from.&lt;/mark&gt; Wilhelm Reich made these dynamics explicit during the rise of Hitler (see his 1933 book, The Mass Psychology of Fascism) and they’re the premise of all totalitarian regimes to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 9/11, we were told that our enemy was the Muslim world; now the “enemy” is invisible and might await us at every door handle, or creep into us as we kiss, hug or even breathe. The more extravagant the neurotic cinema that’s playing in our minds, the easier it is for external powers to control and use us for their interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The great unveiling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much more than just a difficult trial for humanity, the Covid-19 outbreak also holds the possibility for collective healing from the predatory mass infection of Wetiko. We can make sense of it as a global somatization – or symbolic simulation – of the underlying Wetiko disease. As with every outbreak of severe disease, the deeper patterns are now coming unstuck in plain sight at the global level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’re now witnessing a simultaneous unveiling, breakdown and intense exaggeration of Wetiko:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On an ecological level, Covid-19 originated as a direct result of our civilization’s insatiable greed for exponential growth. Probably wild animals transmitted the virus to people after the natural ecosystems which were home to them were destroyed by the ecocidal steamroller of civilizational “progress.” And now we’re equally astonished to see how quickly the air can clear in China, the speed at which wildlife returns to urban areas, and how suddenly old ecocidal endeavors collapse before our eyes (e.g. the S. fracking industry).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On an economic level, Covid-19 has been the straw that’s broken the camel’s back, setting off the chain reaction of a long overdue financial collapse. The lockdown has sent our globalized economy into a full-blown, rapid “evaporation,” with entire industries halting, millions of workers being laid off from one day to the next and stock markets crashing. The fossil fuel industry faces its “gravest challenge in its 100-year history,” from which it may never recover. The Federal Reserves are currently lending big banks an additional $1 trillion a day, which is to say, we’re now barely keeping the economic system on life support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the social and psychological levels, we see both a collective frenzy of extreme Wetiko behaviors and also many people breaking free. On one hand, social atomization, the desire for control and egoistic panic are reaching surreal pinnacles. We are seeing a massive surge in domestic abuse and the rapid conversion of liberal societies into police states; even leftists are praising the strengthening of top-down government and restrictions on civil liberties. On the other hand, thousands of local grassroots initiatives practicing mutual aid have popped up from one day to the next. Millions are entering a rare moment of reflection and of asking “what’s essential?” While locked down in quarantine, we’re confronted with ourselves, our longings and our lives. And &lt;mark&gt;many recognize how deeply we’ve been “socially distanced” all along&lt;/mark&gt; – divided up by the competitive ideals of a precarious labor market and our own inability to engage in authentic interpersonal connection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A parting of ways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will happen next is uncertain, but we can predict that the chain reaction of economic devastation may be inevitable. The global emergency may have come to stay. In other words, &lt;mark&gt;we may not go back to normal anytime soon, or perhaps ever again.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will happen in the next few weeks and months will likely shape the world for many years to come. Rather than resisting the forces of entropy and indulging in faint hopes of a return to normality, &lt;mark&gt;the future will be on the side of those who are able to embrace chaos and disruption as an opportunity to propose a different vision for global society.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naomi Klein, author of The Shock Doctrine, says: “If there is one thing history teaches us, it’s that moments of shock are profoundly volatile. We either lose a whole lot of ground, get fleeced by elites, and pay the price for decades, or we win progressive victories that seemed impossible just a few weeks earlier. This is no time to lose our nerve.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burdened by astronomical debt and commanded by the imperative for exponential growth, the globalized capitalist system has come to an irreversible breaking point. The powers that be will either have to make way for system change or will stubbornly continue to prop up the old order with ever-more brutal force. While there may be many possible futures in front of us, I want to highlight the stark contrast of the historic choice we’re facing, in two contrasting future scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario #1: Surveillance capitalism&lt;/strong&gt;
After many months of lockdown, people have accepted the new era of quarantined existence. Governments have dismantled civil liberties, human rights and environmental protections and, under the pretext of health and safety, deployed unprecedented levels of surveillance technology. Mobile apps are used not only to track people’s physical movements but also their biochemical reactions. As Gideon Lichfield writes, “intrusive surveillance [is] considered a small price to pay for the basic freedom to be with other people.” In the background of a daily onslaught of fear-invoking messages, governments further redistribute wealth from the bottom 99% to the elites. Banks, fossil fuel and airline industries are bailed out with taxpayer’s money, while social security and public health systems are further dismantled. Austerity measures and the abolition of cash further marginalize working people, the poor and the homeless. General apathy and numbness have reached a dimension where the daily shooting of migrants at the borders and other atrocities no longer provoke any moral outcry. Locked into their flats, afraid of infection, monitored by digital body sensors, the powers that be have almost entirely crippled people’s ability to organize themselves and resist. Should protests or strikes still occur, the mass media can report on new dangerous infections spreading so that governments can swiftly impose new curfews to “keep our communities safe.” At some point, with climate breakdown, water crises and food shortages worsening, the system is no longer able to disguise its collapse. Chaos and violence can no longer be contained. The rich retreat to their gated compounds in remote areas, while masses of people find themselves trapped in disintegrating urban centers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario #2: Ecological and social emancipation&lt;/strong&gt;
In the months of uncertainty and economic disintegration, millions of people begin to organize themselves at the local grassroots levels to cover their basic needs. In this time of hardship, they rediscover the power of community, solidarity and localism. As people help each other through sickness and challenge, a spirit of empathy and interdependence spreads. After many months of unemployment, public chaos and food shortages, hopes for strong government and a return to normality have finally faded. &lt;mark&gt;Many realize that either we live out collapse alone or we get through this together.&lt;/mark&gt; The emergency initiatives of neighborhood aid now turn into more long-term initiatives of social, economic and ecological re-organization. People start collective gardens and food cooperatives to supply themselves with local organic crops and open solar energy task forces to decentralize and democratize their energy supply. More and more people leave the cities to found communities in the countryside, where they engage in restoring ecosystems and radical social experimentation for a more trust-based and loving way of living. People work together with progressive governments on large-scale ecological rehabilitation in response to the climate crisis, while governments support citizens’ agency through introducing Universal Basic Income. In the background of this astonishing social and ecological movement, a profound cultural and spiritual transformation takes place – a shift of consciousness from the Wetiko drive for domination to cooperation with all living beings, from atomizing mass societies to communities of trust, from the patriarchal condemnation of Eros and the feminine to a culture that celebrates sensual love in its freedom and dignity, from subduing the Earth to honoring her inherent sacredness, from fearing death to acknowledging our eternal existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;System change: the time is now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dangers of totalitarianism are dire and real and are becoming concretized in many countries already. But we mustn’t forget that those measures are the last resort in prolonging the death of a system that’s already on its way out. &lt;mark&gt;At this point, globalized capitalism is only being kept alive by our fearful projections and our inability to imagine something new, which is to say, if people can leave fear behind and unify around a shared vision of the future they want, nothing can stop the inevitable transition.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see the keys to system change lying in three essential realms of our lives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The spiritual sphere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having exaggerated Wetiko to unthinkably surreal heights, Covid-19 strangely invites us into a dimensional shift of being. As Paul Levy, the author of Dispelling Wetiko, maintains, the anti-virus hidden within the Wetiko disease is the awakening to its dream-like nature – a realization which has the potential to radically change our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we continue to react to the embodiments of Wetiko outside of us (e.g. viruses, external enemies or the dangers of totalitarianism…) as if they were separate from us, we will continue to act in ways that feed the very dynamic we’re afraid of. But if we begin to see Wetiko playing out within ourselves, it loses its grip on us. Compassion opens our eyes to understanding that which we previously could only fear, judge or hate. Trust reconciles us with the world and our fellow beings. &lt;mark&gt;Compassion and trust are the ultimate anti-viruses of Wetiko.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may suddenly wake up and realize how all systems of domination have never been “real” as such, their “reality” has always only existed through our consent. &lt;mark&gt;Money, authority, society, pandemics – we can now see the dreamlike nature of what we believed to be rock-solid and unchangeable.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To awaken from the fearful web of Wetiko is to simultaneously awaken to the interdependent web of Life. This is such a profound shift from where we come from in the Western world that it’s hard to even find words for it. The fear-stricken mind always asks for immediate conclusions, solutions, fixes. But maybe there is no such “fix” right now. Maybe, what this moment calls for is for us to let go of all our notions of self-importance, superiority and domination and to surrender to a greater-than-human intelligence and guidance, to inquire for orientation from the Earth and the Indigenous wisdom of cultures centered around the Earth. In this experience of communion lies a truth that is unambiguous, absolute and deeply healing: &lt;mark&gt;all life is sacred&lt;/mark&gt;. This isn’t only a private experience, but an insight into the inherent matrix of Life. In alignment with this matrix we stand outside the vicious cycles of fear, infection and violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The social sphere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Wetiko plays out relationally, its dissolution is a collective endeavor; a historic project of developing ways of living together in which we can heal our broken relationship to the Earth and each other, and develop deep trust among ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build trust, we need conditions which no longer force us to lie, disguise or protect ourselves. We need ways of living, loving, working and relating in which we can truly recognize each other and dare to show what we actually think and feel, love and desire. “Trust” is a word often used, but what does it mean in the delicate realms of our souls, such as love, sexuality and spirituality, where our vulnerabilities tend to be the greatest? This entails nothing short of a social revolution. Dieter Duhm, a mentor and teacher of mine, and author of The Sacred Matrix, writes, “Trust is not only classified as psychological; it is above all a political term – the most revolutionary of all – for &lt;mark&gt;we need to renew the entire societal structure to bring about sustainable, systemic trust&lt;/mark&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This revolution may not occur in mass movements immediately, but it can begin in small groups – wells of coherence – and extend across society from there, by virtue of raising a new field of consciousness. Based on 40 years of radical experimentation, the “Healing Biotopes Plan” offers a respective vision for such comprehensive transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The political and economic sphere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freedom in the long-term requires our capacity to resist any restriction to civil and human rights in the short-term. In this time of social distancing, let us stand in solidarity together, especially with all those who are marginalized, rejecting any narrative of “us versus them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the globalized system crumbles, localization will be the key to the future. Now is the moment to decentralize supply systems for water, food and energy, to invest in regenerative agriculture and practices of ecosystem restoration, to create seed banks and exchange, and to establish networks and economic mechanisms of mutual aid, resource sharing and reciprocal gifting. &lt;mark&gt;Localization not only offers food sovereignty but also a path to political autonomy – as we take charge of our own basic needs, we can come together to make collaborative decisions from the bottom up.&lt;/mark&gt; From various ecosystem restoration practices to the permaculture, seed saving and ecovillage movements, all the way to large-scale social movements like Extinction Rebellion and experiments of radical grassroots democracy like Rojava and the Zapatistas, the world offers a thousand examples showing that this path is viable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the spiritual, social, and economic-political spheres are so inseparably intertwined, successful system change will rely on profound structural transformations in these three realms in parallel. It doesn’t mean we must all do everything at once, it means we must support each other. May we each listen deeply for what we’re now called to do and be, while remaining aware of each other. &lt;mark&gt;As much as narratives of isolation and social distancing threaten to keep us afraid and separate, our ability to go through this crisis relies on our ability to organize and build alliances, remembering that we are community.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever we may do, may we remember that this is a moment of unique historic possibility. As Julian Assange told Yanis Varoufakis from his prison cell by phone, “Anything goes… Everything is now possible.” And if there’s one thing that Covid-19 has taught us, it is that &lt;mark&gt;dramatic shifts of collective behavior can actually occur overnight.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Can we entertain the possibility that we as humanity – or some deeper part of ourselves, whether conscious or not – have dreamed this moment into existence as a catalyst for our collective evolution?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Pollination Approach</title><link href="/blog/2020/10/15/pollination-approach.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Pollination Approach" /><published>2020-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/10/15/pollination-approach</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/10/15/pollination-approach.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rhsmith.umd.edu/directory/bennet-zelner&quot;&gt;Bennet A. Zelner&lt;/a&gt;, first published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.org/news/bulletin/articles/439-bulletin-spring-2020/8131-the-pollination-approach-to-delivering-psychedelic-assisted-mental-healthcare&quot;&gt;MAPS Bulletin Spring 2020: Vol. 30, No. 1&lt;/a&gt;. Highlights my own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article I outline a novel economic approach for delivering psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare, the Pollination Approach. The Pollination Approach focuses on the intrinsically &lt;mark&gt;interdependent production of individual and community wellness&lt;/mark&gt;. It contrasts sharply with the current pharmaceutical-centered approach to mental healthcare, which focuses on the &lt;mark&gt;management of symptoms rather than the production of wellness&lt;/mark&gt;, and reflects divisive economic conceptions that have contributed to rising rates of mental distress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next section I describe the economic conceptions animating the pharmaceutical approach. In the following section I discuss the relationship among these conceptions, the disruption of community social and economic systems, and mental health. In the third section I present the Pollination Approach, describing how all of its facets–the design of treatment sites, the conduct of integration activities, the &lt;mark&gt;configuration of ownership and decision-making structures, and the financial structures used to create and allocate shared prosperity&lt;/mark&gt;–promote the production of wellness through the &lt;mark&gt;renewal and recirculation of community resources&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Pharmaceutical Approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pharmaceutical approach to mental healthcare portrays mental disorders as clusters of biologically-based symptoms susceptible to being treated primarily with drugs, much like a physical disease. This approach has benefited drug manufacturers, whose U.S. revenues from the sale of psychiatric drugs rose from $2.8 billion in 1987 (the year in which Prozac was introduced) to $34 billion in 2010. Yet despite the fact that antidepressants alone represent the most prescribed category of pharmaceuticals among the U.S. non-geriatric adult population, American mental health has reached a crisis state. &lt;mark&gt;The national suicide rate has increased to its greatest level in 50 years&lt;/mark&gt; and continues to rise. The U.S. also has the highest rate of death from mental health and substance abuse disorders among peer countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dire state of our collective mental health is linked to widely-held economic conceptions that have contributed to the pharmaceutical approach’s financial profitability. The first such conception is that of economic individualism. When psychiatric drugs were first introduced in the 1950s, patients were viewed as socially embedded individuals whose mental illness reflected &lt;mark&gt;both psychosocial and biological factors&lt;/mark&gt;, and for whom pharmaceutical treatment was considered an adjunct to psychological and social remedies. Pharmaceutical manufacturers actively promoted the reconceptualization of mental illness as a constellation of biologically-based symptoms, and of patients as atomized consumers devoid of psychological and social context. These shifts, which leveraged an ascendant cultural view of people as individualistic market participants, &lt;mark&gt;promoted the long-term consumption of medication as the primary modality for treating mental distress&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second widely-held economic conception that has contributed to the pharmaceutical approach’s financial profitability is the belief that unconstrained market processes produce the best economic outcomes. American drug manufacturers have leveraged and promoted this belief, sponsoring numerous economic studies intended to convince policymakers that a hands-off approach to the economic regulation of the industry would maximize innovation, with high drug prices representing the cost of progress. Prescription drug spending in the U.S. has increased dramatically as a result, rising more than 1,800% between 1980 and 2015 and outpacing that in other developed countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Disruption of Community Systems and the Impairment of Mental Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic conceptions animating the pharmaceutical approach have impaired our collective mental health through their influence on an expanding array of policies and practices over the past four decades. Market competition is now widely regarded as the best and most natural organizing principle for all human relations, and economic individualism has come to represent not just independence and self-reliance, but the prioritization of self over relationships, and of individual success over the common good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason that these divisive conceptions have been so damaging is that they conflict with basic human nature. We possess an evolutionary drive to connect and cooperate with each other because doing so helped our ancestors survive. The primary structures in which we have traditionally expressed and fulfilled this drive are &lt;mark&gt;residential communities, complex systems of people and resources linked in interdependent social, economic, ecological, and other interrelated systems&lt;/mark&gt;. As in nature, healthy systems promote individual and collective well-being. However, the ascent of the economic conceptions discussed above has disrupted the functioning of community systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First consider community social systems. Americans no longer come together as they once did: They now have fewer interactions with friends and family, and are less likely to belong to organizations that provide opportunities for social interaction. This &lt;mark&gt;crisis of connection&lt;/mark&gt; is reflected in a loneliness epidemic that has fueled rising rates of depression, anxiety, and addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paralleling the crisis of connection in social systems is a &lt;mark&gt;crisis of extraction&lt;/mark&gt; in economic systems. In localities throughout the U.S., outposts of large corporations have displaced locally owned businesses. As a result, locally produced income is extracted by distant shareholders rather than being recirculated within the community to fund local (re)investment, contributing to economic inequality. Further, the extraction of decision-making authority by remote corporate managers with no direct connection to local ecosystems results in the &lt;mark&gt;unsustainable use of local resources&lt;/mark&gt;, depleting the human, natural, and other forms of productive capital available to provision ongoing local economic activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crises of disconnection and extraction in community social and economic systems have fueled rising rates of disorders such as depression and addiction. Disconnection is a core feature of depression and &lt;mark&gt;addiction represents an adaptive response to disconnection&lt;/mark&gt;. Economic stress increases vulnerability to both conditions. Large-scale statistical analysis supports these ideas, demonstrating that countries with greater income inequality – reflecting the promulgation of policies and practices embodying the individual-centric, hyper-competitive economic conceptions discussed above–exhibit higher rates of depression and illegal drug use (a proxy for addiction). &lt;mark&gt;A comprehensive approach to the delivery of mental healthcare must counteract these divisive conceptions’ damaging psychological influence by facilitating the repair of community systems, complementing and contributing to individual healing.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Pollination Approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pollination Approach to delivering mental healthcare recognizes the &lt;mark&gt;mutually reinforcing relationship between individual and collective wellness&lt;/mark&gt;. It is rooted in the ecological principle that the production of wellness depends on the continual &lt;mark&gt;renewal and recirculation of system resources&lt;/mark&gt; (versus their extraction or depletion). &lt;mark&gt;Pollinator organizations facilitate the renewal and recirculation of resources in community systems as pollinator organisms do in natural systems&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Community Reconnection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delivery of psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare under the Pollination Approach facilitates, first and foremost, the renewal and recirculation of human resources. Psychedelic medicines possess a documented ability to foster connection, and the shift from disconnection to connection represents a key mechanism in the healing process. &lt;mark&gt;The Pollination Approach harnesses this shift by (re)connecting patients to social, economic, and other community systems, contributing to individual healing and the revitalization of the systems themselves.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Treatment sites enacting the Pollination Approach function as wellness centers&lt;/mark&gt;, gathering places where community members may participate in a range of healing and community-building activities in addition to psychedelic-assisted therapy. Explicit reconnection activities for those who have undergone therapy include &lt;mark&gt;group integration sessions&lt;/mark&gt; as well as &lt;mark&gt;community reintegration programs&lt;/mark&gt; conducted in partnership with local organizations, such as businesses, cultural institutions, civic organizations, religious organizations, and others. These organizations may also serve as points of access, especially in communities where psychedelic medicines are viewed with skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Local Wisdom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The identification of specific partner organizations and adaptation of other delivery-of-care elements to community needs and customs are undertaken in close consultation with local wisdom keepers. Community elders, social workers, ER workers, spiritual leaders, union representatives, local business owners, and others may all possess distinctive knowledge of common trauma patterns, recirculatory gaps in community systems, and sources of resource depletion and extraction. The integration of such wisdom with more generalized knowledge of therapeutic techniques and psychedelic medicines optimizes the delivery of care in a given community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Governance Principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ownership and governance of wellness centers under the Pollination Approach also support the production of wellness through the renewal and recirculation of community resources. Two core principles inform choices in this area. The first is &lt;mark&gt;stakeholder inclusivity, the notion that an organization should operate for the explicit benefit of its stakeholder groups including customers, employees, community members, and others&lt;/mark&gt;. The principle of stakeholder inclusivity naturally supports the inherently inclusive process of wellness production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The principle of stakeholder inclusivity contrasts sharply with the creed of shareholder primacy guiding most corporate decision-making.&lt;/mark&gt; The latter ascended in conjunction with the divisive economic conceptions discussed above. It holds that the sole purpose of a corporation is to serve the interests of shareholders by maximizing financial profits, as reflected in the pharmaceutical approach’s emphasis on managing symptoms. The production of wellness is less lucrative for pharmaceutical shareholders because it reduces the need for ongoing medical intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second principle informing the ownership and governance of wellness centers under the Pollination Approach is &lt;mark&gt;distributed local ownership&lt;/mark&gt;. Local ownership supports the health of community economic systems by promoting the recirculation of income, creating an economic multiplier effect from the local (re)investment that such recirculation enables. Local ownership also promotes the sustainable use of a community’s human, natural, and other productive resources because owners and managers participate directly in the local ecosystem, attuning them to local conditions. &lt;mark&gt;Distributed local ownership–ownership that is spread widely among local community members from different stakeholder groups&lt;/mark&gt;–amplifies these benefits by dispersing financial returns and diversifying the information sources contributing to decision-making. Collaborative ties between wellness centers and non-local organizations in the psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare ecosystem, such as MAPS and MAPS PBC, complement local ownership by promoting the circulation of global resources, such as knowledge gained through experiential learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Cooperative Organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The organizational form that most naturally supports the principles of stakeholder inclusivity and distributed local ownership is a cooperative structure, which distributes ownership and control among the members of stakeholder groups such as workers or customers&lt;/mark&gt;. Treatment sites enacting the Pollination Approach may distribute ownership and control most widely by adopting a &lt;mark&gt;multi-stakeholder cooperative structure&lt;/mark&gt;, in which the cooperative’s owners include members of both of these groups as well as other community stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooperatives are typically organized as corporations or LLCs, legal forms that distribute the financial returns from community wellness centers among stakeholder-owners. Though non-profit organizations are more commonly associated with the production of social returns, &lt;mark&gt;existing legal classifications do not readily accommodate entities producing both types of return because they reflect an ingrained assumption that the two are incompatible.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An organization’s legal form also does not by itself guarantee a given behavior pattern. For example, &lt;mark&gt;some non-profit hospitals have been criticized for accumulating large cash reserves that are not being used to benefit the community&lt;/mark&gt;, while the Business Roundtable–an association of corporate CEOs that has traditionally endorsed shareholder primacy–recently proclaimed that a corporation’s purpose is to promote “an economy that serves all Americans.” &lt;mark&gt;The extent to which a wellness center’s specific incentive and decision-making structures support the mission objectives and governance principles discussed above is thus more consequential than its legal form.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Financial Structures for Sharing Prosperity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed above, multi-stakeholder cooperative organization enables community stakeholders to share in the financial returns generated by local wellness centers enacting the Pollination Approach. Symmetrically, wellness centers may finance their ongoing operations by sharing in the economic prosperity they enable for patients and communities. &lt;mark&gt;Mechanisms such as deferred payment plans linked to patients’ post-treatment income, employer-sponsored insurance coverage of consciousness-focused healthcare, and government grant funding based on reduced public welfare spending facilitate the collection of revenues from the provision of psychedelic-assisted therapy.&lt;/mark&gt; Similarly, the performance of contract research for entities such as MAPS, and the provision of therapy sessions and apprenticeships to trainees in external credentialing programs, create revenues and control costs by tapping into shared value co-created with other participants in the psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial funders play a critical role in this ecosystem. &lt;mark&gt;The equitable sharing of jointly enabled prosperity between funders and other stakeholders requires innovation because traditional funding structures reflect the dichotomy between the production of social and economic returns embodied in the legal distinction between non-profit and for-profit enterprise.&lt;/mark&gt; On the one hand, philanthropic funders may be unwilling to contribute to wellness centers organized as for-profit entities due to the ingrained belief that non-profits specialize in the production of social returns, an assumption that is reinforced by the favorable tax treatment of non-profit donations under the U.S. federal tax code. On the other hand, conventional venture-style mechanisms for the external funding of for-profit startups focus on the production of concentrated financial returns for the benefit of shareholders who retain a long-term equity stake, which conflicts with the governance principles discussed above. Wellness centers funded with such mechanisms would be deterred from generating wider social and economic returns through the renewal and recirculation of community resources, and also from engaging in the prototyping necessary for continual learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financing mechanisms that transcend these institutionalized trade-offs are currently under development. One example is a structure that builds on recent innovations in venture capital financing intended to align the long-term incentives of founders and funders. It works by paying initial funders a &lt;mark&gt;capped return&lt;/mark&gt; drawn from wellness centers’ operating cash flows; transferring funders’ original equity claim to a stakeholder pool; and distributing or selling shares in this pool to workers, patients, and members of other local stakeholder groups. Ultimately, these local owners would go on to pollinate additional local economic activity by investing their financial dividends (and perhaps their knowledge, labor, and social capital) into other community enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare holds revolutionary potential for treating various forms of mental distress. In order to fully realize this potential, it should be delivered using an equally revolutionary economic approach.&lt;/mark&gt; The Pollination Approach outlined above seeks to meet this aspiration by serving as more than a conventional business model, and as a source of healing itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Pollination Approach focuses on the intrinsically interdependent production of individual and community wellness</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unplugging from Facebook</title><link href="/blog/2020/07/09/unplugging-from-facebook.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unplugging from Facebook" /><published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/07/09/unplugging-from-facebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/07/09/unplugging-from-facebook.html">&lt;p&gt;Hi friends,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m significantly changing how I use Facebook and other corporate social media. I&amp;#39;m not going to feed it, and I&amp;#39;m not going to let it feed me any longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#39;m not going to post on my Facebook profile or page. I may occasionally post in groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#39;ve set it up so I can&amp;#39;t see my Facebook newsfeed on desktop or mobile (more on this below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially I&amp;#39;m just going to use Facebook as an &lt;strong&gt;address book/events discovery/search tool&lt;/strong&gt; from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also not be posting on Twitter, Instagram or YouTube. I already don&amp;#39;t use the newsfeeds on Twitter or Instagram. I will continue to follow a handful of channels on YouTube that aren&amp;#39;t available on Spotify. &lt;strong&gt;(Edit, Feb 2021: I have started using Twitter again to keep up with developments in the crypto space, though I rarely post there myself.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Where I will be posting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~daily: articles I read to my homepage (&lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.net/&quot;&gt;web&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.net/feed.rss&quot;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~monthly: blog posts to my blog (&lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.net/blog&quot;&gt;web&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.net/blog/feed&quot;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;), written with &lt;a href=&quot;https://typora.io/&quot;&gt;Typora&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~monthly: newsletters to my &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Substack&lt;/a&gt;, which will feature a summary of content I&amp;#39;ve created since the previous newsletter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~occasionally: episodes to my &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.net/podcast&quot;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How I read/listen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discover articles via &lt;a href=&quot;https://feedly.com/&quot;&gt;Feedly&lt;/a&gt;, including following a few Twitter accounts/Facebook pages converted with &lt;a href=&quot;http://fetchrss.com/&quot;&gt;FetchRSS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listen to podcasts via Spotify and (reluctantly) YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Hiding your Facebook newsfeed on desktop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install Stylus (&lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylus/clngdbkpkpeebahjckkjfobafhncgmne?hl=en&quot;&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/addon/styl-us/&quot;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt;) or Stylish (&lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish-custom-themes-for/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en&quot;&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/addon/stylish/&quot;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt;), then install &lt;a href=&quot;https://userstyles.org/styles/186176/facebook-desktop-by-stephen-reid&quot;&gt;this tiny script I wrote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Hiding your Facebook newsfeed on mobile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s no way of hiding the newsfeed in the mobile app, so uninstall it and train yourself to only access Facebook through Firefox. Install &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/addon/stylish/&quot;&gt;Stylish&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://userstyles.org/styles/186175/facebook-mobile-by-stephen-reid&quot;&gt;this tiny script I wrote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Further reading/listening&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/episode/6AMD8pCZzgsdoRvLxlqPJa&quot;&gt;Emerge: Zak Stein - American Culture&amp;#39;s Psychotic Break&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://humanetech.com/problem/&quot;&gt;Center for Humane Technology: The Problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dontgobacktonormal.uk/&quot;&gt;Don&amp;#39;t Go Back To Normal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I'm significantly changing how I use Facebook and other corporate social media</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sand Talk Dream Walk</title><link href="/blog/2020/04/14/sand-talk-dream-walk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sand Talk Dream Walk" /><published>2020-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/04/14/sand-talk-dream-walk</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/04/14/sand-talk-dream-walk.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A guided meditation (&amp;#39;dream walk&amp;#39;) featured in the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/45449501-sand-talk&quot;&gt;Sand Talk: How Indigenous Thinking Can Save the World&lt;/a&gt; by Indigenous Australian author Tyson Yunkaporta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;He recommends reading it aloud to someone, or to a group of people, while they sit or lie down with their eyes closed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here now. Picture in your mind a campfire you have seen, from a time when you have felt safe and happy and connected. See the fire, see it clear, have no fear. See deep into the heart of the hearth to the flame in the hot coals. See it dance, see the rhythm of it flickering. Feel the heat on your hands and face. Rub your hands together, make them hot, then rest them on your belly just under your navel. Rest them warm on your belly and feel the heat there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picture and feel the campfire in your mind. It is a real thing, this image. It exists, but where is it? Is it in your brain? No, it is in your mind. but where is your mind if not just in your brain? Imagine for a minute that your mind is not trapped only inside your skull; that it can move around your body. See the campfire in your head, crackling yellow and red. Feel the heat of it reach your face. Now try and move it down, that image, see it move and feel the warmth of it move, down your face and past your chin, down your neck and to your chest, see it and feel it move down past your liver, down over your stomach to your lower belly area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hold the image of the fire right there in your belly. It is not in your head now. Your mind is more than your brain and your sight is more than what your eyes provide. Your mind’s eye can see the fire there in your belly. See it, feel it burn. There is a power there, in your belly. This is your big power. It has energy, warmth and a rhythm, just like the fire you are seeing there with your mind’s eye. Feel it under your hands, burning bright. Now blow it to burn brighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a slow, deep breath. blow it gently out through lips that are almost closed, the way you blow on hot coals to make them glow. See the coals crackle and spark. Your hands are protecting the fire in your belly. See it as you breathe in again slowly and blow right into the heart of the hearth fire. breathe in, breathe out, see the coals glow and the flames flare. Keep breathing in and out now, fanning the flames. The air from this place, as it enters your lungs, is leaving small pieces of itself behind that enter your bloodstream and race through it to every part of your body. Those pieces are like sponges, mopping up tiny pockets of poison, poison left behind from a thousand sad feelings, bad memories, toxic events and attacks and accidents and damaged lands, stolen places, stolen things, corrupted waters, murders and massacres, fences and blocks and assaults and insults and injuries and hidden histories. let those poisons be mopped up by the little sponges of air in your blood, let them be taken in those sponges all through your body and back to your lungs, moving back from liquid to air and blown back out through your mouth and nose. blow the badness out, let it leave you and disintegrate in the air, rise up far above and blow away on the breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poisonous things leave behind dry areas, damaged areas, in your body. Imagine all through your limbs and torso and head, all this dry and crackly dead grass, snapped branches and grey, papery leaves. All this scrubby trash is blocking your mind from moving freely around your body. See the fire there in your belly. blow again on the hot coals, gently, seeing them glow and feeling the heat. blow again, harder this time, and see the sparks begin to spiral up from the fire as you blow. blow again, harder, and make the sparks fly further from the flames, fluttering upwards into the dry, dead grasses laying thick under your ribs. See them land there, settle in the feathery fronds, smoking softly in wisps that wind up through the itchy snarls of grasses and sticks on layers of leaves. See the tiny flames flare and climb and spiral and spread, and a sparrowhawk swoops in, wings in the rhythm of the flames, to take one of the smoking sticks in its talons, sweeping off inland to drop it smouldering in the knotted undergrowth of your chest. The fire forms a long line burning across your torso, dancing the same rhythm as the fire in your belly, bright yellow flames that burn briefly and not too hot, leaving soft, cool ash that crumbles into the soil, your flesh, and nourishes it, and will continue to nourish it each day as the dew drops fall and settle and sift inwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The line of fire spreads upwards. All the scars and injuries and brittle patches left by damage and loss and abuse are being swept into the fire and made into soft charcoal and ash, swirling together like crow and white cockatoo feathers. Soon it will spread to your throat, then your eyes, then your ears, then your hands. See the flames and smoke and feel the heat and hear the crackling and snapping through your ribs, your collarbones, your neck and throat, mouth and chin, nose and cheeks, eyes, forehead and scalp, ears, shoulders, arms and elbows, forearms and hands all burning and the smoke billowing out through your fingers and high into the sky. Dry, damaged areas are all made clean and new and warm and light. The fire spreads now, from your hands, past the campfire hearth in your belly, flames leaping across from your fingers to your hips, burning through the dry grass there and on through your loins and buttocks and thighs. The fire has a rhythm—feel it dance in your legs. Your knees pop and crackle as they go up in flame, your shins and calves, your ankles and feet, until smoke billows out of your toes and high into the sky, leaving you light and clean and new. Dew drops fall and cool everything down, dampening the ashes and soot and soaking it into the ground where heated seeds sprout and begin to take root. Country is becoming well. You are Country. You are becoming well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of somebody you love unconditionally, no matter what. If you can’t do this you need to stop now and go take care of your life. If you can, picture that person in your mind and let yourself feel that love for them, feel it like a sensation coming over you. Keep seeing the image of that person and feeling that love, then picture them in a special place. That place will be somewhere outdoors that is special to you both, a place where you have shared joy and love together, where you have connected deeply with the land and with each other. See every part of the landscape around you, the plants, trees, dirt or stones. See the person you love holding a big bucket of water. They tip it out onto the ground. They follow it where it flows, but let it ignore any civilised or synthetic barriers. Follow them, the loved one and the water, and pay attention to the way the water moves on the ground in that place, where it goes, where it stops, where it sinks. Feel the love for that person and then stretch out with that feeling, and feel the same sensation for that place. let your love move all across it, through it and into it, the same way rainwater would if it fell there right now. Feel that love spreading all over that Country. Where do you feel it in your body? In your chest, head, belly? Is that all? Is that feeling just inside you, or does it go further? Can you feel that love outside yourself, a long way off, in that special place? It is right there, a part of you and a part of the one you love, a feeling, a part of your mind and spirit, right there in that place. Can you feel it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holding on to that feeling, let the picture of your loved one and that place fade gently into the background. Slowly replace it with an image of the place where you are now. Not a room or a building—allow all that to be transparent. See the land, the ground, the waters and landforms around you and beneath you. Hold the feeling of love. Imagine where the water would flow if it fell on that ground right now. let the love trickle out from you, lapping outwards in ripples or tinkling in streams through the earth, see it there all around you for that place, feel it in the place. Feel the place. love the place. There may be wounds or sickness there in the land that make you sad, but hold that loving feeling because it is unconditional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The love is not just a feeling in your body now, or in a distant place, or with another person. It is around you in the place where you sit, in the land, along with the feeling from all the old people who have been connecting the same way with that place for thousands of years. All the memories of those Ancestors are there. All your own Ancestors’ memories lie inside you in the same way, in your bones, in every part of you, in your cellular memory. Mind and memory are real things although they can’t be touched, measured, proven or even seen. They exist, but not only in your brain. They extend out, to your body, to the land and your relations. Your mind is infinite and extends as far as your attention and love can go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind, brain, body, land, loved ones—all these things at the front of your thoughts at once; they make you heavy. Your body and spirit sinking, thinking, heaviness moving deep through you. Eyelids heavy, closed; hands heavy on your belly, back pressed into the ground—skull, shoulders, feet, legs, all heavy. The feeling, the loving in the land and the love in your body are the same thing, you and the earth the same thing now, so you sink right into it. Feel yourself going through the floor or ground like it’s quicksand, but transparent, the land, you, sinking slowly into the dirt or sand beneath you. There are layers of rock and water down here, and you pass through them, sifted and cleaned by them as they pass through you, cooling you as you fall deeper and deeper into the dark. You are not afraid. You are not alone. You begin to feel that loving feeling again, only now it is not coming from you, but coming into you, flowing through you and around you. There is a warmth and a rhythm to it. A deep rhythm sounding deep, deep down. You sink further, faster towards the loving rhythm and the warmth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see a soft glow, closer and closer, warmer and warmer, the rhythm thicker, thicker and older and stronger and deeper than anything else. It is familiar, comforting, and so is the glow. The glow is from a fire, a hearth fire or a heart-fire with hot coals and you know it. You’ve seen it before. Could it be the sun? It is the same as the fire in your belly, the image in your mind from before, only it is massive. Its power is made of the same stuff as the power you carry in your belly, your big power. As you feel the heat and rhythm you sense the same inside you, beneath your hands, thrumming and glowing. It feels like a fish sniffing at a line, deep beneath the sea. It is faint but real at your fingertips, stirring deep in your belly. You know this. You remember this place, the earth you came from, the big mother that bore you. You’re home. Now that big hearth fire under the earth stokes your own fire, the fire in your belly, replenishing your power, filling you up with endless love and energy. It is clean, warm and pure, and lifts you up. You feel lighter, and upwards you go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glow disappears beneath you but the rhythm and flame remain in your belly. They propel you up, up, up, up through miles of heat and rock and cold and earth and more rock and sand and water and earth, up, up, up until you reach the place where your body is sitting or lying there in the world. but you can’t stop. You keep drifting upwards now, lighter than burnt leaves on the breeze, stirring and rising up, up, up through any ceilings or tree tops, up, up through any clouds and into a shining blueness that stretches as far as you can see all around. Up and up still you rise, as the blue becomes deeper, richer, darker. Soon it falls away beneath you and you are into a clear black infinity all around. The earth is far below and you drift on through burning stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Seven Sisters are here, burning bright. All the hero Ancestors are up here, sky camp, watching you, blazing, that same fire again. Your rhythm is pulsing out to them; they are pulsing back, light washing through you in waves, stoking up that fire inside you again, blazing those coals, washing you clean and clear. Can your mind even extend up here, to the patterns in the endless night sky? Can your mind possibly perceive all of these stars, shapes, gaps—forms made by those gaps, the stories and morality and rich knowledge here, thousands of parts, all at once? Can it know every part at once? What it does hold for sure are the patterns created by all these parts. It sees objects pulled towards a space and knows what must lie there out of sight. It is able to see the swirl and stories and positions and angles and times and seasons all at once, to read the big patterns these show together and therefore make predictions and judgments about land-based events, phenomena, weather, ritual, the timing of all things in your life throughout each cycle of seasons, the longer cycles of generations and the even longer cycles of deep time and story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would it take to free your mind, allow it to see these big patterns again? All the Ancestors up here, they left their traces in the earth and waters below as well, and you carry those traces within, those memories and knowledges and deep, deep love. Those things wait for you, below. They tug at you, begin to draw you down. You are no longer light, but not heavy either. You are in balance, and you return to your place of love below. You are a point of connection between the earth and sky camp, so go, be that. You drop, plummet through stars and darkness and blue-black and deep blue and light blue and maybe clouds and water drops and tree tops and ceilings and then softly, softly, softly settle back down, down to earth, into the feeling of your place and your body, the rhythm that never stops, the fire in your belly, your power and the infinite potential of your mind, within and without. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A guided meditation ('dream walk') featured in the book Sand Talk by Indigenous author Tyson Yunkaporta.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Key concepts from Seeing That Frees</title><link href="/blog/2020/03/24/paticcasamuppada.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Key concepts from Seeing That Frees" /><published>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/03/24/paticcasamuppada</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/03/24/paticcasamuppada.html">&lt;p&gt;Key concepts from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25172403-seeing-that-frees&quot;&gt;Seeing That Frees&lt;/a&gt; by Rob Burbea&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anattā – not-self&lt;br /&gt;
Anicca – impermanence&lt;br /&gt;
Avijjā – ignorance&lt;br /&gt;
Bhava – becoming&lt;br /&gt;
Citta – heart/mind&lt;br /&gt;
Dukkha – suffering, unsatisfaction&lt;br /&gt;
Jarāmarana – decay-death&lt;br /&gt;
Jāti – birth&lt;br /&gt;
Nāmarūpa – mind-and-mattter, mentality-materiality&lt;br /&gt;
Papañca – conceptual proliferation&lt;br /&gt;
Phassa – contact&lt;br /&gt;
Salāyatana – six sense spheres&lt;br /&gt;
Sankhāra – fabrications, volitional formations&lt;br /&gt;
Tanhā – craving&lt;br /&gt;
Upādāna – clinging&lt;br /&gt;
Vedanā – feeling-tone&lt;br /&gt;
Viññāna – consciousness, knowing&lt;br /&gt;
Śūnyatā – emptiness&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dependently arising, and mutually empty!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Paticcasamuppada and related concepts</summary></entry></feed>