<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-03-23T09:44:41+00:00</updated><id>/blog/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">The Four Mountains</title><link href="/blog/2023/03/23/the-four-mountains.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Four Mountains" /><published>2023-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2023/03/23/the-four-mountains</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2023/03/23/the-four-mountains.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Four Mountains story as told by Vanessa Machado de Oliveira Andreotti in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57425775-hospicing-modernity&quot;&gt;Hospicing Modernity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a story about four mountains. Each mountain represents a stage of life that human beings need to go through. There is a baby mountain, a warrior mountain, a hunter/provider mountain, and an elder mountain. If all is in balance, the land, the ancestors, all relations will support the human people to move from one mountain to the other. Humans, like other beings, do not own their time or their life. It is a more powerful force, which many Indigenous people call the Great Spirit or the Creator, who decides the length of time we will travel through life and the visions we will receive for what and how we are meant to contribute. Some people are meant to travel only so far through the mountains—they may complete their journey early for different reasons. Sometimes, with babies, for example, the time is not right for them to stay, but they still come to visit their families for a bit, as a gift. Sometimes people get lost or find a path in the mountains that leads to a dead end, and sometimes they starve there. Sometimes people, individually or collectively, just get stuck in one mountain without the teachings they need to proceed. When this happens, the guidance of elders is necessary to help people to find the path, connect to the visions, and move in a healthier way again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Baby Mountain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first mountain is the baby mountain. If everything is in balance, when you come into the world as a baby, you are received at the base of this mountain with unconditional regard and respect for your existence, in the arms of your parents, your elders, and your communities who are committed to your well-being. Your first rite of passage is your first breath. You are carried up this mountain in a bundle that strengthens the connection between your baby body and the collective bodies around you, of your extended family. Wise and healthy grandparents, great-uncles, and great-aunties have a huge role to play in this mountain; and when they are not there, sometimes babies cannot make it to the other side. Once you reach the top of this mountain, you start to take your first steps on your own on your way down, still held by the hand of older relations. The focus of your learning shifts to your feet on the land. You learn about how to feel and relate to the ground beneath your feet and how to thread your path carefully, with respect and reverence for the land that will hold you for the rest of the journey. Learning that you are part of creation and cared for and guided by the people, the land, the ancestors, and all relations, makes you feel in your bones that your life has intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Warrior Mountain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second mountain is the warrior mountain. Now that you can walk on your own, the rite of passage in this mountain is to learn to set your own boundaries and to encounter your own vision and place in the world, rather than have your parents or other people define it for you. This is the mountain where you find your unique gifts, the unique medicines you bring and that eventually you will learn to put to use as they are needed. When society is in turmoil, it is the young people starting to climb this mountain who feel the consequences the most because they have not yet established boundaries, they have unbound energy and, since they are seeking and learning about self-rule, they also tend to push back against guidance and advice. As young people look for their path on their own, they sometimes end up on the wrong path when guidance is not available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this mountain you also need to meet and wrestle with your shadows. On the way up, it is like going into a very thick forest in the dark, in the middle of the night, with the half-moon and the stars barely illuminating the way. The trees can see your spirit, they know who you are, but they can’t tell you anything directly—you are still too self-absorbed to listen. They need to shake you out of this self-absorption to communicate with you. As you climb up, you grow impatient. It feels as if you can only be well if you find the answers, if you have certainty. But the role of the land as your teacher is to introduce you to the mystery of your existence. It can give you directions, usually in the form of visions and songs, but it won’t give you the final answer for everything you seek at this point. The land will always give you what you need to take the next small step, do the next right thing, and keep moving in a healthy way as your learning and your story gradually unfold. This part of the mountain path can be frustrating because your body has energy to run, but the ground is uneven, requiring you to walk slowly in order to develop patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those going up this mountain often spend a lot of time fighting with the shadows of the trees. There are also many distractions along the way: different pathway options, different voices and choices pointing in different directions. It is like trying to find your medicine, your gift, as a needle in a haystack. Many fears and insecurities show up in this process. Fear of not being worthy. Fear of not finding the “right” answer. Fear of missing out. Fear of humiliation, rejection, and abandonment. Fear of loss, pain, and death. Fear of making wrong choices. Fear that life may not be worth living. Fear that your life is a mistake. Fear of ineptitude and inadequacy. In order to forget these fears, many young people build an image of themselves that prevents others from seeing what is really going on. Some young people focus on building an image where they are strong, invincible, and never wrong. Others want to be seen as friendly, caring, and reliable. Some want to be seen as rebellious, transgressive, and defiant. Some are a mixture of all these types. But an image is just an image and the larger the gap between how you want to be seen (and also how you want the world to be) and the many things that are actually going on within you and around you, the harder the path feels for you and the higher the chances for making poor choices. This part of the mountain path is treacherous because you could be just living in your own bubble, walking in circles without direction, for the longest time. It is the job of families and of elders to support you and guide you, but sometimes they cannot show up because they are lost themselves and it could be that they got lost in the same mountain and never had an opportunity to find the path again. Especially nowadays, many people get trapped on this mountain and we lose too many of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right around the corner from that difficult part of the path there is a clearing, but you can only see it when you are already exhausted from fighting with your shadows and the shadows of the trees. In this clearing you can rest, you can fast, you can breathe, you can observe, you can hear your heartbeat synchronize with the heartbeat of the earth when you calm down. If you manage to quiet your spirit and become humble before the land, you may be contacted by the spirits who have known and observed you; the spirits who know what you need, the next step you must take, and the seedlings of the gifts and medicines you have inside you. From that point of contact onward, your medicines start to grow and to work through you and at least half of the fears and insecurities disappear. On the way down this mountain, you develop familiarity and closeness with your gifts and your medicines, you learn as much as possible about them, and this feels really good in a surprising way. This good feeling is generally different than you might have been expecting or looking for on your way up this mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Hunter/Provider Mountain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third mountain is the hunter or provider mountain. The rite of passage of this mountain is about seeing a much bigger picture and about seeing more than the picture is showing you as well, into the past and into the future. It is also about learning to use your medicines and gifts to contribute toward the well-being of your family, of your community, of the land, and of all relations. Now that you have learned to establish boundaries and you are starting to trust your own gifts, you need to learn how to offer them in a generative way to your community. You need to learn when, how, and how much to offer; when your medicines are good medicines, and when they can turn into poison; and how to integrate them with other medicines and gifts of other relations. This looks simple, but it is actually a period full of challenges. You will make many mistakes before you learn to work well with your own medicines and gifts and before you learn to integrate them with the medicines and gifts of others. This is a very busy and humbling period of deep learning about discernment. For example, some people may notice that you have good medicine, they may come to you to ask for or sometimes to demand some, but what you have may not be the medicine they need and you will need to know how to respond in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this mountain you are learning to be both confident and humble, both autonomous and accountable, to be generous and to not allow your generosity to be exploited, to take things seriously and to laugh at yourself, to learn quickly from your mistakes and only make new mistakes as you move to the next learning, to apologize for the suffering you have caused, to not increase other people’s labor unnecessarily, and to be accountable to the human and nonhuman lives that sacrifice themselves to keep you alive. You learn to gift your gifts—a gift is only a gift when it is gifted. It cannot be sold. A gifted gift moves the heart of those who receive it to a place of reciprocity, but the reciprocity may not be directly back to you. You learn to trust that, as long as you are gifting your gifts and using your medicines in a generative way, the land and the spirits will take care of your needs too. Sometimes you need a day job to sustain your family while you do the work with your gifts and medicines in parallel. It is important to have a clear idea of the difference between what is the job and what is the work that needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also shadows on this mountain that you need to wrestle with. You may be tempted to use your gifts in destructive ways. You need to observe yourself and what is happening around you. If there is imbalance, you can turn from a hunter into a predator who takes more than their fair share from the land and who exploits the weaknesses of other beings, taking advantage of them. This happens when there are gaps in the teachings of the previous mountains. That is why it is important that you learn very early what it means to be a helper; to put your body, your gifts, and your intellect to the service of the greater good of the land and the community. Otherwise you can use your life-force to destroy relations and to destroy yourself. When these imbalances happen, there is a natural law that makes you pay the price, sometimes with your life. Be really careful there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you can apply the teachings of this mountain within your own community, you are ready to learn to integrate your medicines and gifts into a much wider ecology, on the way down from the hunter/provider mountain. This is where you may be ready to mentor others who have similar medicines and gifts to your own, so that they don’t have to repeat the mistakes you have made yourself. As you see your medicines/gifts from a different perspective, you really notice how large the world is, how small you are, and instead of feeling insignificant, you feel the opposite because you see the miracle and beauty of small things—including yourself. You realize how much you don’t know; and how much you can’t know. It is all a mystery, but you are no longer afraid of not having the answers. Shadows no longer scare you and pain no longer haunts you—you have learned to hold the hand of pain and to accept that shadows are everywhere where there is also light. You can see the beautiful and the ugly, the good and the bad, the broken and the messed up, and bear witness. You develop more reverence for the land, for the planet, that holds it all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You start to hear the songs that move everything: the seasons, waters, winds, clouds, plants, ourselves, other animals; the cycles of life, death, and renewal. You notice the rhythms and movements that transform everything around you. The sky and the stars speak with you differently. You experience time differently. Although you have already been told that everything is interconnected and you have seen glimpses of it, this time it is not just a glimpse—you cannot turn it off. You are ready for the elder mountain, but you will say that you don’t feel ready for that yet (which could be one of the signs that you are).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Elder Mountain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth mountain, the elder mountain, is located behind the first three mountains described so far. The rite of passage here is to help other people with their rites of passage; to develop further your hindsight, insight, and foresight; and to become a good guide that can help people find their own direction according to the purpose of the mountain they are on. You will also revisit different teachings you received in your life and these teachings will show you deeper lessons. Since there is no book with an encyclopedia of directions you can give to those who need help, you will need to learn to support people who need your help by meeting them where they are at. In order to reach the elder mountain, which is near the baby mountain, you will need to go around all three mountains and visit the places where you shifted from one mountain to the next. There you will encounter people who need your guidance to find the path where they change to a different mountain. You will pass down your own experience of climbing, especially what you have learned from the mistakes you have made as you were finding your own direction. Like the trees in the warrior mountain, you cannot tell people directly what their purpose or direction should be. This is between them and the Great Spirit and they need to find it for themselves through their connection with the land and with all relations. This is important; otherwise they will not have the energy or the confidence to keep moving. As an elder, you will have to collaborate with the land and create experiences where the land itself can teach, and where you are just holding and protecting the space for those teachings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you walk to the elder mountain, you will meet warriors who are ready to become hunters/providers, you will meet children who are ready to become warriors, and you will meet some people who are stuck. Simultaneously, you will arrive at the place where the baby mountain meets the elder mountain. In the baby mountain you will help welcome new life to your community and help carry this life to the top of the first mountain. Elders are particularly suited to carry the babies because, unlike the warriors, they have patience; and unlike the hunters/providers, they have time. Both babies and elders are close to the ancestors and of the source of life-beyond-form. Elders also have the wisdom of hindsight to protect the babies, avoiding the parts of the path that are dangerous for the young ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this mountain, no one reaches the top still carrying their body. Only your spirit reaches the top. At some point along this mountain’s path you will have to shed your body. When the day of shedding the body comes, you are ready to pass away to the place of the ancestors. You are grateful for what you have been taught in this body; you have settled what needed to be settled; you have prepared your family; you have passed down your stories and your songs; the people you have mentored have become mentors themselves; you have helped people to switch mountains; and you are at peace with the enormity, timelessness, and incessant movement of the land. You go with empty hands. You leave everything behind. You leave no footprints. You become an ancestor and you meet those who have come before, those who are yet to come, and all the invisible relations—both human and nonhuman—who accompanied you in your path on all four mountains. When you shed your body, you integrate all the experiences you have had in this life and your spirit becomes one with the mystery of creation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Four Mountains story representing four stages of life told by Vanessa Machado de Oliveira Andreotti in Hospicing Modernity</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Revolution Will Not Be Psychologized</title><link href="/blog/2023/03/20/the-revolution-will-not-be-psychologized.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Revolution Will Not Be Psychologized" /><published>2023-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2023/03/20/the-revolution-will-not-be-psychologized</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2023/03/20/the-revolution-will-not-be-psychologized.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcript of &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/episode/3e5bkfY8mCsdhb9H39dHmy&quot;&gt;The Revolution Will Not Be Psychologized by The Emerald&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple months ago, the New York Times released an article called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/11/12/opinion/mental-health-therapy-instagram.html&quot;&gt;The Problem with Letting Therapy Speak Invade Everything&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It called into question the increasing dominance of psychology vernacular in modern life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychology vernacular, you know what I mean, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you may have heard words like trauma, narcissism, dissociation, shadow work, process a lot these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone&amp;#39;s processing all the time, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half of TikTok, one recent meme said, is people announcing their pathologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the Times article raised some important issues questioning the end goal of endless individual processing, and the degree to which we evaluate life, relationships, work, and everything else according to whether it is meeting our individualized psychological needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As if, you know, the purpose of life is to get all of our psychological needs met, rather than say, to exist as a strand in a great web within which we have ongoing responsibility to offer back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right around the same time, a prominent progressive organizer, Maurice Mitchell, released an article highlighting the transformation of the activist workplace into a theater of endless personal processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically saying that progressive organizations can&amp;#39;t get anything done anymore because they are constantly engaged in an internal war of psychologically driven discourse that centers around words like trauma and harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s stop everything and process again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then came Nigerian writer, author, philosopher, trickster, Bayo Okomolafe, who spoke about the urgency he felt to de-center Western psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quote, I have felt the need to say more about the colonial dynamics at work within the discipline of psychology, how it manufactures its object of analysis, how it is value-laden and culturally composed instead of being, as is often presumed, an epistemologically superior glimpse of the true nature of the psyche.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why this sudden urgency?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why this urgency to de-center Western psychology?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, surely we all benefit from an increased emphasis on mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely a system that has encouraged individuals to share feelings and bring old traumas to light, to speak repressed truths is a welcome change from the alternative in which everything is buried and never allowed to breathe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therapy can be amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individual therapy helps thousands upon thousands of people in the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I grew up among therapists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know and love many people in the psychology profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve personally benefited from therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would probably never encourage anyone to not get therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please, go to therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, really, get your ass to therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also know very well that there can be value in Western psychiatry&amp;#39;s identification and treatment of what are sometimes called mental disorders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have friends whose diagnoses of ADD or neurodivergence have helped them define something that for years remained frustratingly elusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that in extreme cases mental health help can be a person&amp;#39;s only refuge, and modern psychiatric medicine helps a whole lot of people who otherwise would have no recourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also know that modalities are changing and evolving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depth psychology goes deep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group models, constellational models, relational models, all of these are increasingly common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a co-mingling of therapeutic modalities with what&amp;#39;s called spiritual modalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ritual models are now emerging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a whole lot of profound work happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this episode isn&amp;#39;t a send-up of all things psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, it&amp;#39;s a dive into how psychology vernacular has come to dominate culture, and the consequences on individuals and systems when we evaluate societal issues and personal issues solely through a psychology model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a provocation, an invitation, an invitation to blow open and expand the discussion around the possible in the psychological sphere, and to ask ourselves what we miss, and slips away when this language becomes the primary language of the human experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For psychology, discourse has grown from a simple way to understand and evaluate the forces at play in one&amp;#39;s own psyche to be the medium through which much of modern discourse takes place, through which everything is evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the purpose of everything in one way or another is assumed to be psychological.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s all about the individual process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there&amp;#39;s a value to ritual, it is increasingly articulated as a psychological value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ritual in some circles has become synonymous with processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The yoga world is increasingly inundated with therapy speak, and the traditional yogic process has become deeply conflated with the psychological process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consciousness has been psychologized to the point that psychologists who long rejected the centrality of altered states of consciousness are now somehow arbiters of what states are safe and what aren&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional plant medicines are on the verge of a global psychologization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychology vernacular has been adopted en masse and also weaponized en masse, so that simple disagreements in viewpoint or worldview are now called out as psychological pathologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, you don&amp;#39;t agree with me, so you must be a narcissist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Societal ills are psychologically evaluated and activist movements have abandoned the spiritual vocabulary of Martin Luther King and Gandhi and the Dalai Lama in favor of psychology vernacular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Movements are now less about walking hand in hand to promise lands and much more about outing narcissists and addressing collective traumas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you can say, well, it&amp;#39;s just another language, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just another prism, just another way of seeing the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s just as good as any other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And sure, I&amp;#39;ve benefited greatly from psychology terminology and the understandings of individual process-oriented systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But like any vernacular, it has qualities, characteristics, and limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the issue is that this particular vernacular is increasingly being positioned, both intentionally and unintentionally, as absolute, as the right way to evaluate life, as the only legitimate way to talk about certain things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular vernacular prism is increasingly seeping into every aspect of our lives, encroaching into traditional animisms and spiritualities, encroaching into discourse around consciousness and psychedelics, around ritual, around yoga, around, you know, what it means to be alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what I&amp;#39;m offering here today with a few accompanying drums is that there are consequences to this process of psychologization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, consequences, like an inordinate emphasis on the individual, like pathologization as currency, like an erosion of animacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m always looking at the way that the animate gets sidelined, often imperceptibly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have to be careful in the hyper-focus on individual process, in the trauma discourse and shadow work, that we don&amp;#39;t inadvertently lose connection to a greater animacy, to the breath of life that is beyond us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when the third book of the Yoga Sutras is omitted from yoga teacher trainings because the first two books are much more recognizably psychological, and the third one is frighteningly animist, that is a subtle consequence of psychologization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When countless yoga teachers post psychotherapeutic lingo as if it&amp;#39;s traditional yogic wisdom, which happens all the time now, that is psychology vernacular fundamentally changing the scope of how we experience certain things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When all of the once inextricable animisms and magics of Buddhism get forgotten, and Buddhism is presented as almost indistinguishable from the psychotherapeutic process, that is psychologization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When all of the associated songs, beings, forces, protocols of a particular Amazonian plant medicine are left aside in favor of the understanding that the core of the process is individually therapeutic, that is a deeply consequential byproduct of psychologization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we have to be careful in all this not to lose connection to the breath of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The breath of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, psychologist James Hillman spoke about anima, the breath of life, the soul of the individual, the soul of the world, as something that had to be rescued by psychologists from theologians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the time he wrote that, given the iron vice that theology held the world in, he may have been right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now in this climate in which we&amp;#39;ve possibly reached the natural limit of the amount of individual processing that any planet can take, in which we are losing traditional perspectives in favor of self-help modalities, in which a particular vernacular is turning public discourse into a massive struggle session, I&amp;#39;m saying that anima, the soul of the world, the breath of life, may have to be rescued all over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are simply some things about this life, ways of seeing and being, that cannot adequately be defined through the vocabulary of modern psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are textures and depths to the way that traditional systems understand consciousness and relationality with the larger animate world that get lost when seen through the modalities that have arisen out of individualism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there is value in preserving, for example, tantric systems of understanding consciousness, or Yoruban systems of understanding consciousness, on their own terms, as opposed to seeking to make them all fit into psychological terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are ritual systems that can only be understood from within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are animacies that move through these ritual systems that modern psychology as a science would simply have no conception of and no vocabulary to even begin to elucidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forces that the Yoruban or Afro-Haitian practitioner, for example, understands intimately that psychology vernacular fails to even touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this podcast, as you know, is very concerned with what it means to re-center the animate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means understanding animacy on animacy&amp;#39;s terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In traditional animist visions, there are forces that cannot be fully understood as individual mental archetypes or even collective archetypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forces of ancestry, of place, of grove, of stream, of season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forces of growth and rot, of balance and imbalance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are forces that spring to life through song, that leap from head to head in group ritual, that arrive through hot points in diagrams in the center of the circle, that creep up the back of the neck as burnings and itchings, that devour unless fed, that stagnate unless acknowledged over and over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forces that want to be honored much more directly than we honor them when we speak of them as archetypes, as brain chemistry, as behavioral patterns, as symbols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forces whose intentions can be described in no other way than that they want us on our knees, singing to them, arms raised, crying aloud, crying aloud to the powers of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are forces that in their ritual context defy modern psychological notions of safety and agency and trauma and dissociation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, throw them completely to the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you hear the call of such forces?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you hear the tremble of the revolutionary drum?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s something I hear, something brewing, a far off sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the cry, the cry of the devotee, the cry of the mad saint who revels in the divine madness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the cry of the boiling trance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hear it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stirring of forgotten beings, of neglected forces, with names like Bacchus, with names like Eshu, with names like Grace, with names like outstretched on the ground before you, Mother Power, with names like in awe before the ocean of mystery, with names like weeping at your feet, with names like eternal sacrifice, with names like the devouring jaws of creation, with names like nature, nature, nature, wild in her mysteries, with names like the ocean who owns all of the heads, who cries to us that not all that moves through this body, this head, is mine to own or process, who speaks to a profound porousness to individual bodies and that what we call ourselves is actually an interweaving and within that not all patterns are mine to bear, who whispers directly to individual heads, remember the web, remember the breath of life, the breath of life that sounds across oceans of time and resounds with ecstatic shouts that cry beyond doubt that the revolution, the revolution will not be psychologized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution, the revolution, the revolution, the revolution will not be psychologized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution, the revolution, the revolution, the revolution will not be psychologized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Revolution Will Not Be Individualized&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;#39;s a question to start us off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#39;s the goal of the psychological process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, what&amp;#39;s it for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, for a very long time the end goal of the psychological and psychiatric process was considered to be normalcy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never mind that no one could ever quite agree about what exactly that was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normalcy was the goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normalcy quote can be defined as any behavior or condition which is usual, expected, typical, or conforms to a pre-existing standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which sounds nice and friendly enough, I guess, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s all be normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s help those who aren&amp;#39;t yet normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that it hasn&amp;#39;t been historically friendly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It hasn&amp;#39;t been friendly to anyone who veered from the narrow definition of normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s just say that Western psychology and psychiatry have committed brutalities in the quest for normalcy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pathologized entire native traditions in their narrow vision of normalcy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Institutionalized women for being hysterical in the name of normalcy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over-medicated in the name of normalcy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lobotomized 50,000 people in the United States alone in the name of normalcy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demonized anyone who deviates from the norm in the name of normalcy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which sounds a whole lot like, you know, what the Puritans did to the witches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So clear are the historic parallels between the Western psychological pathologization of the abnormal and the Christian persecution of heretics and witches that writer and friend of the pod Sophie Strand has called the DSM, the traditional psychiatric manual for classifying mental disorders, the modern day Malleus Maleficarum, the modern day hammer of the witches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So historically, the different has been psychologically pathologized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deviance from normality is the monster that must be driven out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in this Puritan vision in which ugliness and difference is to be rejected and wellness and normalcy are to be embraced, the psychological process for a long time was the process of ridding the individual of abnormality in favor of an elusive wellness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, in recent decades, psychology has rebounded from the stark black and white definitions of abnormal and normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an insane world, a world on the verge of environmental collapse, what does normal even mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s no measure of health, Krishnamurti famously said, to be well adjusted to a profoundly sick society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as part of this rebound, you see what hopefully less emphasis on the goal of normalcy, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gabor Maté just released a book called The Myth of Normal that specifically addresses what it even means to be normal in a sick world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is an individual supposed to do if they&amp;#39;re not supposed to be seeking normalcy or an ever elusive wellness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just show up, right for the ongoing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emphasis now is on showing up for the process, showing up for a kind of perpetual brokenness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a lot of beautiful discourse celebrating brokenness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve written many poems celebrating brokenness, discussed this in many episodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;#39;s a thought to chew on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if neither the quest for individual psychological normalcy and wellness or the perpetual celebration of individual brokenness is a complete picture?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s like we&amp;#39;ve been given two options, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either you&amp;#39;re working towards some elusive individual health wholeness or you&amp;#39;re doing shadow work forever, celebrating your own individual muck as some kind of end into itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don&amp;#39;t get me wrong, I think shadow work is valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;#39;s just say that there are traditions, non-psychological traditions, animate traditions that might say, what if you aren&amp;#39;t the issue at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if you aren&amp;#39;t the issue at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if all of this is way too much emphasis on the individual, the individual as processing unit for all the pain in the world, the individual that must rid themselves of patterns and traumas all by themselves, the individual that is fully responsible for the progression of their own psyche that has to make it on their own, come to resolution on their own, figure it all out on their own, plagued forever by what Tyson Yonca Porta calls the adolescent questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What am I doing here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it for?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And left to figure it out on our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the entire context of communal interaction, every single psycho-spiritual support system the individual being unit has historically had, which has mostly involved each individual not being treated as an individual unit at all, each strand in the web is plucked away until the individual is alone in the glaring light of their own consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brushed by the weight of the world and then told that everything is up to them to sort out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s up to you to figure it all out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, let&amp;#39;s isolate the individual and watch them under a microscope in a fluorescent lit room and then marvel at the fact that they shrivel in those conditions rather than thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in a world of interconnected systems, many current psychology models put too much weight on the individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have withdrawn to a highly subjectivist form of individualism, says Eva Illouz in the New York Times article, in which everything is about how I feel, what I want, if my needs are being met, and then conversely, the burdens I bear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact I&amp;#39;m not living exactly the life I want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#39;t lived up to the great standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#39;t saved the world from climate change yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of it is about me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, let&amp;#39;s be real here for a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern humans, specifically modern middle to upper class humans from the developed West, spend a whole lot of time talking about ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of you who&amp;#39;ve spent time in indigenous communities, traditions, have you ever heard discussion of the individual process on the level that we do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talk about ourselves constantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And let&amp;#39;s just say that this is an emphasis on individual process that has never existed in the 350,000 year history of human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you can say it&amp;#39;s necessary in a world which has isolated individuals as the unit at the heart of everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s necessary to have a model in which people treat individualized symptoms individually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, you can say that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there also comes a point where you have to be willing to question that model too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There comes a point where it might also end up exacerbating the problem, where it reifies self-centered individualism, where it reinforces the vision that the individual is the unit at the center of everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said in the episode on embodiment recently that the transformation of the old gods into archetypes that live within individual heads puts too much pressure on the individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for example, the gods that form the basis of certain modern psychological traditions, the Greek gods, these were never traditionally seen as internal psychological forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were ecological forces, communal forces, external forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so they were traditionally honored how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Externally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through protocols and practices that get lost when you make the process solely an internal one rather than a process of external alchemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of fire and water and sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;#39;s something to be really clear about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not in any way saying don&amp;#39;t do the inner work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m saying that we have a stunted view of what most effectively gets at the inner work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because in fine western individualist tradition, we assume that the work must involve the isolation of the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the scientific way, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;#39;m saying there are a hundred thousand ways of doing the work that are lost to us when we think that the work only happens inside us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That it&amp;#39;s our responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That we must bear the weight of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps we can turn the microscope off of ourselves just a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when we expand the scope of vision we get a glimpse of something much larger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Circles within circles, hoops within hoops, spheres within spheres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we shrug the weight off our shoulders, shrug off those spheres with a sigh and a sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we cry beyond doubt that the revolution, the revolution, the revolution will not be individualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Revolution Will Be Alchemized&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be familial, polyvagal, not I alone, I and you, and the inexpressible force between us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question will be less about what&amp;#39;s wrong with me, it will be how can we work to bring whole animate ecosystems into balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the health of the individual must be looked at, but so must the whole mandala of systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a meme about a wilting plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;#39;t diagnose the plant with wilting plant syndrome, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You look at the soil, the water, the light, the container, the mandala of systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is not about one person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full evaluation of the health of the individual is the individual in relation to systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human journey is not simply a journey in our heads, a journey that is mostly about brain chemistry, about an internal process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary issue facing individual beings has to do with connection to the web of life, with the wheel of animacy, with the breath of the world, with spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not about who am I in relation to my own brain, or even just in relation with other people, it&amp;#39;s about who I am in relation to the power of nature itself, in relation to what Joseph Campbell called, thou, you, you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within this, the recognition of external forces, forces beyond brain chemistry, is absolutely vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, there are therapeutic systems that recognize this, but I want to give these external forces more than tacit acknowledgement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to go into what I mean by rigorous interaction with external animate forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to go into some of the simple animate protocols that get lost when the journey becomes just about me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So imagine this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if there are certain things at play in our lives and in the world around us that are only addressed, only opened up, only transformed through drumming?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only drumming, nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something so specific as this understanding, for example, in Afro-Brazilian or Haitian traditions, that there are certain rhythms for certain forces that need to be called, certain rhythms for certain communal adjustments that need to be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are rhythms for the seas that wash away the sorrows, rhythms for the winds that move internal and communal stucknesses, rhythms for aggressive forces that need to be given their time and space to burn, need to be honored ritually so they don&amp;#39;t play out intercommunally, rhythms for the waterfall that returns us to easeful joy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rhythm syncopates the heart-mind of the individual in tune with the pulse of the animate world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only drumming will adjust certain patterning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No amount of talking about it will do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain movements, certain currents, certain shifts can only be initiated through the steps of the dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain communal patterning does not melt away until three hours into the dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s an alchemy to pounding feet, an alchemy to repetitive sweat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can&amp;#39;t dance to it, said Emma Goldman, it&amp;#39;s not my revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that beat of ritual feet reaches back across oceans of time, resounds with ecstatic shouts and cries beyond doubt that the revolution, the revolution, the revolution will be...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, the transformation of base matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Revolution Will Be Ancestralized&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It happens through the friction generated from repetitive synchrony, from sweat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It happens through enacting over and over the stories of the old gods until tissues start to re-knit, until cells of fascia start to spiral around ancient songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around what are we spiraling?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around what are we re-knitting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around ancient songs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or only around ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mass enactment of Demeter&amp;#39;s grief over the loss of her daughter Persephone required nine full days of fasting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you know, it wasn&amp;#39;t fasting for your nine day individual wellness challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fasting as alchemy, to empty so that the force of the goddess can move through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;#39;t fasting for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fasting for thou.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this, all alchemy, all ritual activity, all of it is about relationality with the breath of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You breath of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relationality with spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relationality with the mystery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relationality with specifically that which is not me but of which I am a part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alchemy doesn&amp;#39;t happen with me in my head alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey to find harmonic balance is a journey that necessitates interaction with that which lives without as well as within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inner work is not so much a thing in the animist world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a fusion of inner and outer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outer ritual transforms the inner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within sanctified ritual space, the individual is a facet, a conduit, never the culmination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how energy moves between things, through story and offering, through ritualized communal enactment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feed you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I offer water to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I offer fire to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over and over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if there are certain things, certain patterns, that may only be dispelled with fire?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To substitute anything other than fire doesn&amp;#39;t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists have found that there is a certain neurological calm that is only instigated with campfires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an alchemy to getting covered with ash and soot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is alchemy to getting buried up to one&amp;#39;s neck in red earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an alchemy to the application of ochre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any revolution must involve ashes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s alchemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tinders become cinders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be alchemized with drops of sweat and ceremonial fires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be awake and sensitized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will prickle and burn at the nape of the neck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be awake to the four winds, awake to the voices of the forest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be an ancient pulse, a thrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you hear the revolution thrumming?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The universe reimagining herself as a heartbeat inside of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s the revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boom boom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s the revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boom boom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that boom is a beat that reaches back across oceans of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across meters and rhymes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across creatures and kinds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across teachers and minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across seekers and signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across flowering vines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across spiraling lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A beat that resounds with ecstatic shouts and cries beyond doubt that the revolution, the revolution will be ancestralized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are certain things that require negotiations with ancestors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct negotiations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only today I want to talk about my ancestral trauma, but through a contained space in which ancestral forces are called, fed, offered to, honored, appeased, reconciled, invited to sit beside us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congolese ancestral negotiations happen through cauldrons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meticulous construction of ancestral cauldrons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through concoctions of ancestral soil and ash and medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you held a pinch of ancestral soil in between your thumb and forefinger and whispered to the ancestors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whispered come here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Present now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you heard the ancestral voices?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Why would I want the voices in my head to stop?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bayo Okomolafé asks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be a grandmother trying to speak to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be guided by voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By whispers and unseen forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will recognize the ghosts that are hidden in corners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Revolution Will Be Ritualized&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the spiritist traditions are to be believed, there are forces that stick in the corners of houses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain energies perhaps can only be dispelled with salt or with ringing bells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some animist visions, there are certain entities that will only dissipate with loud cracking noises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are certain entities who are fed outside to rid them from the house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are entities that like chilies and lime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are others that like to be slathered in red clay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And others that like to be doused in milk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an alchemy to ritually pouring milk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an alchemy to pouring water on stone that can be accomplished through nothing other than pouring water on stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are transformations that can only happen texturally, sonically, repetitively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain things will never shift other than with a great cry to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great cry of, Oh Mother Power, I offer everything to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be an offering, a great offering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world offers itself to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sacrifice myself to myself, cries Odin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the revolution, the cycle of offering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be a platter of marigolds and opening of palms, a song offered from the heart, a surrender outwards, northwards, westwards, eastwards, southwards, feast directional horses, thunderous horses, forest mosses, through our pains, our losses, feast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in many, many traditions, certain dynamics can only be addressed through deliberate feeding of forces that exist outside oneself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are certain things that only begin to move once there is offering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In traditional animisms, the offering is essential to the transformational shift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can there be movement unless there is offering first?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I show up to therapy and sit down and immediately start talking about myself and what I feel and what I want without any offering first, then how would anything shift?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would powers move?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where&amp;#39;s the space for them to move?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sacrifice is first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hestia, the goddess of the hearth, eats first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First is the acknowledgement of the spiraling animate breath around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First is the opening of palms to the holy air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First is, I am nothing without you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am nothing without you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many traditions, to be a human in balance requires sacrifice, especially in times of exaggerated consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are taking more than ever we must offer back more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we give back?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through offering food, through offering fire, through offering song, through offering prayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine from Santa Clara Pueblo here recently reminded me, remember our prayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember our prayers in these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the breath of life that leaves the lips as an offering prayer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And with arms upheld and the name of the holy mystery of life on one&amp;#39;s lips, maybe there arrives that little thing called grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that grace is a space that opens up wide across oceans of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rain sublime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wind in the chimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A space that leaves its trace within the whispers of place and speaks aloud in undeniable ways that the revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution is a flood of grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you felt grace?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a movement that happened wholly outside of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an exhalation from the forest, a downpour from above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great shedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here was the thing about that moment of grace, the only thing you had to do was make space for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And perhaps you didn&amp;#39;t even need to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You weren&amp;#39;t responsible for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was not your mind that made it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was not your process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was instead a conspiracy of vast forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an utterance of the breath of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was, as Paul Tillich said, an all-encompassing acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That place where all we could do in the face of a hard, hard world is soften even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever our vernacular, whatever the prism through which we see the world, it is vitally important that we leave room for grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A worldview that doesn&amp;#39;t leave room for grace has abandoned the winds and seas and the currents and the tides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are traditions that sing for hours and hours and days and days just about grace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will come as a cascade of grace, of falling rain, and arms uplifted in devotion that grace arrives at last in rhythmic refrain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devotion, have you heard?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are aspects of the human experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are patterns, there are forces that can only be addressed through devotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are certain downpours that only come when crying aloud for rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution is us, cast upon the ground in devotion, in awe before the powers of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution is us, weeping by the side of the river that day, held by the riverbank, washed in the waters of the world, washed clean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devotion, the drip of devotion, the nectar of devotion, the flood of devotion, the downpour of devotion, the fire of devotion, the warmth of devotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devotion unlocks certain marrows, precipitates certain tricklings, instigates certain burnings, fires certain primordial kilns, crumbles certain constructs, emits certain ashy residues, allows for certain downpours that nothing else does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when the devotional saints cry to the vastness, cry to the great power, make me into a pyre of sandalwood and aloe, light me on fire, reduce me to ashes, rub those ashes all over your great body, and then dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a therapeutic request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the devotional cry that says obliterate me altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obliterate me altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we gaze out across human history through the lens of devotion, we see the centrality, the essentiality, the primal necessity of devotion to the human organism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see multi-thousand year movements that have swept across vast territories of earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find a torrent of songs and poetry and cries from the heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find that the sound of people falling to their knees before the mother of the universe has been the percussive soundtrack of human life, a soundtrack of individual obliteration and absorption into the web of life that reaches back, back, back, across oceans of time, across rhythms and rhymes, across luminous sublimes, like, lover, did you see it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sun through the blinds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be daytime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be daytime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It must be daytime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another day in awe of the shine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another day in awe of the shine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that shine reminds that in precarious times, the revolution, the revolution, the revolution will be bhaktified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So devotional fervor in these times gets a pretty bad rap, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because in the West now it&amp;#39;s mostly associated with conservative right-wing ideological fanaticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But mystic devotional fervor has actually been a vital driving force, a necessity for many who feel so deeply, long so fervently, want so wildly to be held to the heart of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unclothed, raw, skin against skin, real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are hearts that will settle for nothing less than for the devotional cry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For surely there is a place in this world for the mad saint who can do nothing but sing the name of the great power again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever happened to the cry of the mad saint?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ektara, the one-stringed instrument, leads the baul singer across the torrent, through the great spirals of their lives into the great beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ektara is the guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you hear the sound of the ektara, says Sri Parvati Baul, it will take you, take you, you will never be the same again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be careful, beloveds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow that call and who knows where it may lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knows what long winding path through what steep canyons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That path, the devotional path, is deadly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knows how many hearts lay scattered by the wayside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for some it is undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An undeniable twang that grows, that gnaws, that pulls at us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, the one-stringed instrument that whispers your name, that calls you with the call that sends the gopis fleeing their houses at midnight to join the devotional dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The call that sends us flying out of our doors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The call that asks, which path is yours?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which path is yours?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which path is yours?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pranamandura, yamar, ekul, kul, du, kul, gailu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it would be so clear if we weren&amp;#39;t so deeply timid around the word devotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a feeling that there are a hundred thousand closeted devotional singers out there, longing to be set free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a sense of a hundred thousand voices longing to cry out, a hundred thousand tears waiting to be shed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many in this culture, this modern world, how many fractured individual minds long to drop to our knees and open our arms to the great mystery and turn the spotlight off of ourselves for just a minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because what we&amp;#39;ve wanted all along, perhaps, is for this I that bears so much burden, this I that stumbles blindly, that awkwardly seeks its way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we&amp;#39;ve wanted all along is for this I to be in right humming relation with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You great world of forces, you winds and directions, you waters and waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the I wants, perhaps, is not to talk about itself for endless hours, to shout what does it all mean forever into the echo chamber of its own cranium, but to be humbled, cast upon the forest floor, sent stumbling in awe before you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be madness within madness, a great clamoring of the ostracized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the revolution will be ecstaticized by ecstatics, lunified by lunatics, wept by weepers, sung by seekers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will not seem remotely sane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m mad, cries Ramdrasad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mirabai by all accounts was mad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bamakepa was mad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bengali saints are mad for God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wear their madness like a badge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Siberian shaman convulses in ecstasy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The voodoo practitioner shakes for spirit, disassociates flies, jerks about to feel the breath of life, move them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Boiling energies and wild otherworldly visions populate the devotional histories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Odin hangs upside down for nine days, gasping for a vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yelopa, the Tibetan yogin, was stark raving mad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadhus cast away their clothes and smear themselves in cemetery ash and cry, Bum Shiva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bum Shiva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bum Shiva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crying to the vastness from the ash heaps of these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crying force of life, force of life from the cremation pit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Force of life, force of life, force of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you feel what I mean now about the breath of life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you feel what I mean about the breath of life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you feel what I mean about the breath of life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invitation of this life is pranic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, how are we in relation to the breath of life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offer those anxious thoughts up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offer them out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They might not even be ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this is about the breath of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This journey is about the breath of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The breath of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the power, the pulse, the lightning tree of ancestry and ecology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey of what it is to be a breathing being in a world of vast forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supportive forces, devouring forces, and the potion of mouths that need to be fed and are constantly feeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of what it is to be one with this great world and separate at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of what it is to feel trans hairs rise and mist lick the skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of what it is to be born and live and die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And along the way to root and grow and branch like wind whipped cedars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like wounded cedars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like glorious cedars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like wounded glorious cedars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Howling with pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dripping with medicinal sap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dancing in the spaces where pain and medicine and beauty are not separate things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drinking the world into us and expelling it back out with words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey of what it is to strum, to sigh, to sing, to chant, to invoke, to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This journey can only be described in terms of breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of vibrancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that vibrancy, that breath is known, is felt in ritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ritual exists so that we may have direct communion with the pulse of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct communion with the powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct communion with the powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be ritualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be enacted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be drummed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be chanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be sung aloud in circles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be burnt as offerings on altars and set adrift and left for the angels of the waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will be ritualized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Western psychology will describe to no end what it considers to be the value of ritual for the individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of ecstatic ritual cannot be psychologized or anthropologized from the outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are things that communal ritual gets to that only it can get to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are animacies that are only understood within that specific ritual framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are forces that move through ritual space that can only be understood as exactly how they are understood in traditional context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things that psychology has no words for at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So ritual transcends the limitations of psychology vernacular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It exists within another sphere entirely, which is the sphere of direct communion with actual powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of ritual is deeper than a psychological value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But increasingly the value of ritual is seen as psychological.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And modern reclamations of ritual tend to be rituals of personal process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rituals in which the focus is mostly on individuals and their experience of the ritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need all kinds of expressions of ritual these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But check this out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a fundamental difference between I am participating in this ritual to go through my own personal process and I am participating in this ritual to honor Persephone&amp;#39;s descent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am participating in this ritual as part of my journey towards wellness versus I am feeding the devouring goddess because the devouring goddess needs to be fed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am doing this for me versus I am doing this to reprioritize and connect to the movement and balance of the greater animate world, of which I am only a part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a hyper-individualized world, there is value in a festival of the goddess that is just about the goddess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently went to Navaratri, the nine-day goddess festival in India, for the fourth time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was all about her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All nine days it&amp;#39;s about feeding her, singing her songs, telling her stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what re-centering the animate means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;#39;s so difficult to convey in this psychologized day and age that it doesn&amp;#39;t all have to come back somehow to the individual process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that in having it not be about the individual process, there actually may be more room for individual alchemy to occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ritual puts the individual, the communal, the ecological, and the cosmic in humming relation and then enacts alchemic change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that change only works when the individual turns it over in some way to the communal and ecological and universal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why traditional ritual is trauma work without ever having to name itself trauma work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when you take the individual out of the individual spotlight, another alchemy occurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You ensure that whatever individual triumphs, ecstasies, aggrandizements, depressions, weepings, or despairs each person experiences in the ritual live as part of a larger aesthetic being understood within the contextual whole rather than reinforcing either individual specialness or worthlessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the Haitian trans-practitioner, after convulsing on the floor with clenched fists as the force of the loa moved through, would be less likely to say, this is how I felt about what happened, and more likely to say, spirit showed up strong today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that spirit moved through is the barometer of efficacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More important ultimately than if each individual body felt well or heard or held within a cradle of safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;#39;s the paradox, ultimately the individual is held within a safety that is beyond what we call safety in modern psychology terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the safety of having it not be about us at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if the devotional texts and songs are to be believed, it is the greatest safety there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be perpetually dissolving like offering sugar on the tongue of this lion universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all that matters is that the lion was fed, and that the feeding was sweet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the ritual process has been conflated as psychological.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And really the entire spiritual process and psychological process have become conflated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if there is a value to spiritual practice these days, it&amp;#39;s seen as psychological value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m meditating or chanting this mantra to, you know, become more well adjusted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To self fulfill, to actualize wellness, to live my best self, to show up for the process, to do the individual work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is all fine and good, but this isn&amp;#39;t traditionally what most spiritual systems are actually about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s take the example of yoga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, yogic discourse has basically become psychology discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yoga teachers on Insta post psychology quotes all the time as if they&amp;#39;re ancient yogic teachings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;#39;s the thing, yoga and the modern Western psychological process are actually pretty different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, traditional yoga doesn&amp;#39;t really want you to dive into the content of your thoughts and own them as inseparable parts of your identity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are aspects of the yogic journey that run directly contrary to what we would call modern psychological processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mostly in terms of yoga&amp;#39;s attitude towards the individual self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are both important?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are both valuable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can therapeutic experience be spiritual and spiritual experience therapeutic?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there&amp;#39;s no dividing line between what an individual might experience in a therapy session versus on a yoga mat or a meditation cushion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But dividing lines also become necessary in order to preserve the value of traditional systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When everyone starts to believe, for example, that the goal of yoga is individual wellness or personal process, then it can be important to say, this isn&amp;#39;t exactly what traditional yoga was about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the issues arise when psychology tries to have the final word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tries to define spiritual experiences as ultimately psychological because that&amp;#39;s the only language it knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, tries to appoint itself as the expert in the room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when it steps into the realm of mystic experience and altered consciousness and tries to arbitrate, modern Western psychology has very little idea what it&amp;#39;s doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, let&amp;#39;s take a big example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big example where all this comes to a head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The psychologization of traditional plant medicines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is a tricky one because I&amp;#39;m ultimately in favor of psychedelics being used to treat PTSD and treatment resistant depression and this kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;#39;s good that psychedelics are going to be more widespread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just also happen to think that the psychology world has no idea what it&amp;#39;s getting itself into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychedelics are magnifiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know this, I&amp;#39;m sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything is magnified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little moments are blown up into something big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That one story, that one thought, that one spoon becomes the whole universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever seen that spoon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That spoon is f***ing huge, man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are like whole worlds in that spoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this magnification means that in traditional contexts, when done ritually and communally, psychedelics can magnify communal fields, enhance communal bonds, enhance ability to perceive forces that are known to the entire community and interacted with ritually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychedelics magnify relationships with ecologies, with particular beings, plant beings and animal beings and luminous beings and oceanic beings, beings sung to and named.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They magnify a person&amp;#39;s sensitivities to animate forces, both benevolent and not so benevolent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when you turn that magnification entirely on one&amp;#39;s own individual thought process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all the forces that one encounters are said to be inside one&amp;#39;s own head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if not inside one&amp;#39;s own head, then dealt with inside one&amp;#39;s own head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the therapist&amp;#39;s role is to facilitate the person going deeper and deeper into their own heads and to perceive everything as their own story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this not magnify already existing problems of hyper-individualism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this not turn up the pressure on the individual psyche even more?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you avoid, I went into psychedelic rapture and encountered the supreme importance of my own process again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, this is intricate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I said, I&amp;#39;m in favor of more widespread psychedelic use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m just posing some difficult questions here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when something that in animistic psychedelic ritual would be seen as a not so benevolent force passes through a psychedelic therapy session?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And instead of knowing what counteracting force is to call, the assumption is that this is an inextricable part of someone&amp;#39;s psyche.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trauma is them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That this must be part of their story rather than a confluence, an arising of factors and forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This intense force must be owned, must be part of the individual psyche because, you know, there&amp;#39;s no such thing as external forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And rather than simply clearing that intense force and moving on, a magnifying glass is turned on the person&amp;#39;s own head and once again we find a way to say, it&amp;#39;s all you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s all your responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the everything is in my head worldview results on the one hand in inordinate guilt, shame and pressure on the individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on the other hand, everything is in my head leads to I&amp;#39;m the most important thing in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In individual psychedelic therapy sessions, things may arise that the modern psychotherapeutic practitioner simply doesn&amp;#39;t even have the vocabulary to recognize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But people who&amp;#39;ve had how many experiences of psychedelic journeying, like a few, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly will be the experts on states of consciousness and fields of animacy that they know nothing about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will they know about the spirals, tunnels, other world portals, beings that populate the entheogenic realms and how to work with them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, there are traditions that have built relationships with plant entities over thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can recognize disturbances in the group field, can recognize what needs to be called and what needs to be cleared and they know how to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;#39;m concerned that the psychology model is not nearly complete enough to encompass the scope of what people encounter in psychedelic rapture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because for a system that considers itself the authorities on consciousness, modern Western psychology actually understands very little about consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, this vibratory field that is inextricably linked to ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inextricably linked to the moon and the sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inextricably linked to the land and the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That like all else, follows the principles of wave dynamics, reflects the pulses and movements around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consciousness flows, it lingers in eddies and pools, it expands, it self-architects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One moment transparent as sunlight through crystal and the next floundering in a whirlpool of muck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can you understand consciousness unless you have sung hours and hours of hymns to consciousness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you have met one by one each of the hundreds of goddesses that preside over the varying states of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you have basked in their luminous gradations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tantric traditions recognize tens of thousands of gradations of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each gradation a being, and in this recognize the potency and power and necessity of both the internalization and externalization of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tantric dakinis are both inner and outer forces at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yoruban orishas, the forces of nature, are described as shards of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These traditions, the Afro-Caribbean traditions, the Afro-Brazilian trans traditions, the Spiritist traditions, the Kalahari trans traditions, the Peruvian Shipibo traditions, these traditions exhibit a complete understanding of the spectrum of consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have celebrated and steeped in the centrality of altered consciousness for thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in its understanding of consciousness, Western psychology is still in the infant stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though Carl Jung spoke directly of outside forces, imaginal forces, of the archetypal symbol as a living being, a living presence, there is an unmistakable modern tendency to abstract the animate forces of consciousness and place them only in the individual head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Freudian side, states of altered consciousness were banished altogether, and modern psychology is still reaping the after effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of altered consciousness, the playing ground of the Siberian shaman and traditional tantrika has been historically pathologized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entire traditions that center around what modern psychology would call dissociative trance are pathologized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intuition is still to this day pathologized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The urge towards spirituality, an absolutely fundamental human urge, is still pathologized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inclination towards the religious or the spiritual is seen as a flaw or a coping mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not saying in any way that all psychologists think this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m saying that it is out there in the discourse in a pretty strong way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pathologization, a byproduct of psychology&amp;#39;s fraught history with that which veers from normal, is at an all-time high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, have you been on the internet recently?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s like a full-on carnival funhouse of pathologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perceived pathologies are celebrated, used as currency in one instance, and then vilified in another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, like, my own trauma story can become a way of propping myself up, of making myself unassailable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet calling out someone else&amp;#39;s trauma can be a way of putting them down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trauma discourse becomes a way to absolve oneself of sin and to label others as sinners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kind of becomes a little like hierarchical puritanism, doesn&amp;#39;t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like, I&amp;#39;m in favor of non-hierarchical communication models, but anyone who doesn&amp;#39;t see the socio-politics of the day in the exact same way I do is pathological.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s a good one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or when we psychologically diagnose as a way of making our view seem like the only view, that&amp;#39;s the new thing, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I don&amp;#39;t like what someone says, then I label what they&amp;#39;re doing as dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can&amp;#39;t simply live in the paradox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to pathologize it and label it as dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That must be your trauma talking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That must be narcissism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pathologize rather than accept paradox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;#39;m going to say that again, because it&amp;#39;s an important one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pathologize rather than accept paradox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you remember that scene from White Lotus where Harper just can&amp;#39;t stand the thought that the possibly right-wing couple across from her who don&amp;#39;t share her socio-political views might actually be happy, so she has to diagnose them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet check this out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who see the world differently than I do are just as likely to be happy as I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal stories are intricate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communal stories are intricate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal stories are intricate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is paradox upon paradox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it fills us with dread, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paradoxes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like that cultural appropriation might have led to some of the most beautiful music ever made?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It fills us with dread that, say, a Hindu woman in an arranged marriage might appear on Indian matchmaking and say that arranged marriage is really the only way to find love?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She must be oppressed, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She must have internalized the patriarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She&amp;#39;s certainly not actually happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to diagnose it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, what&amp;#39;s the alternative?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That we live in an infinitely variegated web of life in which we have little to no control over the prevailing winds or prevailing thoughts or prevailing ideologies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And our viewpoint isn&amp;#39;t superior to anyone else&amp;#39;s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we&amp;#39;re not better than anybody?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, of course we carve out views and we hold to those views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, in an age of environmental destruction and systemic racism, we see views that perpetuate injustice as problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s natural.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But increasingly, the culture of supposed inclusivity is constructing major walls around the acceptable and the unacceptable when it comes to discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And increasingly, those walls are defended with the twin armaments of psychologization and pathologization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it&amp;#39;s different from how I see the world, then it must be a pathology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in this, we see a worldview that is not very different at all from its ancestral puritanism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps in times of rupture and ambiguity, of forced cross-pollination, we have to become a lot more familiar with what Bayo Akomalafé calls the gods of the fault lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to not only nourish the ability to hold paradoxes, but to place paradoxical gods right at the center of our altars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the world doesn&amp;#39;t fit neatly and tidily into postmodern, postcolonial psychological definitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are native traditions that, when judged through a modern psychological lens, would be considered deeply codependent in their familial and social structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are traditions in which rituals of dissociation form the lifeblood of the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are traditions that harness trauma specifically as a means to instigate the visions that come with dissociation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is seen as a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s not a perfect answer for how to be a person in these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s not a fail-safe recipe for individual wellness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s not, ultimately, a trauma-free option in this cycle of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cycle of the birth canal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cycle of the hunt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This cycle of the cooking pot and cauldron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This life is a response to a rupture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A detour of flower is a response to a rupture, whose seed pods crack open and spark a thousand more ruptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Songs emerge in the rupture spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Syncretic traditions blossom in the rupture spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;West African orishas possess the hollow bodies of Catholic saints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazonian plant medicines sprout through their eye sockets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They deliver songs of pain and rupture and joy and renewal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we do in such precarious times?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we seek to wall trauma out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we seek to extract it like a tumor?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we seek to keep out all that is unsafe, like a great wall to keep out barbarian hordes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Revolution Will Not Be Safe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, times of precariousness, times of revolution, times of what is sometimes called apocalypse, are invitations towards rituals in which the prevailing energies are harnessed, not shied away from, utilized in all their broken glory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of the only successful slave revolt the Western Hemisphere has ever known was a trance ritual, born of trauma, born of blood and fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quote, dance of violent trembling to explosions of gunpowder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The petwo voodoo ritual harnessed off-kilter rhythms, sharp sounds, and volatile substances to send participants into states of trance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petwo comes alive at night, says Richard Ward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the time when it forged its path in Haitian history, as powerful spirits were called to free the enslaved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petwo is and always has been an incendiary rite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its true face is illuminated by flames flickering in the darkness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is bathed in the blood of its ancestors, proudly bearing its scars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing about the petwo ritual was safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indigenous Taino warrior relics, Congolese mountain spirits, colonial whips and whistles and Masonic Christian symbols fused in a ritual that was hot, intentionally harnessing precarious forces, conflicting ideologies, and conflicting energies to substantively alter consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question wasn&amp;#39;t about clearing individual patterns or processing individual emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overarching question was, what forces need to be called?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do the times require?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;#39;s ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do the times require?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are our rituals in precarious times?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are they rituals of pathologization that reinforce the other as the enemy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or can it last at last?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can it last they be rituals that embrace precious precarious paradox?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wonder why I&amp;#39;m focusing so much attention in this episode on Yoruban traditions, Afro-Haitian traditions, Afro-Brazilian traditions, it&amp;#39;s because these traditions occupy a space that is so thoroughly realized in their own treatment of gradations of consciousness and relationality, and simultaneously stand in glaring juxtaposition to current psychological models of safety, agency, trauma, and alterity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are traditions in which spirit governs all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spirit determines and delineates ritual space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spirit determines safety along its own terms, not ours, and its terms, in the convulsion of the trance and the heat of the beat, look nothing like current discussions around psychological safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#39;s no accident that these are also the traditions that were most likely to be historically psychologically pathologized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, for the obvious reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because they&amp;#39;re African.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the rhythms jolt Western minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the firelight on the faces haunts Western dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because convulsing bodies speak to a place where we have to let go of individual safety in favor of a much vaster safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to reach that safety has often required being obliterated along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very little about traditional ritual is safe at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We might look at safety as that which doesn&amp;#39;t trigger a trauma response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is only one vision of safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional animus cultures might look at psychology&amp;#39;s hyperfocus on the individual as profoundly unsafe, at the fact that there&amp;#39;s no sacrificial offering performed as unsafe, at the fact that we don&amp;#39;t know how to clear malevolent forces as unsafe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safety in these traditions can&amp;#39;t be achieved in carving out spaces of vernacular control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safety comes through knowing who to feed when, knowing who to call when, comes through the right talismans and adornments, through learning how to dispel thoughts that don&amp;#39;t lead anywhere good, through, in the Yoruban traditions, knowing who owns your head, knowing your ori-sha, and cultivating a good long-term relationship with them so that in the ritual circle agency can be turned over altogether at last as we&amp;#39;ve always longed for it to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And within that larger spiritual safety, what another person does or doesn&amp;#39;t say doesn&amp;#39;t matter very much at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will not be safe at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be many things, but it will not be safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will breathe hot breath down the back of the neck like an untamed, unwelcome god.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trance starts with a burning at the nape of the neck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something is happening, something beyond control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volatility is the very medium of the dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In times of precariousness, times of collapse, cultures ritualize access to dangerous spaces instead of attempting to retreat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the revolution will not preserve selves or identities or beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does the jaguar care what I believe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does nature care what I believe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does Kali care what I believe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will devour us whole, each of us, completely regardless of belief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, it may come as a surprise in these times of I, Me, and Mine, but the revolution will eat us alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will eat us alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you heard?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day nature is going to eat us alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day these bones are going to be worm food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a patch of blue forget-me-nots to blossom from my bones there on that high, penitent ridge line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And possibly blue blossoms to grow from my bones in that brief, glorious alpine summer in which everything is in full flowering, prismatic flowering, and nothing is remotely safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Norse tradition, the apocalypse, the end times, the Ragnarok, arrives specifically because the gods try to extract guarantees of safety from the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when that fails, they pin Trickster underground so that he can&amp;#39;t move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They pin down Loki, immobilize his joints, and if you know myth, you know that trying to immobilize Trickster is probably never a good plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Revolution Will Be Poeticized&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can&amp;#39;t wall other opinions out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can&amp;#39;t wall the different out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can&amp;#39;t expect everyone to share the same vernacular lens as we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increasingly, discourse seems to want to wall the other out on both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we need different gods of discourse besides Puritan gods that would see only the demonic in the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a different aesthetic governing the space of discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a fully realized pantheon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s a question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What gods do we invite close to us with the words that we speak?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What forces do we invoke?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have we ever considered, for example, that we might have an obligation to the deities that govern aesthetic beauty when we speak words?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would that change things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To consider the needs of Aphrodite every time we speak?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The space of modern discourse has become so narrow, a polarized, dichotomized, walled-off fortress of ick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we urgently need discourse to expand from this little jail cell to a vibrant capoeira circle or a hip-hop battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hip-hop battle, you know, when people used to be able within a ritually marked circle to be able to air conflict but it was all considered part of the play?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the aesthetics and the poetics of the play were of the ultimate importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It had to be done to the beat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It had to be done within a flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if it wasn&amp;#39;t, then the content of what you said didn&amp;#39;t even matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the end of the day, no one actually meant anyone any harm over it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what really mattered was the connection to the underlying aesthetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what I mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You old enough to remember those classic takedowns?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like when LL Cool J said, or more mythically, or when Cannibus inexplicably decided to pick a fight with LL Cool J with the meekest takedown of all time, saying 99% of your fans wear high heels?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And LL responded with one of the greatest disses ever, 99% of your fans don&amp;#39;t exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;99% of your fans don&amp;#39;t exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or this simple diss from the justifiably maligned yet still deeply quotable Kanye West before he lost it completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did Ye say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said, I forgot better shit than you ever thought of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I forgot better shit than you ever thought of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember when takedowns had style?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, really, like how boring is it to tear people down the way people tear each other down these days with psychology terminology?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#39;re a narcissist, you&amp;#39;re dissociative, you&amp;#39;re codependent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So aesthetically boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where&amp;#39;s the anima?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where&amp;#39;s the breath of life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened to the aesthetics and play of the hip hop battle?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like this one from the king of diss, Jay Z.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s right, sooner or later, Trickster says, I&amp;#39;ll take you up on your offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take me down, I&amp;#39;ll take you down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s make a game of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But somewhere along the line, we lost the game of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lost the aesthetics, the lightness, the play of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And these days we have a very unhealthy relationship with the gods of takedowns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there are gods of takedowns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because takedowns are an inevitable fact of community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, someone somewhere is going to want to take someone down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Capoeira circle, there are deep protocols to takedowns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And nothing is more important than the integrity of the circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flow of energy, the alignment to the axé, the breath of life, the prana that moves through the circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of it must be in service to the rhythm, the music, and ultimately all interpersonal conflict must be resolved without breaking the aesthetic of the circle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, it should enhance it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invitation in those takedowns is call and response and conversation and theatrically enacted battle in a way of reinforcing human bonds and bonds with the more than human at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrast that with people lobbing pathologies at each other on social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All life gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All aesthetic gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All responsibility gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All relationality gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No humor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No sense of, at the end of the day we can work this out and go break bread together and I respect you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I respect you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I respect you because ultimately no one&amp;#39;s better than anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;#39;s the mythological thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re going to try to be Trickster, if you&amp;#39;re going to decide to be the god of takedowns on your own, you better be willing to have the trick played on you too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re willing, if I&amp;#39;m willing, to point out others&amp;#39; flaws but I&amp;#39;m not willing to have my flaws pointed out, then I&amp;#39;ve quickly drifted from Trickster to fascist dictator or cadre leader and the Capoeira circle quickly becomes a struggle session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what a struggle session is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When everyone points fingers at someone in the town square and shouts out their flaws publicly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound familiar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound like the internet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aesthetic of communication spaces is something that traditional cultures have a vernacular for, often an unspoken one, that we in the modern world have a very difficult time understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For what does it mean to have a communication aesthetic in which spirit, the animate, sits right at the center?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what is of utmost importance is not necessarily individual process or opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to honor animacy in group conversation, even in heated discussion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to make space for gods of war and tricksters and goddesses of fierce beauty and huntresses and lunar kings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make space for expansions and flows, eddies and currents and all varieties of fluid interplay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means a focus off of the immediate utilitarian mechanistic needs of me as an individual unit establishing either my perfection or my brokenness towards a much larger vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means the adoption of a whole panoply of animate considerations, which can sound complicated, but it&amp;#39;s most easily summarized like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make space for poetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make space for poetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened to poetry in discourse?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the revolution, the revolution will be poeticized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please let it be poeticized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look at discourse today and I&amp;#39;m like, where is the poetry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tired overused vernacular repeated over and over stifles the flow of the poetic, leaves no space for unexpected revolutionary acts, unpreprogrammed ruptures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All transpires as the paralyzing virus intends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital buzzwords freeze people in their tracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly it is as if we each have to defend against charges rather than co-create space for a larger life force, a larger aesthetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d like to see a greater commitment to poetic rhapsodic throwdowns to free us from the cinderblock wall of modern discourse, the eastern block architecture of modern discourse, the struggle session of modern discourse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For when a movement loses its poetry, it is a dire, dire warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;#39;ll just say it outright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The language of modern activism is losing its poetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historic movements for social change, Martin Luther King and Gandhi&amp;#39;s movements for social change had at their core a spiritual vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in any spiritual tradition that I know of, everything always comes back to how am I walking in the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How am I living?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the role I&amp;#39;m playing in my own resentments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything comes back to the fact that if I point fingers, as the old saying goes, I&amp;#39;ve got at least one finger pointing back at myself too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I&amp;#39;ve got a responsibility to reflect the larger vision of the change that I want to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that what is loosely called the left these days, the progressive left, needs a deep spiritual renewal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A deep reintroduction to the breath of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a spiritual fervor to these historic movements that allowed for anima to awaken and pass through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fervor that is very different than the fervor of finger pointing or the fervor of individual takedowns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fervor of spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A glimpse of the promised land, which is us in conjunction with the infinite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fervor of alignment to something much larger, within which human concerns, as vital as they are, are also small and transitory in the face of a larger movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A justice that is aligned not to immediate individualisms, but to long arcs in the cosmos, primal forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the ritual architecture, not just human bickering at the center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life community in alignment with the great wheels of the cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I don&amp;#39;t hold a whole lot of sway, but I guess I&amp;#39;m inviting, for whatever it&amp;#39;s worth, the progressive movement, the activist world, to examine its relationship with spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if the immediate response is, well, what is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the answer is, exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anima.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is that mysterious thing that we may have never directly felt, but that is present in the tides of history as it is present in the next breath we take?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are things we must do, Bayo Okomalafé says, sayings we must say, thoughts we must think, that look nothing like the images of success that have so thoroughly possessed our visions of justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever our modality, whatever our framework, let&amp;#39;s spark an inquiry into the life breath itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Into animacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Into how to make space for it to flow through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Into how our conversation spaces and our therapeutic sessions and our ritual circles and our strategizing workshops can honor a multiplicity of gods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hidden gods we&amp;#39;ve forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we allow the polyvalent dynamism of nature itself to be present, for the non-human world to ring out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For it does ring out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It rings out when we make space for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success from an animate perspective may not look like psychological normalcy, like all traumas cleared, like wellness, nor may it necessarily look like showing up for the endless work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may not look like one viewpoint or ideology triumphing for one hot minute over another until another one comes around and wrecks that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may look like an ongoing commitment to presence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may look like that time I sang instead of speaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I wept instead of singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I poured coconut milk into the sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I mumbled a name that I&amp;#39;d forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A viable success metric poet Tom Hirons recently told a group of us is if the fibers of the universe start to hum along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does that get you to your next immediately articulated conversation or campaign objectives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it does is open up space, eventually, for another world to squeeze through just because we made space for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the breath of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that breath reaches back across oceans of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across meters and rhymes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across creatures and kinds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across teachers and minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across seekers and signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across flowering vines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across spiraling lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A breath that resounds with ecstatic shouts and cries beyond doubt that the revolution, the revolution will not be psychologized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, much praise and adoration due to the song The Revolution Will Not Be Televised, the 1971 song by Gil Scott-Heron off of the album Pieces of a Man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously it served as the inspiration for this episode and all respect and love to the great spoken word artist and musician Gil Scott-Heron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And speaking of musicians, an old friend of mine played some guitar on this episode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His name is Sonny Reinhart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best guitarists I know and his current band is called Necrot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;N-E-C-R-O-T.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know, easy listening type stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also special thanks to Bayo Okomolafé.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conversation that I had with him wove its way into this episode in numerous places and then there is going to be a full episode coming on similar topics that is an interview with Bayo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as always, this episode contains reference to many songs, books, movies, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These include the song Petro Voodoo Ceremonie Petro by Roots of Haiti, Ceremonie Petro by Voodoo La Friguenine, the book Mama Lola, A Voodoo Priestess in Brooklyn by Karen McCarthy Brown, The Spirits and the Law, Voodoo and Power in Haiti by Kate Ramsey, The Problem with Letting Therapy Speak Invade Everything, an article in the New York Times, November 12, 2022 by Tara Isabella Burton, Building Resilient Organizations by Maurice Mitchell and The Forge on November 29, 2022, the DSM-5, The Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 5th edition, 2013 by the American Psychiatric Association, and its ancient partner the Malleus Maleficarum, The Hammer of the Witches, Born of Blood and Fire, an incredible book about the Haitian pet will ritual by Richard Ward and Scarlet Imprint Press, the book Divine Horseman by Maya Deren, Voodoo Music in Haiti, an article by Bettino Lara, The Myth of Normal by Gabor Mate, the song Ako-Runo-Shatire by Parvati Baul, and I highly recommend listening to Parvati Baul&amp;#39;s music, it&amp;#39;s P-A-R-V-A-T-H-Y, and then new word B-A-U-L, the song Ogun Beramar by Kabogla Yaqira, the song Arawa Romiwa and Oshum Omiro, the song Now Beretowa by Carlos Nunez, the song Volto No Mundo Kamara, Zinga Capoeira, volume three, the songs Get Down, Four Three Two One, and The Ripper Strikes Back by LL Cool J, the song Diamonds from Sierra Leone by Kanye West, the song Watch What You Say to Me, T.I. featuring Jay-Z, The White Lotus, the HBO show from Mike White, and of course the Netflix show Indian Matchmaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am rooting for you Aparna.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t have much hope, but I am rooting for you.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A breath resounds with ecstatic shouts and cries beyond doubt that the revolution- the revolution, will not be psychologized.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Seeing through Dualities, Deepening in Emptiness</title><link href="/blog/2023/03/13/seeing-through-dualities-deepening-in-emptiness.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Seeing through Dualities, Deepening in Emptiness" /><published>2023-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2023/03/13/seeing-through-dualities-deepening-in-emptiness</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2023/03/13/seeing-through-dualities-deepening-in-emptiness.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To mark the completion of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://dharmacourse.org/seeing-through-dualities-deepening-in-emptiness/&quot;&gt;Seeing through Dualities, Deepening in Emptiness&lt;/a&gt; course, here are two of my favourite passage from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/25172403&quot;&gt;Seeing That Frees&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If what one is seeking is a final, intellectual understanding of ‘how it all works’, then there may be frustration. A view which comprehends the emptiness of all phenomena does not, and cannot, give an ultimately coherent explanation of the functioning of conventional reality in conceptual terms. Any such hypothetical account could only be available from views which reify at least some thing as elementary, including time. In seeking a full explanation then, we may be missing the point of the teaching. For explanation is not the task of emptiness; liberation is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely though, and as we have suggested before, simply shrugging and declaring ‘unknowing’ too early would also be a mistake. A premature retreat from knowing, before one has probed such mysteries as mutual dependency and the emptiness of time, can only deliver a limited freedom. Unknowing is not in itself, therefore, the point of the path. It is thoroughly &lt;em&gt;knowing&lt;/em&gt; voidness that brings a fuller release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at least one of these two tendencies – on the one hand, wanting the ‘clarification’ of a reductionist explanation, and on the other, wanting to abandon concepts too early – is usually very strong for most people. One person may be attached to descriptions of atomized items neatly categorized with their well-delineated functions within a mechanism, and believe such descriptions to be reality. Another may be attached to the concept that all concepts are burdensome and that they block any possibility of opening to reality. Sometimes a practitioner’s tendency careens back and forth over time between these two extremes. More often we each sustain a certain disposition to one or the other. This pair of views and tendencies are like Scylla and Charybdis, and somehow a middle way between them needs to be charted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most skilful use of the teachings of &lt;em&gt;paṭiccasamuppāda&lt;/em&gt; is to regard the terms and the relations between them as offering powerful ways of looking for meditation. &lt;mark&gt;What we actually require is just enough clarification to enable us to meditatively work with the map so that it begins to lead beyond its own terms, its own conceptual structure dissolved in the radical freedom and emptiness into which it opens.&lt;/mark&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;mdash; Chapter 27, Dependent Origination (2)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some, of course, initially encountering either a refusal to establish any valid cognition of conventional truth, or a view such as Mipham’s, which establishes it only contextually, may give rise to suspicion and even annoyance. Yet a profound meditative exploration of dependent arising will likely end up with similar sorts of conclusions to those of Mipham, or lead at least to a letting go of the felt need to define valid conventional cognition. At the same time, as we have repeatedly stressed, and as will be obvious to anyone practising this way, the understanding and freedom that are opened bring no irresponsibility with respect to conventional appearances, no behaviour that harms self or other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it could be said that, as beautiful as the inquiry may be, a clinging to wanting to determine what is ‘really and unequivocally there’ on a conventional level simply betrays a mistaken premise of fundamental delusion. &lt;mark&gt;Perhaps we may say, with the Buddha, that some questions do not need answers. What matters is the freedom and love that comes from realization of the emptiness of all phenomena.&lt;/mark&gt; Still, our inquiry into emptiness involves inquiry into appearances; and since cessation is not regarded as the goal, that inquiry may become a kind of open-ended exploration – of ways of looking and the perceptions of their associated appearances. It is not the assumed objectivity status of its appearances at a conventional level, but the blessing and liberation that any way of looking effects that becomes the primary criterion for judging it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as being ultimately pragmatic, the adoption of a core approach of exploring different ways of looking has been concordant with a fundamental and vital insight right from the start. For it is in fact the fundamental openness of things that allows us the possibility to play with ways of looking and to see their effects on the heart and on perception. From the perspective of this approach, the very least that can be said of a view which, understanding that objects, awareness, and ignorance are all empty, &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; see a world of magical appearances, inseparable from a mind that is ultimately groundless too and beyond time – and &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; sense all of it thus as ‘holy’, ‘blessèd’, or ‘divine’ – is that such a way of looking sees appearances skilfully. What is opened by a view is what is most important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, everything is empty. Heart, appearance, way of looking – these too are void, and actually inseparable. With respect to &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; things appear though, we can acknowledge the primary significance of ways of looking and their effects on the heart, and also some degree of flexibility in perception. At this level, it is certainly clear that the state of the &lt;em&gt;citta&lt;/em&gt; shapes and colours perception. But the truth of the converse is easily recognized as well: perception shapes and colours the &lt;em&gt;citta&lt;/em&gt;. Understanding all this opens a door. &lt;mark&gt;In practice we may, to a degree, shape empty perception in the service of freedom and compassion. When there is insight, we know that how and what we see are not simply givens, but are the colourable and malleable, magical, material of empty appearances.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is space here, and space for reverence and devotion. When we see the void – the open and groundless nature of all things, the inseparability of appearances and emptiness – we recognize anyway just how profound is our participation in this magic of appearances. Then whether fabrication, which is empty, is consciously intended in a certain direction or not, the heart bows to the fathomless wonder and beauty of it all. It can be touched by an inexhaustible amazement, touched again and again by blessedness and relief. In knowing fully the thorough voidness of this and that, of then and now, of there and here, this heart opens, over and over in joy, in awe and release. Free itself, it knows the essential freedom in everything. &lt;em&gt;&amp;mdash; Chapter 31, An Empowerment of Views&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">To mark the completion of the Seeing through Dualities, Deepening in Emptiness course, two of my favourite passages from Seeing That Frees</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wetiko: Healing the Mind-Virus That Plagues Our World</title><link href="/blog/2023/03/04/wetiko.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wetiko: Healing the Mind-Virus That Plagues Our World" /><published>2023-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2023/03/04/wetiko</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2023/03/04/wetiko.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Epilogue from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/57335928-wetiko&quot;&gt;Wetiko: Healing the Mind-Virus That Plagues Our World&lt;/a&gt; by Paul Levy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In times of great social and political upheaval such as we see in the world today, whatever has been suppressed by the prevailing agreed upon attitudes builds up in—and disturbs—the collective unconscious, accumulating enormous energy that needs to be channeled somewhere. If these contents of the activated unconscious remain suppressed, however, there is a great danger that the unconscious will get into the driver’s seat of our vehicle. There it will, so to speak—destructively, instead of constructively—act out in the world what has been blocked from healthy expression and thereby rendered unconscious. Then we will be truly dreaming a nightmare, as we see in the converging world crises that are engulfing us at this current moment in history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes humanity is not saved from a crisis by the products of our conscious intellect, but rather the saving grace comes from something being revealed to us that emerges unexpectedly as a result of the crisis. Revelations—which can be likened to timeless treasures waiting to be discovered in time—come in many forms and in many ways. Sometimes they first emerge seemingly outside of ourselves through—or are triggered by—some external event in the world like the coronavirus outbreak. Ultimately speaking, however, the deepest revelation is something that lies hidden within the nature of our soul awaiting discovery. We have to reveal it out of and from within ourselves, which is a self-sanctifying act needing no outside validation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Awakening Treasures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are treasures buried within us, concealed within our unconscious. These hidden gems are like precious jewels or diamonds in the rough that are encoded within the fabric of the unconscious psyche. They can be conceived of as existing in a higher dimension relative to our conscious mind, and as such, are typically invisible to our intellect. These treasures, having lain buried and dormant in the collective unconscious of our species from time immemorial, are typically awakened in times of great need and duress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the time is ripe, our intuition—due to its connection to our unconscious—divines and begins to “see” the heretofore formless revelation that is gestating in the alchemical cauldron of the unconscious. Our task then becomes how to bring forth and creatively express the revelation in a form that helps it come to fruition as we realize it more clearly within ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential revelation can be conceived of as an innovative force of nature alive in the unconscious. This force is thirsting to incarnate both within our minds and into our world. As if a living entity gestating in the womb of the collective unconscious of humanity, this soon to be revelation will draft a suitably creative person—someone who is sensitive to and resonates with the potential revelation—to become the instrument through which the newborn revelation clothes itself. In this, it takes on a particular individualized form and enters into our third-dimensional world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our spirit, the sentient presence that animates us, is by its very nature creative. The very center of our being is an unknown creative energy that forges us in its likeness, one way or another (with our cooperation or not). As human beings we are a creative force thirsting for conscious realization. Our creativity isn’t as a mere hobby, a sideline, something that we should just indulge in on our days off. The creative spirit is an essential part of our being, the life-giving oxygen for our soul. Creative expression is not merely the embellishment of the forms of life, but the very dynamic of the life force itself taking new forms. The mysterious secret of our being can only be realized via participating in the creative act itself. Knowing is an act of creation in itself; if we want to know creativity, we have to be creative. There are no holy scriptures for this creative activity—we are left to our own devices. Being creative means to partake in our innate godlike spiritual freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can conceive of the creative instinct as a timeless, living impulse implanted in the human psyche that moves through the generations. The inspired individual participates within their own soul in the same creative process that takes place outside of themselves in nature. The creative person follows an unknown directive, a higher authority, what Jung would call the Self, the wholeness and guiding force of the deeper personality. People who are inspired by the creative spirit are oriented toward the invisible, toward a mysterious something that wants to become visible and reveal itself. The creative artist is giving utterance to the authentic and direct revelation of the numinosum, which raises their function to the level of the sacred. “The creative principle,” Erich Neumann writes, is typically venerated “as the hidden treasure that in humble form conceals [and, I might add, simultaneously reveals] a fragment of the godhead.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Listening to the Voice Inside&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wetiko is a “daemonic” energy, which is to say it is a transpersonal energy—beyond the merely personal—that can take over a person (or a group of people). The “daemon” can be envisioned as an indwelling force that can’t be nailed down because of its nomadic nature, taking up residence in those who are receptive to its call. Etymologically speaking, the inner meaning of the word daemon is our guiding spirit, inner voice, internal teacher, muse, spiritual ally, wish-fulfilling genie, and genius. The daemon connects us with our calling, and helps us find our vocation, our mission in life, why we are here on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original meaning of the word vocation has to do with being addressed by a voice. In listening to our inner voice—what Jung calls “the voice of the inner man”—we are at the same time given the sacred responsibility to outwardly speak in the world the voice that is uniquely ours to speak—our true authentic voice. The paradox is that in speaking the voice that is most our own, this voice does not belong to us. Rather it is the voice of all of humanity that resounds in us. The truly creative person, be they poet, writer, dancer, or painter, for instance, is that courageous someone, Jung writes, “voicing aloud what others only dream.” In other words, a creative person gives living form to something that exists in the formless and seemingly insubstantial ethers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demonic is the creative in statu nascendi, “not yet realized,” or “made real” by a conscious ego. This is to say that hidden encoded within the darkness of wetiko is our unexpressed creativity. When the creativity that naturally bubbles forth within us is suppressed, however, it feeds the poisonous aspect of wetiko. The malady that our species is collectively suffering from is, in essence, the fact that we are not connecting with, mobilizing, and expressing our creative nature. Once our creativity is repressed, the daemonic aspect of wetiko becomes demonic, our creativity turns back on itself and manifests destructively—be it within ourselves or out in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To have eyes and not see—to be blind—is an unmistakable symptom of an occlusion to the call of the creative spirit. The figure of the artist is the one who opens humanity’s eyes, teaching us how to see. The black-hole aspect of wetiko is a creativity-destroyer by its very nature, so we need to generate and mobilize as much ingenuity as possible in order to contend with it. Paradoxically, wetiko both spurns and spurs our creative impulses. &lt;mark&gt;The blazing fire of a soul set aflame with its own destiny, burning with the passion of following its deeper calling, fulfilling its mission in life, puts a stake through the heart of the inner vampiric figure of wetiko. The more we pursue what we love, what gives meaning to our lives, the more we allow our creative nature to express itself and the more we “kill” the inner figure of wetiko.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revelation is not something that the conscious ego could have invented by itself, but can only organically arise out of the tension between a stable consciousness and a charged unconscious. To consciously endure this innate creative tension necessarily involves a state of suffering. Describing the creative individual, Neumann writes, “Only by suffering, perhaps unconsciously, under the poverty of his culture and his time can he arrive at the freshly opening source which is destined to quench the thirst of his time.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our own individual suffering of the daemonic energies that pervade and make up the collective unconscious, the spirit within us intimately experiences the profound depths of the woundedness of the collectivity and the time in which we live. Spiritual practitioners and true artists are able to find within their own subjective experience, however, a unique and utterly original response to their wound. As if organs of the collective body politic of humanity, sensitive, spiritually attuned, and creative people are the alchemical retorts in which the poisons, the antidotes, and the psycho-spiritual medicines for the collective are distilled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Healing Power of the Creative Spirit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is no badge of honor or measure of sanity to adapt to a world gone mad. Instead of trying to adapt to the world’s insanity, a person who is awakening remains open to the world—and open to their wounds—such that a regenerative and curative power arises from within their own dark depths in response. This healing power is the creative spirit. The creative impulse is simultaneously an individual and collective phenomenon, which is to say that when any of us becomes a channel for this spirit, it serves all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A creative person’s healing power lies in their willingness to not cling to fixed ideas—of who they are or of the world at large—but to allow themselves to be shaped and informed by new experiences of the world. Then, in turn, they are able to translate and craft these experiences into novel “art”-iculations. This involves a receptivity to authentically and imaginatively respond to the reciprocal interactions and continual collisions—with the inevitable wounding—between ourselves and the world. The litmus test for our creativity is our inspired response—or lack thereof—to these experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hidden treasure, the great revelation that is hidden within our unconscious—also referred mythically as “The Treasure Hard to Attain”—is the creative spirit itself. When tapped into, this spirit is a seemingly inexhaustible source of inspiration within us that issues forth a stream of revelations like a spring bubbling upward from the depths of our unconscious. This living current—our greatest resource—helps us to connect with our source. Whenever it manifests, this vital spirit appears as a revelation in which we are participating as the instrument through which it incarnates in time and space. Our creativity transforms the world so as to find our place in it. To quote philosopher Martin Heidegger, “A work of art is something new in the world that changes the world to allow itself to exist.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our species is desperately in need of the guidance and aid of the boundless creative forces latent within the depths of our unconscious to help us find new ways to resolve the myriad interwoven aspects of our multiple world crises. Creative expression is the zero point at which consciousness and the unconscious momentarily become a generative unity. Only at the point in which the stream of unbridled inspiration emerges from the darkness of the unconscious and enters the light of consciousness, and is thus both at once—darkness and light—is the creative spirit made real in time. As resourceful individuals, it is our job to harness the raw impulses arising from the depths of the unconscious into a form that serves our world. This “creative point,” to again quote Neumann, is “the buried treasure which is the water of life, immortality, fertility, and the after-life all rolled into one.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not the conscious ego that will change the world, but rather, sufficient numbers of people who develop a relationship within themselves between their conscious and unconscious parts who then connect with one another—deepening each other’s inspiration in the process. As long as we remain unaware of the contents of our unconscious—therefore not being able to be the conscious architects of our inner landscape—our ability to transform the outer world will be limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that our widespread systemic crises are the result of a deficiency in human consciousness, it becomes obvious that it is only through an expansion of consciousness that we will be able to navigate the tight passage before us. Consciousness can evolve and develop, however, only where it preserves and cultivates a living connection with the creative powers of the unconscious. Just as our view of the world is a decisive factor in shaping the unconscious, the forces activated in the unconscious reciprocally transform our conscious perspectives. In its collective archetypal dimension the unconscious contains the wisdom and experience of untold ages and could serve as a guide par excellence for us during these troubled times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain individuals gifted with particularly strong intuition sense the moving currents taking place in the collective unconscious and are able to translate these changes into communicable language (verbal and/or nonverbal). These original expressions can potentially spread rapidly—going viral—and have such powerful transformative power because parallel changes have been taking place in the unconscious of other people. Contagious in its effects, genuine creative expression emerging at the right moment can “virally” spread via the unconscious of our species in ways that can ignite latent, creative energy lying dormant in the collective unconscious of humanity. This can bring forth and actualize hidden possibilities (both within us and in the world) into the light of conscious awareness, which is a process that has the power to effect real change in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new idea is itself an expression of a creative act. Certain ideas can assist us in remembering something that we had forgotten we had forgotten. A new idea—such as wetiko—can set up a chain reaction in people’s minds that can potentially unleash previously unimagined insight and creativity. As part of their design, mind-expanding ideas are meant to be shared with others so as to fully activate their nonlocal benefit and blessing. These ideas endlessly increase in potency the more they are shared among us. Like a key unlocking a door or like a charm that breaks a spell, a new symbolic idea can unleash the dormant creative spirit imprisoned within us. A revolutionary idea has the potential to catalyze revolutions in thinking; a shift in a single idea can precipitate a shift into a new epoch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The creativity of the unconscious psyche—which is an agency in a state of never-ending re-creation and re-formation—continually transforms our experience of reality as well as itself. As an artist of life, we are what Neumann refers to as a “bearer of the divine miracle,” actively and endlessly participating in re-creating ourselves anew, revealing ourselves—to ourselves—through the bringing forth of our gifts to the world. Only in these acts do we actualize our wholeness. Acting out of our wholeness is like kryptonite to the seeming superpowers of wetiko. &lt;mark&gt;In being creative we not only find refuge from the dangers of wetiko, but we discover the true revelation that is none other than ourselves. Each new act of creativity brings with it an element of self-discovery. We must create in order to know ourselves.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When human beings are deprived of their freedom and power of expression, however, they will unconsciously express themselves in the drive for power. This only feeds the will to power of the demonic and destructive shadow, with the baneful consequences we see in the world today. Being oppressed in our expression, instead of stopping us cold, however, can potentially—if we so choose—fuel our creative fire, forging in us an “inner necessity” to connect with the living primal generative spirit that lives within us. The authentic creative spirit—if it’s the real thing—can’t be discouraged or kept down for long, for then it wouldn’t be creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Artists as Molders of the Collective Unconscious&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote poet Allen Ginsberg, “The warfare’s psychic now. Whoever controls the language, the images, controls the race.” Instruments of war in the hands of generals are extremely dangerous. In the same way, nothing is more dangerous and potentially world-transforming than implements of creative expression in the hands of artists. They are the molders of the unconscious psychic life of humanity, the mythmakers of their age. It is the artists—and we are all artists—who are the healers of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than letting our perceptions be managed and manipulated by the powers that be and their propaganda organs, we as sovereign beings can connect with our own perceptions and create our own unique and authentic experience of the world and a refreshed experience of ourselves. What a radical—and truly liberating—idea!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healing wetiko entails each of us becoming an empiricist—there is no getting around this. In this we must simply inquire directly into the nature of our present moment experience, without giving credence to what any outer authority is telling us is true. Ultimately speaking, we ourselves are the arbiters of our own experience. By our very nature, we are interpreters of our experience and generators of meaning. This is a process that affects our experience of both ourselves and of the universe at large. Realizing our own creative agency is where we find ourselves, which is the beginning of the cure for wetiko as well as the cure itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we creatively express our nature, it is nature itself that is doing the talking. Then there’s nothing to do but listen and respond in kind to our unique and individual call.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Epilogue from the book by Paul Levy</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond Privacy: The Seven Darknesses of Lunarpunk</title><link href="/blog/2022/09/30/beyond-privacy-the-seven-darknesses-of-lunarpunk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Privacy: The Seven Darknesses of Lunarpunk" /><published>2022-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2022/09/30/beyond-privacy-the-seven-darknesses-of-lunarpunk</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022/09/30/beyond-privacy-the-seven-darknesses-of-lunarpunk.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You darkness from which I come,&lt;br&gt;
I love you more than all the fires&lt;br&gt;
that fence out the world,&lt;br&gt;
for the fire makes a circle&lt;br&gt;
for everyone&lt;br&gt;
so that no one sees you anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But darkness holds it all:&lt;br&gt;
the shape and the flame,&lt;br&gt;
the animal and myself,&lt;br&gt;
how it holds them,&lt;br&gt;
all powers, all sight –&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and it is possible: its great strength&lt;br&gt;
is breaking into my body.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have faith in the night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Rainer Maria Rilke&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunk first rose to the attention of the web3 community via the essay &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.egirlcapital.com/writings/107533289&quot;&gt;Lunarpunk and the Dark Side of the Cycle&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lunar_mining&quot;&gt;@lunar_mining&lt;/a&gt; in February 2022. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite a note there that lunarpunk is &amp;quot;the solar shadow-self&amp;quot;, the author goes on to define lunarpunk overwhelmingly in terms of privacy, anonymity and a &amp;quot;conflict between crypto and existing power structures&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this piece I seek a broader notion of lunarpunk, returning to the idea of the &amp;quot;solar shadow-self&amp;quot; and exploring lunarpunk in its most general form as &lt;em&gt;the dark side of solarpunk&lt;/em&gt;, a complementary opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I identify privacy/anonymity as just one of Seven Darknesses of Lunarpunk, each with an associated &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/age-of-awareness/psychotechnology-and-the-multi-state-future-of-humanity-37a31a506022&quot;&gt;(psycho)technology&lt;/a&gt;: the Darknesses of &lt;strong&gt;Privacy, Attention, Suffering, Eros, Plants, Soul and Light&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks understand that there is nothing inherently bad or wrong about the dark, and to speak of darkness is not to suggest the &lt;em&gt;sinister&lt;/em&gt;. Rather, the commonality between the tools, techniques and technologies featured here is an association with &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;unconscious, the shadow&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;the taboo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of Privacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key technology: cryptography, as explored in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.egirlcapital.com/writings/107533289&quot;&gt;Lunarpunk and the Dark Side of the Cycle&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lunar_mining&quot;&gt;@lunar_mining&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/image/1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Strong cryptography can resist an unlimited application of violence. No amount of coercive force will ever solve a math problem.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/16153182-cypherpunks&quot;&gt;Cypherpunks: Freedom and the Future of the Internet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;What’s the most powerful force on earth? In the 1800s, God. In the 1900s, the US military. And by the mid-2000s, encryption.. It doesn’t matter how many nuclear weapons you have; if property or information is secured by cryptography, the state can’t seize it without getting the solution to an equation.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenetworkstate.com/god-state-network&quot;&gt;The Network State&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks are masters of cryptography. They understand how pseudonymity grants not just freedom of speech, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehub.ca/in-the-know/2021-06-10/what-is-the-pseudonymous-economy-balaji-srinivasan/&quot;&gt;freedom after speech&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of Attention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: mastering of submissive/dominant attention, as explored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kasiaurbaniak.com/&quot;&gt;Kasia Urbaniak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/image/2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;I understood that both the Taoist nuns and dominatrices I most admired were powerful precisely because they could control that conversation under the conversation—and it wasn’t through a self-conscious manipulation of their body language. Instead, they did so with something far more powerful and primal: their attention.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What I had been learning in the desert, in the dojo, and in the dungeon, then, could be summed up this way: the art of attention. Attention dictates where the energy is—the juice, the qi, the life force—in any given interaction. It is how our animal bodies communicate with one another. Language is important; so are physical gestures. But more important than both is where the attention is directed.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/51205436-unbound&quot;&gt;Unbound&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks are masters of attention, both submissive (inward) and dominant (outward). They practise a dominance that has nothing to do with the violent, toxic mimic of power we see so often in the world, and a submission that is never obsequious or subservient. Rather, in both states, they and those around them experience a deep sense of relaxation and flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of Suffering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50915816-existential-kink&quot;&gt;Existential Kink&lt;/a&gt; by Carolyn Elliott&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/image/3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;One does not become enlightened by imagining figures of light, but by making the darkness conscious… Until you make the unconscious, conscious, it will rule your life and you will call it Fate.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; ― C.G. Jung&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;It&amp;#39;s impossible to desire something without also fearing it a bit, and it&amp;#39;s impossible to fear and dislike something without also desiring it.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/50915816-existential-kink&quot;&gt;Existential Kink&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks are highly attuned to their fears, aversions and dislikes, and see all of these as an opportunity for growth. They understand the freedom that comes from acknowledgement of the taboo, the disowned and the repressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of Eros&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: harnessing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/RadicalWomenCommunity/posts/pfbid02xdxph6ZhNqzb4omvz2uFUnzxL5Z9eHARmxkxTh68N5exSWY1R5RbYd4yqhMeFRXRl&quot;&gt;Light/Dark Masculine/Feminine&lt;/a&gt; as explored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ista.life/trainings/ista-level-2&quot;&gt;ISTA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/image/4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;The DARK FEMININE: sensual pleasure, erotic wisdom, emotional fluidity, and naked authenticity. This energy has a sexual sovereignty, the capacity to attract/magnetize, and the willingness to feel everything, even the most apparently ugly, desperate, and suffering parts of life. The shadow expression is manipulation, power games, chaoticness, vengeance, and emotionally explosive. The stunted version is frigidity (rejection or judgment of sensual and sexual pleasure), and emotionally, physically or sexually detached.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rememberyourself.live/a-brief-introduction-to-the-cross/&quot;&gt;A Brief Introduction to The Cross&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks healthily express all four archetypes of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/RadicalWomenCommunity/posts/pfbid02xdxph6ZhNqzb4omvz2uFUnzxL5Z9eHARmxkxTh68N5exSWY1R5RbYd4yqhMeFRXRl&quot;&gt;dark/light masculine/feminine&lt;/a&gt; cross. In particular, they understand the distinction between &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecross.one/initiation-into-the-feminine-for-women&quot;&gt;evil, shadow and darkness&lt;/a&gt; and have harnessed the dark energies for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of Plants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: plant medicine, especially ayahuasca (&amp;quot;vine of death&amp;quot;) as practised by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://niweraoxobo.com/&quot;&gt;Shipibo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/image/5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Ayahuasca is not a recreational drug taken for entertainment, relaxation, or escapism. The medicine does not allow us to suppress issues and escape reality. In fact, quite the opposite is typically the case. Ayahuasca compels us to face, resolve, and release issues that have been buried throughout our lives.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://templeofthewayoflight.org/integrating-ayahuasca/facing-your-shadow/&quot;&gt;Temple of the Way of Light&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;The fact that Westerners will seek out a foul-tasting jungle medicine in a faraway environment and culture, a medicine that frequently leads to violent purging and can include terrifying visions, is a remarkable paradox.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://templeofthewayoflight.org/integrating-ayahuasca/facing-your-shadow/&quot;&gt;Ralph Metzner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks are intimately familiar with the healing power of plant medicines, particularly those used in &lt;a href=&quot;https://templeofthewayoflight.org/shamanism-ayahuasca/shipibo-energy-healing/&quot;&gt;night-time ceremonies&lt;/a&gt;. They embrace mystery and approach indigenous wisdom with respect and humility, accepting the possibility of mechanisms not yet understood by science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness of the Soul&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/books/soulcraft/&quot;&gt;Soulcraft&lt;/a&gt; by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/&quot;&gt;Animas Valley Institute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/image/6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;In the course of healthy human development, we are each meant to reach this breakpoint, this crisis, this divide beyond which we’re no longer able to decisively define ourselves in terms of social or romantic relationships, or in terms of a job or career, a creative or artistic project, a political affiliation, a theory or philosophical perspective, a religious or ethnic membership, or a transcendental spiritual goal. We are propelled — compelled! — toward an underworld self-definition, a soul-infused experience of meaning and purpose and identity. True for all humans, this is our evolutionary birthright, a necessary passage on the way from psychological adolescence to true adulthood… The mainstream currents of our contemporary cultures neither assert nor deny the existence of an underworld identity; it has simply disappeared from awareness.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/the-realm-of-purpose-least-realized-but-most-essential-in-our-time-of-radical-global-change/&quot;&gt;Bill Plotkin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunarpunks are practitioners of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/books/soulcraft/&quot;&gt;Soulcraft&lt;/a&gt;, seeking to become ever more aware of their unique &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/glossary-to-language-of-soul-canyon/#mythopoetic%20identity&quot;&gt;mythopoetic identity&lt;/a&gt; through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.animas.org/glossary-to-language-of-soul-canyon/#Descent%20to%20Soul&quot;&gt;Descent to Soul&lt;/a&gt;. Soulcraft practices include dreamwork and deep-imagery journeys, solo ceremonies and exercises while wandering on the land, trance dancing and drumming, council work, storytelling, vision fasts, symbolic artwork, soul-oriented poetry, Shadow work, and communicating with birds, trees, the winds, and the land and waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Darkness in Light&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key psychotechnology: Meditations on Emptiness and Dependent Arising as explored in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25172403-seeing-that-frees&quot;&gt;Seeing That Frees&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://tasshin.com/blog/rob-burbea-ordinary-guy-werewolf-eternal-wanderer/&quot;&gt;Rob Burbea&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/image/7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;img&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;They are the same thing, but our lazy mind separates darkness from light. To plunge into the light, to find darkness in light, to find Buddha nature in perfect zazen is our way.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/361898.Branching_Streams_Flow_in_the_Darkness&quot;&gt;Shunryu Suzuki Roshi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through meditative practice, lunarpunks approach the understanding that ultimately, there is no separation between darkness and light – rather, they are &amp;#39;dependently arising&amp;#39; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prat%C4%ABtyasamutp%C4%81da&quot;&gt;paṭiccasamuppāda&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every characterisation of lunarpunk in this piece is simply an opinion (mine), an offering – I make no claim to the right to define the term any more than the next &amp;#39;punk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is clear to me, though, is that lunarpunk existed before web3 and exists beyond it. I hope this piece stimulates useful discussions on holistic and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/age-of-awareness/a-metamodern-guide-to-human-development-49fe8d8f0e8f&quot;&gt;developmentally-focused&lt;/a&gt; notions of both solarpunk and lunarpunk in the web3 space and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scienceandnonduality.com/article/david-bohm-implicate-order-and-holomovement&quot;&gt;May we continue to move towards wholeness&lt;/a&gt;, embracing both dark and light 🌓&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;New blog post – Beyond Privacy: The Seven Darknesses of Lunarpunk:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Darkness of Privacy&lt;br&gt;Darkness of Attention&lt;br&gt;Darkness of Suffering&lt;br&gt;Darkness of Eros&lt;br&gt;Darkness of Plants&lt;br&gt;Darkness of the Soul&lt;br&gt;Darkness in Light&lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/MiGa5vHLF1&quot;&gt;https://t.co/MiGa5vHLF1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Stephen Reid ☯️ (@lunarpunk_0x) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lunarpunk_0x/status/1575970584789295104?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;September 30, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Expanding notions of lunarpunk in web3</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Coach maturity: An emerging concept</title><link href="/blog/2022/08/04/coach-maturity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coach maturity: An emerging concept" /><published>2022-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-08-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2022/08/04/coach-maturity</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2022/08/04/coach-maturity.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidclutterbuckpartnership.com/wp-content/uploads/Coach-maturity.pdf&quot;&gt;Professor David Clutterbuck and Professor David Megginson&lt;/a&gt;. Highlights my own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coaching sometimes seems like Keats’ rainbow – the more we try to define it, dissect it, classify it and demystify it, the more we diminish it and lose its essence. One of the concerns both of us have about so much of the coaching literature is that it represents attempts to confine coaching within the partisan wrappings of a particular school, philosophy or approach. Such narrow and sometimes self-serving perspectives seem to us to be completely at odds with the essential ethos of coaching – &lt;mark&gt;enquiring, open, inclusive, subtle and multi-perspective&lt;/mark&gt;. This perspective has been called ‘relational coaching’ by Erik de Haan and colleagues (de Haan, 2008).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, we accept and encourage the notion of quality in coaching, even though we may struggle even more in defining what that, too, means. Ingredients in a definition of quality of coaching might be posited to include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The delivery of intended and positive &lt;mark&gt;unintended&lt;/mark&gt; outcomes. &lt;mark&gt;Simply delivering against the initial, presented goal is not necessarily an indicator of quality&lt;/mark&gt;, for a number of reasons:

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The goal may be the wrong one&lt;/mark&gt; for the client and or the organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Achieving goal clarity may be the end point&lt;/mark&gt;, not the beginning of the coaching assignment – &lt;mark&gt;many clients need coaching to establish what they want and why, but are self-sufficient in thinking through how they are going to achieve it&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even coaching at a relatively low level of competence can achieve change in the client. &lt;mark&gt;Simply being there and allowing the client to talk things through can be remarkably effective, where the client needs only to structure their own thinking&lt;/mark&gt;. The primary skills required in such cases are attentive listening and knowing when to shut up!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depth of rapport, which may in turn relate to attentiveness, awareness of one’s own values, and authenticity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Energy: Observation of coaches in assessment centre ‘real plays’ suggests that &lt;mark&gt;the most effective coaches create simultaneously an intense stillness and an intense energy field&lt;/mark&gt;. &lt;mark&gt;The space between them and the client almost crackles!&lt;/mark&gt; By contrast, the least effective coaches seem to suck energy from the room, dissipating energy as they flail about seeking to “plug in” to the client and his or her issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A systemic approach to the coaching dynamic. The coaching context extends beyond the individual client to the human and organizational systems, in which they operate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Observations about coaches and coaching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our observations of many coaches in and out of action in the context of coach assessment centers suggests that &lt;mark&gt;it may be easier to define what does not define quality&lt;/mark&gt; – for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Having a certificate or diploma&lt;/mark&gt;. At best this is a hygiene factor, indicating that the coach has undergone some form of training in the role. But rigorous assessment shows that &lt;mark&gt;many “certified” coaches are severely lacking in competence&lt;/mark&gt;, while many of the most effective coaches are “naturals”, who bring to the role a mixture of innate intuitiveness and reflection on experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having individual accreditation. The International Coach Federation, the Association for Coaching, the European Mentoring and Coaching Council and others (Brennan and Whybrow, 2010) have set up systems for individual accreditation. This seeks – more directly than certification – to measure something akin to maturity. However it largely shows that the coach is good enough, rather than how far on a personal journey they have travelled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Client satisfaction. Some clients may over-rate the efficacy of their coaches, confusing empathetic conversation (simply having someone listen to them) with transformational dialogue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fee rates. We have found a variation of 15 to 1 in fees charged per hour, but &lt;mark&gt;no significant correlation with quality of coaching delivered&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our reflections to reconcile the spontaneity, dynamism and variety of coaching with the need to maintain standards lead to the conclusion that simplistic classifications are likely to be divisive and of dubious validity. What’s needed is a conceptual framework that reflects the evolution of complexity in coaches’ way of thinking about themselves, their clients and the context, in which they operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A possible solution may lie in the context of maturity. In the sense of the development of human beings, a number of authors have proposed models of the &lt;mark&gt;evolution of maturity&lt;/mark&gt;. These models broadly assume that changes in the structure of thinking about oneself and the world, with which we interact, &lt;mark&gt;evolve slowly and in recognisable, sequential patterns&lt;/mark&gt;; that &lt;mark&gt;higher levels involve a greater degree of awareness about the individual’s environment, and greater complexity in how they interpret their environment&lt;/mark&gt;; that evolving through one level is an essential precursor to the next; that cognitive and socio-emotional responses at earlier levels may remain open and available, even though the individual’s “centre of gravity” is at a higher level; that people evolve at different rates; and that only a small proportion of the population become centred in the highest levels of maturity. These models tend to emphasize either cognitive-reflective processes or ego-development (Bachkirova and Cox, 2007), meaning “the development of self-identity and maturing of interpersonal relationships”. Key authors here include Torbert (1991), Wilber (2000), Cook-Greuter (2004), Beck &amp;amp; Cowan (1996) and Kegan (1992).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Bachkirova and Cox express it: “What is particularly important in relation to development of coaches is that each stage enriches individual capacity for reflection and effective interaction with others. Their ability to notice nuances and details of situations is increasing. The resultant self-awareness gives them a better opportunity to articulate, influence and potentially change these situations.” Otto Laske (2006, 2009), who has built in particular upon Kegan’s approaches, maintains additionally that in a coaching context the relative maturity of the coach and client are significant in the relationship dynamic. Most importantly, if the coach is less cognitively or socio- emotionally mature than the client, this is likely to have a significant and negative impact on the quality of the coaching process. Chandler and Kram (2005) make a similar point with regard to the related activity of mentoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mindsets and models&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our own interpretations of coach maturity are not based on empirical research, but we hope they will stimulate such research and serve as a starting point for debate. Our model derives from observation in a variety of contexts, but particularly within coach assessment centers, where it is possible to benchmark coaches against consistent criteria, and hence to reflect on characteristics and thinking patterns exhibited by coaches of different levels of demonstrated competence. It is important to emphasise here that we are not equating maturity and competence as the same construct. However, it is reasonable to conclude that they are closely related.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The four levels are models-based, process-based, philosophy or discipline-based, and systemic eclectic.&lt;/mark&gt; &lt;mark&gt;Models-based coaches&lt;/mark&gt; are often very new to the field and seek the re-assurance of a closely defined approach that they can take into any situation they might meet. This type of coaching is characterised by mechanistic conversations, where following the model is more important than exploring the client’s world. It is about doing rather than being and tends to be about coaching to the client than coaching with the client; and about the coaching intervention, rather than the coaching relationship. The dangerous myth that a good coach can coach anyone in any situation appears to stem from this very narrow perception of coaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Process-based approaches&lt;/mark&gt; allow for more flexibility. They can be considered as a structured linking of related techniques and models. The coach has a number of specific tools to use in helping the client’s thinking, but the toolbag is still relatively limited. Solutions focus, for example, assumes that the client’s immediate need is to find a solution, but in practice, many clients simply want to build a greater understanding of their situation and/or to come to terms with a problem that is inherently insoluble. Yet there are many coaching situations where the emotional engagement between coach and client provides the most powerful resource for change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Philosophy or discipline based mindsets&lt;/mark&gt; tend to offer a wider still portfolio of responses to client needs, because they operate within a broad set of assumptions about helping and human development. They can still be applied mechanistically, however. What prevents them being so is the coach’s ability to reflect on his or her practice, both while coaching and after each coaching session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The fourth, most liberating mindset is the systemic eclectic.&lt;/mark&gt; These coaches have a very wide array of ways of working and a toolkit amassed from many sources, both within couching and from very different worlds. They have integrated this into a self- aware, personalized way of being with the client. They exhibit an intelligent, sensitive ability to select a broad approach, and within that approach, appropriate tools and techniques, which meet the particular needs of a particular client at a particular time. This relates to what Webb (2008) calls coaching for wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observation of and discussion with a sample of systemic eclectic coaches suggests that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;They have immense calm, because they have confidence in their ability to find the right tool if they need it&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Yet they hardly ever use tools&lt;/mark&gt;. When they do, it is subtly and integrated almost seamlessly into the conversation. Indeed, they allow the conversation to happen, &lt;mark&gt;holding the client in the development of insight and steering with only the lightest, almost imperceptible touches&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They place great importance on understanding a technique, model or process in terms of its origins within an original philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use experimentation and reflexive learning to identify where and how a new technique, model or process fits into their philosophy and framework of helping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They judge new techniques, models and processes on the criterion of “Will this enrich and improve the effectiveness of my potential responses to client needs?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They use peers and supervisors to challenge their coaching philosophy and as partners in experimenting with new approaches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They take a systemic and holistic view of the client and the client’s environment; and of the coaching relationship; and this makes them more sensitive to nuances of the situation and hence to what approaches they can employ&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Table 1: A comparison of the four levels of coaching maturity in coaching conversations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Coaching approach&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Style&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Critical questions&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Models-based&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Control&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;How do I take them where I think they need to go?&lt;br /&gt;How do I adapt my technique or model to this circumstance?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Process-based&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Contain&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;How do I give enough control to the client and still retain a purposeful conversation?&lt;br /&gt;What’s the best way to apply my process in this instance?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philosophy-based&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Facilitate&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;What can I do to help the client do this for themselves?&lt;br /&gt;How do I contextualise the client’s issue within the perspective of my philosophy or discipline?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Systemic eclectic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Enable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Are we both relaxed enough to allow the issue and the solution to emerge in whatever way they will? &lt;br /&gt;Do I need to apply any techniques or processes at all?&lt;br /&gt;If I do, what does the client context tell me about how to select from the wide choice available to me?&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observation in coach assessment centers gave us the basis for proposing an approach, which does more closely parallel other models of maturation. Areas where mature coaches demonstrate that they have reflected deeply include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personal philosophy of coaching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding of the business context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freedom from the tyranny of the question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they use coach supervision and mentoring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they maintain professional development and integrate learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they identify and manage boundaries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their personal journey as a coach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowing what kind of clients and situations they work best with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding what makes a fully functioning individual&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding what makes an effective organisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Personal philosophy of coaching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although ontology has developed specific meaning as a genre of coaching practice, in the more generic sense of coaching as “being about being”, mature coaches tend to reflect more deeply on the nature of the interaction between themselves and their clients. Their reflections lead them to an understanding of this interaction that goes far beyond textbook explanations of the coaching process, whether these derive from models-based, process-based or discipline-based approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They integrate their learning from such sources, with reflection on their experiences with clients, to develop and articulate a unique and personal perspective of the coaching dynamic. Some parallels can be drawn here with Kegan’s stages of adult maturity (1992). Absorbing values and beliefs of others – accepted wisdom – whether consciously or unconsciously, is perhaps typical of Kegan’s level three. As they mature, coaches question these “given” beliefs and begin to develop their own, self-authored perspectives, based on their own experience and reasoning. This suggests Kegan’s level four. &lt;mark&gt;Some go a step further, challenging their own self-focused assumptions, embracing uncertainties and letting go of any sense of needing to exert control over the conversation. For example, they may see coaching as a process of shared meaning making, in which the client’s values and perspectives have equal validity to their own.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Understanding the business context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;One of the most pernicious myths about coaching is that coaches need no contextual knowledge of the client’s world.&lt;/mark&gt; Whether born of self-aggrandizement or a mechanistic view of coaching, this is manifestly untrue, on two counts – client safety (and hence ethicality) and efficacy. In sports coaching, it is important to know enough to ensure that the client is not led to adopt behaviors, which might be detrimental to themselves. Similarly in the business world, a coach working with top managers, who has poor knowledge of corporate governance rules, poses a risk both to the client and to him or herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an efficacy perspective, the coach has to have enough contextual knowledge first to demonstrate empathy and build rapport and credibility with the client. Secondly, construct questions that stimulate significant insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coach assessment observations show clearly that the most effective coaches ask questions and make supportive comments that demonstrate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A broad understanding of the client’s world (not necessarily of the client’s specific job role or function)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Knowledge of the “big themes” affecting the organization and the industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An ability to link day-to-day issues for the client with these big themes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Of course, having too close an understanding of the client’s world also has its downsides. In particular, it leads the coach instinctively to come up with their own answers and suppressing these may divert attention from listening to the client.&lt;/mark&gt; Mature coaches work to give up a directive, “I’ve been there” approach. &lt;mark&gt;It seems, from observation, that the most effective coaches are often those, who have enough knowledge to contextualize questions, yet are able to maintain a deep, curious and constructive naiveté.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Freedom from the tyranny of the question&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Systemic eclectic coaches give themselves permission to do less, with resultant great efficacy. In classroom experiments, we have artificially limited the number of times coaches can speak, to only once in every 10 minutes, on average. In almost all cases, coaches’ and coachees’ perception of the quality of the dialogue and, in particular, of the questions asked, is higher than under normal conditions. &lt;mark&gt;Our observation of systemic eclectics is that they are almost miserly with their questions, giving the client maximum time for reflection before they will nudge them gently along in their thinking.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Use of coach supervision or mentoring&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although all the major coaching professional bodies require member coaches to have some form of coach supervision or mentoring, remarkably few coaches seem to have developed a mental model that embraces supervision as a core activity in their practice. For many, it appears to be a tick the box requirement, with little proactivity and little practical relevance to their development as coaches. Peer coaching, in particular, can become a collusive, self-congratulatory activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have very little evidence with regard to how coaches at different levels of maturity approach supervision, but we can posit that there might be differences in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they choose their coach supervisor or mentor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The psychological contract they have with their supervisor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they decide what to take to supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they prepare for supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they reflect upon supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they ensure the quality of the supervision they receive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their awareness of specific changes that have happened in them and their practice as a result of coach supervision.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We suspect – but do not yet have evidence to support – that &lt;mark&gt;mature coaches would tend to have more developed, more proactive approaches to coach supervision and mentoring.&lt;/mark&gt; Certainly, in assessment centers, more mature coaches tend to give clearer, more specific responses to all of the seven issues above. From comments by systemic eclectics, we glean a number of possible differentiators, which include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sense of needing to be challenged fundamentally by supervision – and hence to &lt;mark&gt;choose supervisors, whose background and perspective is dissimilar to their own&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The use of more than one supervisor, to provide different perspectives and challenges – for example, &lt;mark&gt;one with a strong formal psychological background and one with a deeper business background&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration of supervision and self-supervision&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Personal development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What might a mature approach towards self-development as a coach look like? Based on a small sample of systemic eclectics, they might exhibit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Openness to a wide spectrum of learning opportunities – reading, exploration with peers, supervision, conferences, workshops and so on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-coaching – proposing insightful questions to themselves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Networked learning – building around them a network of peers, who bring different perspectives but a similar dedication to learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engagement with research and/or development of the profession – for example, using writing as a vehicle for self-discovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Boundaries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to be a psychologist to recognise phenomena such as projection, dependency or sociopathy. But you do need at least some understanding of psychological and behavioural processes. Assessment centres have, however, revealed some very dangerous coaches, who have little appreciation of boundaries. For example, the coach, who claimed to have done 4000 hours of coaching, but could not think of a single occasion when he had met a boundary issue!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Your personal journey as a coach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common to all theories of maturity is a sense of progression. Inherent in the concept of wisdom is the use of reflection to raise awareness of both current and precursor states. Integral to the assessment centre design is a description of the coach’s learning journey – how they make current sense of their evolution towards their current level of practice. &lt;mark&gt;For many, the learning journey appears to have begun and ended with a certificate or other formal recognition as a coach.&lt;/mark&gt; Their practical experience with clients has largely reinforced the “given” knowledge, rather than inspired them to question it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further along the maturity spectrum, we extrapolate, coaches are able to articulate critical shifts in their awareness of themselves as coaches, of the coach-client relationship and of the coaching process. A little further along again, they are able to describe – albeit often with hesitancy – where the journey appears to be taking them. It seems that, as with other maturity models, they are aware that the centre of gravity of their maturity level is shifting and they are searching for client opportunities, insights and pivotal conversations that will assist that movement, even if their vision of where it will take them is still somewhat hazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Knowing who they work best with&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;It is arguable that all coaches are better suited to some clients and situations than others.&lt;/mark&gt; Key factors here may be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether transfer (of knowledge/expertise) is an important dynamic in the role&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The client’s perceptions (rightly or wrongly) about the importance of the coach’s background and experience either inside or outside the context of coaching&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The depth of psychological/ behavioural competence required to help the client understand their issues and maintain client safety&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The perceived relative status of coach and client.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coaches bring different kinds of life experience, and corporate buyers tend to place a higher value on coaches who have client credibility by virtue of their own experience at senior executive level. (However, assessment center data suggest that a high level of experience in management, when not accompanied by a high level of coaching maturity, represents poor value for money and may sometimes do more harm than good.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conception of a fully functioning person&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many coaches Rogers’ (1961) conception of a fully functioning person may describe the coach’s perception of what it means to be human. Many ex-executives have a much more business–like model. Whatever model one has, it is useful to articulate it, so that clients know where the coach is coming from and the coach realises that views or hints about what the client might do or aspire to, come from a position rather than appearing out of thin air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Making the transition to a system eclectic coach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can and do coaches mature into systemic eclectics? One ingredient is likely to be time. Malcolm Gladwell (2008) summarises research into exceptional performance in a range of activities from business to sport and suggests that it takes 10,000 hours to achieve mastery in any field. Certainly, all the systemic eclectics we have observed have been involved with coaching – or with related disciplines – for a good many years. &lt;mark&gt;But putting in the hours does not automatically create mastery – there has additionally to be an immense amount of reflection, experimentation and adaption of practice.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For systemic eclectics, we observe that the learning they acquire shows them how much more they could learn. It’s like climbing a mountain – the higher you ascend, the bigger and more distant the horizon. Feeling comfortable with this diminishing perspective of one’s own importance and competence relative to what might conceivably be possible, requires a great deal of personal maturity, we suspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is one characteristic of systemic eclectics, which can potentially be learned and used by coaches at any level of maturity – and can possibly speed the transition between levels – it is this ability to savour where you are, to contextualise it and to be able to look both forwards and backwards along the path. Accepting and valuing your current state may be the critical component in achieving the next level of maturity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Defining quality in coaching</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An introduction to platform co-ops</title><link href="/blog/2020/11/22/an-introduction-to-platform-coops.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An introduction to platform co-ops" /><published>2020-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/11/22/an-introduction-to-platform-coops</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/11/22/an-introduction-to-platform-coops.html">&lt;h2&gt;What does &amp;#39;platform&amp;#39; mean here?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The word ‘platform’ is often used to describe &lt;mark&gt;an internet service which brings together suppliers and consumers in an online marketplace&lt;/mark&gt;. But platforms don’t necessarily provide traditional ‘products’; they often facilitate the trade of services, like taxis or temporary accommodation. Most people have heard of Uber and Airbnb, whose platforms have disrupted the minicab and short-term lettings industries while generating enormous profits for their shareholders.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.coop/2016/12/02/introduction-platform-co-ops/&quot;&gt;An introduction to platform co-ops&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Platform capitalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The rise of the platform economy over the last decade promised to boost flexible employment, extra income, and collaborative consumption. Instead, &lt;mark&gt;the ‘disruption’ of the digital economy has removed regulations, increased precariousness of work, and created the conditions for market monopolies dominated by a handful of digital giants&lt;/mark&gt;.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uk.coop/start-new-co-op/support/start-platform-co-op/why-platform-co-ops&quot;&gt;Why platform co-ops?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;More and more people are organising their work and resources through digital platforms. The marketplace for these is dominated by a small number of large corporations: be it Uber drivers, freelancers on TaskRabbit or Amazon’s Mechanical Turk marketplace, home rentals on Airbnb or food deliveries using Deliveroo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These digital platforms offer people unprecedented flexibility and independence. The barriers to entry to becoming a taxi driver, a holiday apartment landlord, or freelance worker are now incredibly low, and it’s never been easier to be a consumer on the other side of these markets. But while these positives are acknowledged, &lt;mark&gt;large platform companies have also been criticised for being exploitative, monopolistic and extractivist&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, this system has been described as &lt;mark&gt;platform capitalism&lt;/mark&gt;. &lt;mark&gt;In this system a large number of consumers and vendors generate profits which accrue to a comparatively small number of people&lt;/mark&gt;… Ordinary users who rely on these platforms typically find they have little control over their personal data and have no say about how they are run. It has led to the formation of monopolies that encourage financial extraction and the monetisation of personal data.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://media.nesta.org.uk/documents/Nesta_Platform_Report_FINAL-WEB_b1qZGj7.pdf&quot;&gt;Platform co-operatives – solving the capital conundrum&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Why we need platform co-operatives in the digital economy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What is a platform co-op?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;A platform cooperative, or platform co-op, is &lt;mark&gt;a cooperatively owned, democratically governed business that establishes a computing platform, and uses a website, mobile app or a protocol to facilitate the sale of goods and services&lt;/mark&gt;. Platform cooperatives are an alternative to venture capital-funded platforms insofar as they are owned and governed by those who depend on them most—workers, users, and other relevant stakeholders.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/12/20/8309&quot;&gt;Platform and Data Co-Operatives Amidst European Pandemic Citizenship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;A platform co-op is a &lt;mark&gt;digital platform&lt;/mark&gt; that is designed to provide a service or sell a product, and that is &lt;mark&gt;collectively owned and governed&lt;/mark&gt; by the people who depend on and participate in it.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://media.nesta.org.uk/documents/Nesta_Platform_Report_FINAL-WEB_b1qZGj7.pdf&quot;&gt;Platform co-operatives – solving the capital conundrum&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;The origins of platform co-operatives&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Just like traditional co-ops, platform co-ops are organisations that are owned and managed by their members. &lt;mark&gt;While traditional co-ops are normally based around a physical community of members, platform co-ops live online and are normally populated by online communities of members&lt;/mark&gt;.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://open.coop/2016/12/02/introduction-platform-co-ops/&quot;&gt;An introduction to platform co-ops&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Two types of co-op, as platforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Worker co-ops&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;A workers’ co-op [is] a business owned and managed collectively by its workers for their mutual benefit. It’s organised democratically and fairly by (and only by) its members.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seedsforchange.org.uk/workersco-ops.pdf&quot;&gt;Seeds for Change: How to set up a Workers' Co-op&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Stocksy United: a platform worker co-op where the members are individuals&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stocksy.com/&quot;&gt;Stocksy United&lt;/a&gt; provides curated stock photography and video footage with almost 1000 photographer member-owners, across 63 countries. The members license creative content and receive 50% royalties on standard license sales and 75% on extended license sales – they also receive dividends which equated to $300,000 in 2016 on $10.7m in sales.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Up &amp;amp; Go: a platform worker co-op where the members are organisations (a platform consortia)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.upandgo.coop/&quot;&gt;Up &amp;amp; Go&lt;/a&gt; is a platform that offers on-demand cleaning services at guaranteed fair wages launched by four worker co-operatives, based in New York City. The worker-owned cleaning businesses, which are all majority women owned, earn 95% of the cost of every Up &amp;amp; Go cleaning job. The remaining 5% supports the costs to maintain the platform.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Multi-stakeholder co-ops&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;mark&gt;Multi-stakeholder cooperatives are co-ops that formally allow for governance by representatives of two or more “stakeholder” groups within the same organization, including consumers, producers, workers, volunteers or general community supporters&lt;/mark&gt;. Rather than being organized around a single class of members the way that most cooperatives are, multi-stakeholder cooperatives enjoy a heterogeneous membership base. The common mission that is the central organizing principle of a multi-stakeholder cooperative is also generally broader than the kind of mission statement needed to capture the interests and benefits of only a single stakeholder group, and will often reflect the interdependence of interests of each stakeholder group in its articulation.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;mark&gt;Rather than being organised around a single class of members the way that most co-operatives are, a multi-stakeholder co-operative is any co-op that draws its membership from two or more different classes of stakeholders&lt;/mark&gt;. After two decades of local experimentation, Italy was the first country to adopt a multi-stakeholder statute in 1991. Over 14,000 ‘social co-ops’ now exist across Italy and provide social care, health and educational services to over 5 million people. In Quebec, home to one of the most productive and vibrant co-operative development sectors in the world, multi-stakeholder co-ops are now the fastest growing type of co-op, with more than 50% of all new co-ops opting to register what they refer to as ‘Solidarity Coops.’ The movement is just getting here in the UK, but there are now over 20 multi-stakeholder co-ops who have incorporated using the Somerset Rules.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.p2pfoundation.net/Multi-Stakeholder_Cooperatives&quot;&gt;Multi-Stakeholder Cooperatives - P2P Foundation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;mark&gt;Multi-stakeholder cooperatives present a departure in ownership structure from the more familiar consumer-owned and worker-owned co-ops. Also known as solidarity co-ops, hybrid co-ops or social co-ops, multi-stakeholder cooperatives welcome a variety of groups to become owners, including employees, producers, customers and clients, and community members (including investors).&lt;/mark&gt; These co-ops may appear to operate similarly to corporations, but as Shareable’s David Boiler points out, while they have “a keen focus on profit and loss, social co-ops are committed to meeting social goals such as healthcare, eldercare, social services, and workforce integration for former prisoners. They are able to blend market activity with social services provisioning and democratic participation, all in one swoop.”&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainableconsumption.usdn.org/initiatives-list/multi-stakeholder-cooperatives&quot;&gt;Multi-stakeholder co-operatives - USDN&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Multi-stakeholder platform co-ops&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://resonate.is/&quot;&gt;Resonate&lt;/a&gt; is a stream-to-own music platform harnessing blockchain technology. It is a multi-stakeholder co-operative giving democratic control to artists (45%), listeners (35%) and workers (20%). Through its model, it pays up to 2.5 times more revenue to artists than other streaming services.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://equalcare.coop/&quot;&gt;Equal Care Co-op&lt;/a&gt; are building a new, co-owned social care platform that puts care givers and receivers in charge. By incorporating as a multi-stakeholder co-operative, their digital product and accompanying service is owned by and accountable to the communities using and sustaining it. They arrived at the platform co-op model as a response to systemic inequities within the social care system, seeing it as a practical route to centering choice, power and ownership with the two most important people in care – the person giving and the person getting support.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/image/equal-care.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;table table-bordered text-sm&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
     &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Supported member:&lt;/strong&gt; You are being regularly supported by Equal Care Co-op (whether that's voluntary or paid support)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Advocate member:&lt;/strong&gt; Your relative or friend is being supported by Equal Care Co-op but they cannot be a Member themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;    
     &lt;strong&gt;Investor member: &lt;/strong&gt;You support our aims and have invested in our Community Share Offer.&lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;
     &lt;strong&gt;Worker member: &lt;/strong&gt;You are regularly contributing your labour to Equal Care Co-op, whether that's paid or voluntary work.&lt;/p&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Somerset Rules: creating multi-stakeholder co-ops in the UK&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;mark&gt;Launched in 2009, the Somerset Rules were one of the UK’s first set of model rules for a multi-stakeholder co-op, and they’re arguably still the best.&lt;/mark&gt; Packed full of best practice gleaned from decades of co-operative development experience, they’re structured to closely follow co-op principles, written in relatively plain English, and are cleverly drafted to allow for a wide range of different configurations. You can define the percentage of overall control each stakeholder group has. They are also ‘social accounting ready’ and are designed to enable the widest range of options for financing. In 2012 they were fully revised and overhauled and a version for use as a Community Interest Company limited by guarantee was developed.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;attribution&quot;&gt;
— &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.p2pfoundation.net/Somerset_Rules&quot;&gt;P2P Foundation: Somerset Rules&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Check out the latest version at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.somerset.coop/p/somerset-rules-registrations.html&quot;&gt;Somerset Rules registrations&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Graphic guides&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ia601506.us.archive.org/16/items/platform-cooperativism_graphic-individual-letter-size-pages/platform-cooperativism_graphic-individual-letter-size-pages.pdf&quot;&gt;Introduction to platform co-ops&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ia601506.us.archive.org/16/items/platform-cooperativism_graphic-individual-letter-size-pages/platform-cooperativism_graphic-individual-letter-size-pages.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/image/intro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uk.coop/start-new-co-op/support/start-platform-co-op/why-platform-co-ops&quot;&gt;Why platform co-ops?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uk.coop/start-new-co-op/support/start-platform-co-op/why-platform-co-ops&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/image/unfound.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Prepared as part of the Platform Co-ops Now! course</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Psychedelics and the Living Planet</title><link href="/blog/2020/11/18/psychedelics-and-the-living-planet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Psychedelics and the Living Planet" /><published>2020-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/11/18/psychedelics-and-the-living-planet</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/11/18/psychedelics-and-the-living-planet.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If the self is expanded to include the natural world, behavior leading to destruction of this world will be experienced as self-destruction.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Psychology as if the Whole Earth Mattered, Harvard Center for Psychology and Social Change, 199&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I gave a talk on the topic &lt;strong&gt;Psychedelics and the Living Planet&lt;/strong&gt; to the Cambridge Psychedelic Society. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Oz55NNRzOyNFHH-jz87G9PaPJhfief00rsHE3QsTojM/edit#&quot;&gt;You can check out the notes I used here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Notes from a talk I gave to the Cambridge Psychedelic Society</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Compassion and trust are the ultimate anti-viruses of Wetiko</title><link href="/blog/2020/10/19/searching-for-the-anti-virus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Compassion and trust are the ultimate anti-viruses of Wetiko" /><published>2020-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/10/19/searching-for-the-anti-virus</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/10/19/searching-for-the-anti-virus.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tamera.org/martin-winiecki/&quot;&gt;Martin Winiecki&lt;/a&gt;, first published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kosmosjournal.org/kj_article/searching-for-the-anti-virus-covid-19-as-quantum-phenomenon/&quot;&gt;Kosmos Journal&lt;/a&gt;. Highlights my own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve struggled to make sense of what is going on. My suspicious mind wandered around restlessly, examining all theories and possible explanations, yet I must admit: I don’t know what is happening. I do know this is a crucial moment of choice for humanity. In this essay, I will not suggest or discuss “what is going on.” I rather want to invite you into a realm transcending the dichotomy of “objective reality” vs “subjective thoughts/feelings,” which underlies most theories, predictions and calls to action in this crisis. &lt;mark&gt;Coming from a spiritually-informed holistic worldview, I entertain the possibility that we as humanity – or some deeper part of ourselves, whether conscious or not – have dreamed this moment into existence as a catalyst for our collective evolution.&lt;/mark&gt; If that were true, how might we engage and respond? Covid-19 could actually present an unlikely possibility for collective awakening and far-reaching system change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Neither real nor unreal, but dreamlike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This place is a dream. Only a sleeper considers it real. Then death comes like dawn, and you wake up laughing at what you thought was your grief.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Rumi&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For over a hundred years, physicists and philosophers have tried to wrap their heads around the manifold wonders of quantum physics. Subatomic entities, such as electrons, they saw, behave in awe-striking and magical ways. They do not simply exist “as such,” as fixed and finished entities; they can appear as a wave in one instant or as a particle in another, depending on whether or not they are observed. This is true. &lt;mark&gt;Our perception of the world isn’t just passive, it is creative – it literally in-forms its very being and reality. Quantum physics invites us into a view of reality in which the seeming “objective” reality out there and the “subjective” experience “in here” become inseparably intertwined.&lt;/mark&gt; Just as the characters and events in dreams aren’t separate from the dreamer, the world, according to the great psychoanalyst Carl Jung, is but a living symbol, the embodiment of deeper parts of ourselves, which we collectively dream into existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing reality in this way, how would we make sense of Covid-19?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through spiritual experiences and studies, I’ve learned that &lt;mark&gt;diseases rarely appear for no reason. They often carry deeper messages&lt;/mark&gt;. For example, conflicts, longings, and vital drives our minds suppress may resurface in bodily symptoms. &lt;mark&gt;Healing often occurs in the moment we realize what we have suppressed.&lt;/mark&gt; Such insights have the possibility to make us more whole and may, in fact, change our lives. In this way, we can say the healing antidote – or, in this case, the anti-virus – lies hidden within the disease as the treasure of transformative realization. &lt;mark&gt;If we exclusively fight the symptoms without exploring the deeper root, we might survive the disease but other symptoms are still likely to materialize.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is true for an individual disease may also be true for epidemic or pandemic outbreaks. In his provocative book, Selbstzerstörung aus Verlassenheit [Self-Destruction due to Abandonment], the psychotherapist Franz Renggli ascribes the outbreak of the Great Plague in Christian Europe in the 14th century, which killed 30%–60% of the continent’s population, to an “eruption of mass psychosis.” He writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My psycho- or rather socio-somatic model is psycho-neuro-immunology: neither a bacterium nor a virus is the core problem, but rather the people within a society who have been shaken by a crisis. &lt;mark&gt;If this crisis lasts too long, is too severe or too traumatic, the immune system of the population is slowly weakened and finally collapses.&lt;/mark&gt; The people become vulnerable to illnesses and finally to death. This model is valid for any epidemic and can serve as a key for a new understanding of history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the century preceding the Black Death, he argues, the Catholic Church began advising mothers to separate from their babies during day and night. Children growing up in the 13th and 14th centuries thus suffered a collective trauma of primal abandonment. Renggli shows that regions in which mothers continued to practice close physical contact with their children were spared from the plague. Might we be experiencing something similar right now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;How has the specter of Covid-19 been able to haunt 7.5 billion people and bring the world to a standstill in no time at all? Because the narrative massively resonates with something latent that is both teeming and deeply suppressed in people’s subconscious.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “mental” coronavirus spread earlier, faster and much more powerfully than its biological counterpart. Covid-19 began to make headlines and &lt;mark&gt;people suddenly found an “objective” justification for the fear and despair which had been gathering unconsciously within them for a long time. The feedback loop between the hourly onslaught of fear-inducing headlines in the media and the growing anxious expectations in people’s minds trapped humanity in a vicious neurotic cycle.&lt;/mark&gt; Every new “case” in our neighborhood or region, every cough in the subway, every stranger coming too close doubled-down on an eerie sense of ubiquitous danger. The more we think about illness, the more afraid we are. The more fear we experience, the weaker our immune system gets. The weaker our immune system, the more likely we’ll develop symptoms. Try not to think of a pink elephant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The psycho-spiritual dimension has been proven to have a very concrete effect on the material realm. The astonishingly far-reaching physical impacts of the placebo effect are well documented, and likewise, many studies show how emotional stress, chronic fear and loneliness can dangerously weaken our immune system and corrode our health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Please bear with me. I’m not suggesting Covid-19 is just a hoax, nor am I trying to downplay or deny the tragedy so many people are experiencing.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m suggesting we look at it from a different angle: What if Covid-19 weren’t a danger independent from our minds and souls but, in fact, a quantum phenomenon – &lt;mark&gt;a shared dream character we’ve collectively summoned into existence?&lt;/mark&gt; An embodiment of something buried deeply in the realms of the collective subconscious that we haven’t, so far, been able to comprehend? &lt;mark&gt;A living symbol of a much deeper infection?&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mind viruses and the magic of fear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching back to the oral traditions of several First Nations, Native American scholar Jack D. Forbes writes in Columbus and Other Cannibals, “For several thousands of years human beings have suffered from a plague, a disease worse than leprosy, a sickness worse than malaria, a malady much more terrible than smallpox.” The Algonquin and other Indigenous First Nations identified the mental illness of the white man, upon his arrival to their native homelands in the 15th and 16th centuries, as “&lt;mark&gt;Wetiko&lt;/mark&gt;,” literally translating as cannibalism: &lt;mark&gt;“the consuming of another’s life for [one’s] own private purpose or profit.”&lt;/mark&gt; Forbes concludes by saying, &lt;mark&gt;“This disease is the greatest epidemic sickness known to man.”&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wetiko – often referred to as a mind virus – propagates the deep-seated illusion of seeing oneself desperately confined to the cage of a separated ego. From this perspective of isolation, others appear either as competitors or as prey. In a worldview in which fear is the basic condition, fight and exploitation seem rational, empathy ridiculous and sentimental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;After 5000 years of patriarchy, 500 years of capitalism and 50 years of neoliberalism, Wetiko has come to define nearly every area of our (Western) world and lives.&lt;/mark&gt; The reason we can accept an economic system celebrating the biggest-possible devastation of the natural world as “success” is due to our own infection with the virus. &lt;mark&gt;Wetiko has numbed our hearts, blurring our ability to perceive both the sacredness and the pain of life, both outside and inside ourselves. Innumerable beings are perishing due to this chronic inability to feel empathy.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the compulsive fixation on maximizing artificial values in the economy all the way down to the pandemic of broken and abusive love relationships, &lt;mark&gt;the Wetiko sickness has become so normalized it’s no longer even recognized as such&lt;/mark&gt;. A miserable cult of self-obsession has eroded the social tissue of humanity and desecrated the Earth. As a result, fear is everywhere – fear of abandonment, fear of death, fear of life, fear of sexuality, fear of punishment, fear of the coming collapse… &lt;mark&gt;The benign front of bourgeois decency conceals a psychological basement in which the children of fear roam freely: permanent anger, general mistrust, addiction, depression, boredom, perversion, compulsive consumption and control and the secret or open fascination with violence.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 narrative has been able to infect humanity at such record speed because fear is so deep-seated and unconscious in humanity that we’re no longer aware of what is happening within us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragedy is that the virus operates in the shadows of our consciousness. We infect ourselves and others unknowingly. As Forbes writes, we’re conditioned by the disease through “authoritarian family structures,” “male dominance,” “subjugating women” and “extremely negative attitudes towards sex” – and on an ideological level, through “notions of racial and cultural superiority.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once stuck in this box, we mindlessly perpetuate the disease in our day-to-day interactions, by feeding off and into each other’s blind spots and pain points. As we project what we fear internally onto others or external events, we validate our fear while suppressing where it comes from. We believe danger to be outside of us, so we try to protect ourselves from it and, thereby, often act in ways that perpetuate the very danger we try to protect ourselves from. Jung describes this mechanism as “shadow projection.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the extent we’re unconsciously driven by fear, we become susceptible to manipulation. &lt;mark&gt;When millions of people project their unconscious shadows onto others, they conjure up the very danger everyone is trying to escape from.&lt;/mark&gt; Wilhelm Reich made these dynamics explicit during the rise of Hitler (see his 1933 book, The Mass Psychology of Fascism) and they’re the premise of all totalitarian regimes to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 9/11, we were told that our enemy was the Muslim world; now the “enemy” is invisible and might await us at every door handle, or creep into us as we kiss, hug or even breathe. The more extravagant the neurotic cinema that’s playing in our minds, the easier it is for external powers to control and use us for their interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The great unveiling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much more than just a difficult trial for humanity, the Covid-19 outbreak also holds the possibility for collective healing from the predatory mass infection of Wetiko. We can make sense of it as a global somatization – or symbolic simulation – of the underlying Wetiko disease. As with every outbreak of severe disease, the deeper patterns are now coming unstuck in plain sight at the global level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’re now witnessing a simultaneous unveiling, breakdown and intense exaggeration of Wetiko:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On an ecological level, Covid-19 originated as a direct result of our civilization’s insatiable greed for exponential growth. Probably wild animals transmitted the virus to people after the natural ecosystems which were home to them were destroyed by the ecocidal steamroller of civilizational “progress.” And now we’re equally astonished to see how quickly the air can clear in China, the speed at which wildlife returns to urban areas, and how suddenly old ecocidal endeavors collapse before our eyes (e.g. the S. fracking industry).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On an economic level, Covid-19 has been the straw that’s broken the camel’s back, setting off the chain reaction of a long overdue financial collapse. The lockdown has sent our globalized economy into a full-blown, rapid “evaporation,” with entire industries halting, millions of workers being laid off from one day to the next and stock markets crashing. The fossil fuel industry faces its “gravest challenge in its 100-year history,” from which it may never recover. The Federal Reserves are currently lending big banks an additional $1 trillion a day, which is to say, we’re now barely keeping the economic system on life support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the social and psychological levels, we see both a collective frenzy of extreme Wetiko behaviors and also many people breaking free. On one hand, social atomization, the desire for control and egoistic panic are reaching surreal pinnacles. We are seeing a massive surge in domestic abuse and the rapid conversion of liberal societies into police states; even leftists are praising the strengthening of top-down government and restrictions on civil liberties. On the other hand, thousands of local grassroots initiatives practicing mutual aid have popped up from one day to the next. Millions are entering a rare moment of reflection and of asking “what’s essential?” While locked down in quarantine, we’re confronted with ourselves, our longings and our lives. And &lt;mark&gt;many recognize how deeply we’ve been “socially distanced” all along&lt;/mark&gt; – divided up by the competitive ideals of a precarious labor market and our own inability to engage in authentic interpersonal connection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A parting of ways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will happen next is uncertain, but we can predict that the chain reaction of economic devastation may be inevitable. The global emergency may have come to stay. In other words, &lt;mark&gt;we may not go back to normal anytime soon, or perhaps ever again.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will happen in the next few weeks and months will likely shape the world for many years to come. Rather than resisting the forces of entropy and indulging in faint hopes of a return to normality, &lt;mark&gt;the future will be on the side of those who are able to embrace chaos and disruption as an opportunity to propose a different vision for global society.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naomi Klein, author of The Shock Doctrine, says: “If there is one thing history teaches us, it’s that moments of shock are profoundly volatile. We either lose a whole lot of ground, get fleeced by elites, and pay the price for decades, or we win progressive victories that seemed impossible just a few weeks earlier. This is no time to lose our nerve.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burdened by astronomical debt and commanded by the imperative for exponential growth, the globalized capitalist system has come to an irreversible breaking point. The powers that be will either have to make way for system change or will stubbornly continue to prop up the old order with ever-more brutal force. While there may be many possible futures in front of us, I want to highlight the stark contrast of the historic choice we’re facing, in two contrasting future scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario #1: Surveillance capitalism&lt;/strong&gt;
After many months of lockdown, people have accepted the new era of quarantined existence. Governments have dismantled civil liberties, human rights and environmental protections and, under the pretext of health and safety, deployed unprecedented levels of surveillance technology. Mobile apps are used not only to track people’s physical movements but also their biochemical reactions. As Gideon Lichfield writes, “intrusive surveillance [is] considered a small price to pay for the basic freedom to be with other people.” In the background of a daily onslaught of fear-invoking messages, governments further redistribute wealth from the bottom 99% to the elites. Banks, fossil fuel and airline industries are bailed out with taxpayer’s money, while social security and public health systems are further dismantled. Austerity measures and the abolition of cash further marginalize working people, the poor and the homeless. General apathy and numbness have reached a dimension where the daily shooting of migrants at the borders and other atrocities no longer provoke any moral outcry. Locked into their flats, afraid of infection, monitored by digital body sensors, the powers that be have almost entirely crippled people’s ability to organize themselves and resist. Should protests or strikes still occur, the mass media can report on new dangerous infections spreading so that governments can swiftly impose new curfews to “keep our communities safe.” At some point, with climate breakdown, water crises and food shortages worsening, the system is no longer able to disguise its collapse. Chaos and violence can no longer be contained. The rich retreat to their gated compounds in remote areas, while masses of people find themselves trapped in disintegrating urban centers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario #2: Ecological and social emancipation&lt;/strong&gt;
In the months of uncertainty and economic disintegration, millions of people begin to organize themselves at the local grassroots levels to cover their basic needs. In this time of hardship, they rediscover the power of community, solidarity and localism. As people help each other through sickness and challenge, a spirit of empathy and interdependence spreads. After many months of unemployment, public chaos and food shortages, hopes for strong government and a return to normality have finally faded. &lt;mark&gt;Many realize that either we live out collapse alone or we get through this together.&lt;/mark&gt; The emergency initiatives of neighborhood aid now turn into more long-term initiatives of social, economic and ecological re-organization. People start collective gardens and food cooperatives to supply themselves with local organic crops and open solar energy task forces to decentralize and democratize their energy supply. More and more people leave the cities to found communities in the countryside, where they engage in restoring ecosystems and radical social experimentation for a more trust-based and loving way of living. People work together with progressive governments on large-scale ecological rehabilitation in response to the climate crisis, while governments support citizens’ agency through introducing Universal Basic Income. In the background of this astonishing social and ecological movement, a profound cultural and spiritual transformation takes place – a shift of consciousness from the Wetiko drive for domination to cooperation with all living beings, from atomizing mass societies to communities of trust, from the patriarchal condemnation of Eros and the feminine to a culture that celebrates sensual love in its freedom and dignity, from subduing the Earth to honoring her inherent sacredness, from fearing death to acknowledging our eternal existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;System change: the time is now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dangers of totalitarianism are dire and real and are becoming concretized in many countries already. But we mustn’t forget that those measures are the last resort in prolonging the death of a system that’s already on its way out. &lt;mark&gt;At this point, globalized capitalism is only being kept alive by our fearful projections and our inability to imagine something new, which is to say, if people can leave fear behind and unify around a shared vision of the future they want, nothing can stop the inevitable transition.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see the keys to system change lying in three essential realms of our lives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The spiritual sphere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having exaggerated Wetiko to unthinkably surreal heights, Covid-19 strangely invites us into a dimensional shift of being. As Paul Levy, the author of Dispelling Wetiko, maintains, the anti-virus hidden within the Wetiko disease is the awakening to its dream-like nature – a realization which has the potential to radically change our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we continue to react to the embodiments of Wetiko outside of us (e.g. viruses, external enemies or the dangers of totalitarianism…) as if they were separate from us, we will continue to act in ways that feed the very dynamic we’re afraid of. But if we begin to see Wetiko playing out within ourselves, it loses its grip on us. Compassion opens our eyes to understanding that which we previously could only fear, judge or hate. Trust reconciles us with the world and our fellow beings. &lt;mark&gt;Compassion and trust are the ultimate anti-viruses of Wetiko.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may suddenly wake up and realize how all systems of domination have never been “real” as such, their “reality” has always only existed through our consent. &lt;mark&gt;Money, authority, society, pandemics – we can now see the dreamlike nature of what we believed to be rock-solid and unchangeable.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To awaken from the fearful web of Wetiko is to simultaneously awaken to the interdependent web of Life. This is such a profound shift from where we come from in the Western world that it’s hard to even find words for it. The fear-stricken mind always asks for immediate conclusions, solutions, fixes. But maybe there is no such “fix” right now. Maybe, what this moment calls for is for us to let go of all our notions of self-importance, superiority and domination and to surrender to a greater-than-human intelligence and guidance, to inquire for orientation from the Earth and the Indigenous wisdom of cultures centered around the Earth. In this experience of communion lies a truth that is unambiguous, absolute and deeply healing: &lt;mark&gt;all life is sacred&lt;/mark&gt;. This isn’t only a private experience, but an insight into the inherent matrix of Life. In alignment with this matrix we stand outside the vicious cycles of fear, infection and violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The social sphere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Wetiko plays out relationally, its dissolution is a collective endeavor; a historic project of developing ways of living together in which we can heal our broken relationship to the Earth and each other, and develop deep trust among ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build trust, we need conditions which no longer force us to lie, disguise or protect ourselves. We need ways of living, loving, working and relating in which we can truly recognize each other and dare to show what we actually think and feel, love and desire. “Trust” is a word often used, but what does it mean in the delicate realms of our souls, such as love, sexuality and spirituality, where our vulnerabilities tend to be the greatest? This entails nothing short of a social revolution. Dieter Duhm, a mentor and teacher of mine, and author of The Sacred Matrix, writes, “Trust is not only classified as psychological; it is above all a political term – the most revolutionary of all – for &lt;mark&gt;we need to renew the entire societal structure to bring about sustainable, systemic trust&lt;/mark&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This revolution may not occur in mass movements immediately, but it can begin in small groups – wells of coherence – and extend across society from there, by virtue of raising a new field of consciousness. Based on 40 years of radical experimentation, the “Healing Biotopes Plan” offers a respective vision for such comprehensive transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The political and economic sphere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freedom in the long-term requires our capacity to resist any restriction to civil and human rights in the short-term. In this time of social distancing, let us stand in solidarity together, especially with all those who are marginalized, rejecting any narrative of “us versus them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the globalized system crumbles, localization will be the key to the future. Now is the moment to decentralize supply systems for water, food and energy, to invest in regenerative agriculture and practices of ecosystem restoration, to create seed banks and exchange, and to establish networks and economic mechanisms of mutual aid, resource sharing and reciprocal gifting. &lt;mark&gt;Localization not only offers food sovereignty but also a path to political autonomy – as we take charge of our own basic needs, we can come together to make collaborative decisions from the bottom up.&lt;/mark&gt; From various ecosystem restoration practices to the permaculture, seed saving and ecovillage movements, all the way to large-scale social movements like Extinction Rebellion and experiments of radical grassroots democracy like Rojava and the Zapatistas, the world offers a thousand examples showing that this path is viable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the spiritual, social, and economic-political spheres are so inseparably intertwined, successful system change will rely on profound structural transformations in these three realms in parallel. It doesn’t mean we must all do everything at once, it means we must support each other. May we each listen deeply for what we’re now called to do and be, while remaining aware of each other. &lt;mark&gt;As much as narratives of isolation and social distancing threaten to keep us afraid and separate, our ability to go through this crisis relies on our ability to organize and build alliances, remembering that we are community.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever we may do, may we remember that this is a moment of unique historic possibility. As Julian Assange told Yanis Varoufakis from his prison cell by phone, “Anything goes… Everything is now possible.” And if there’s one thing that Covid-19 has taught us, it is that &lt;mark&gt;dramatic shifts of collective behavior can actually occur overnight.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Can we entertain the possibility that we as humanity – or some deeper part of ourselves, whether conscious or not – have dreamed this moment into existence as a catalyst for our collective evolution?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Pollination Approach</title><link href="/blog/2020/10/15/pollination-approach.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Pollination Approach" /><published>2020-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/10/15/pollination-approach</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/10/15/pollination-approach.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rhsmith.umd.edu/directory/bennet-zelner&quot;&gt;Bennet A. Zelner&lt;/a&gt;, first published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.org/news/bulletin/articles/439-bulletin-spring-2020/8131-the-pollination-approach-to-delivering-psychedelic-assisted-mental-healthcare&quot;&gt;MAPS Bulletin Spring 2020: Vol. 30, No. 1&lt;/a&gt;. Highlights my own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article I outline a novel economic approach for delivering psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare, the Pollination Approach. The Pollination Approach focuses on the intrinsically &lt;mark&gt;interdependent production of individual and community wellness&lt;/mark&gt;. It contrasts sharply with the current pharmaceutical-centered approach to mental healthcare, which focuses on the &lt;mark&gt;management of symptoms rather than the production of wellness&lt;/mark&gt;, and reflects divisive economic conceptions that have contributed to rising rates of mental distress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next section I describe the economic conceptions animating the pharmaceutical approach. In the following section I discuss the relationship among these conceptions, the disruption of community social and economic systems, and mental health. In the third section I present the Pollination Approach, describing how all of its facets–the design of treatment sites, the conduct of integration activities, the &lt;mark&gt;configuration of ownership and decision-making structures, and the financial structures used to create and allocate shared prosperity&lt;/mark&gt;–promote the production of wellness through the &lt;mark&gt;renewal and recirculation of community resources&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Pharmaceutical Approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pharmaceutical approach to mental healthcare portrays mental disorders as clusters of biologically-based symptoms susceptible to being treated primarily with drugs, much like a physical disease. This approach has benefited drug manufacturers, whose U.S. revenues from the sale of psychiatric drugs rose from $2.8 billion in 1987 (the year in which Prozac was introduced) to $34 billion in 2010. Yet despite the fact that antidepressants alone represent the most prescribed category of pharmaceuticals among the U.S. non-geriatric adult population, American mental health has reached a crisis state. &lt;mark&gt;The national suicide rate has increased to its greatest level in 50 years&lt;/mark&gt; and continues to rise. The U.S. also has the highest rate of death from mental health and substance abuse disorders among peer countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dire state of our collective mental health is linked to widely-held economic conceptions that have contributed to the pharmaceutical approach’s financial profitability. The first such conception is that of economic individualism. When psychiatric drugs were first introduced in the 1950s, patients were viewed as socially embedded individuals whose mental illness reflected &lt;mark&gt;both psychosocial and biological factors&lt;/mark&gt;, and for whom pharmaceutical treatment was considered an adjunct to psychological and social remedies. Pharmaceutical manufacturers actively promoted the reconceptualization of mental illness as a constellation of biologically-based symptoms, and of patients as atomized consumers devoid of psychological and social context. These shifts, which leveraged an ascendant cultural view of people as individualistic market participants, &lt;mark&gt;promoted the long-term consumption of medication as the primary modality for treating mental distress&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second widely-held economic conception that has contributed to the pharmaceutical approach’s financial profitability is the belief that unconstrained market processes produce the best economic outcomes. American drug manufacturers have leveraged and promoted this belief, sponsoring numerous economic studies intended to convince policymakers that a hands-off approach to the economic regulation of the industry would maximize innovation, with high drug prices representing the cost of progress. Prescription drug spending in the U.S. has increased dramatically as a result, rising more than 1,800% between 1980 and 2015 and outpacing that in other developed countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Disruption of Community Systems and the Impairment of Mental Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic conceptions animating the pharmaceutical approach have impaired our collective mental health through their influence on an expanding array of policies and practices over the past four decades. Market competition is now widely regarded as the best and most natural organizing principle for all human relations, and economic individualism has come to represent not just independence and self-reliance, but the prioritization of self over relationships, and of individual success over the common good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason that these divisive conceptions have been so damaging is that they conflict with basic human nature. We possess an evolutionary drive to connect and cooperate with each other because doing so helped our ancestors survive. The primary structures in which we have traditionally expressed and fulfilled this drive are &lt;mark&gt;residential communities, complex systems of people and resources linked in interdependent social, economic, ecological, and other interrelated systems&lt;/mark&gt;. As in nature, healthy systems promote individual and collective well-being. However, the ascent of the economic conceptions discussed above has disrupted the functioning of community systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First consider community social systems. Americans no longer come together as they once did: They now have fewer interactions with friends and family, and are less likely to belong to organizations that provide opportunities for social interaction. This &lt;mark&gt;crisis of connection&lt;/mark&gt; is reflected in a loneliness epidemic that has fueled rising rates of depression, anxiety, and addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paralleling the crisis of connection in social systems is a &lt;mark&gt;crisis of extraction&lt;/mark&gt; in economic systems. In localities throughout the U.S., outposts of large corporations have displaced locally owned businesses. As a result, locally produced income is extracted by distant shareholders rather than being recirculated within the community to fund local (re)investment, contributing to economic inequality. Further, the extraction of decision-making authority by remote corporate managers with no direct connection to local ecosystems results in the &lt;mark&gt;unsustainable use of local resources&lt;/mark&gt;, depleting the human, natural, and other forms of productive capital available to provision ongoing local economic activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crises of disconnection and extraction in community social and economic systems have fueled rising rates of disorders such as depression and addiction. Disconnection is a core feature of depression and &lt;mark&gt;addiction represents an adaptive response to disconnection&lt;/mark&gt;. Economic stress increases vulnerability to both conditions. Large-scale statistical analysis supports these ideas, demonstrating that countries with greater income inequality – reflecting the promulgation of policies and practices embodying the individual-centric, hyper-competitive economic conceptions discussed above–exhibit higher rates of depression and illegal drug use (a proxy for addiction). &lt;mark&gt;A comprehensive approach to the delivery of mental healthcare must counteract these divisive conceptions’ damaging psychological influence by facilitating the repair of community systems, complementing and contributing to individual healing.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Pollination Approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pollination Approach to delivering mental healthcare recognizes the &lt;mark&gt;mutually reinforcing relationship between individual and collective wellness&lt;/mark&gt;. It is rooted in the ecological principle that the production of wellness depends on the continual &lt;mark&gt;renewal and recirculation of system resources&lt;/mark&gt; (versus their extraction or depletion). &lt;mark&gt;Pollinator organizations facilitate the renewal and recirculation of resources in community systems as pollinator organisms do in natural systems&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Community Reconnection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delivery of psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare under the Pollination Approach facilitates, first and foremost, the renewal and recirculation of human resources. Psychedelic medicines possess a documented ability to foster connection, and the shift from disconnection to connection represents a key mechanism in the healing process. &lt;mark&gt;The Pollination Approach harnesses this shift by (re)connecting patients to social, economic, and other community systems, contributing to individual healing and the revitalization of the systems themselves.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Treatment sites enacting the Pollination Approach function as wellness centers&lt;/mark&gt;, gathering places where community members may participate in a range of healing and community-building activities in addition to psychedelic-assisted therapy. Explicit reconnection activities for those who have undergone therapy include &lt;mark&gt;group integration sessions&lt;/mark&gt; as well as &lt;mark&gt;community reintegration programs&lt;/mark&gt; conducted in partnership with local organizations, such as businesses, cultural institutions, civic organizations, religious organizations, and others. These organizations may also serve as points of access, especially in communities where psychedelic medicines are viewed with skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Local Wisdom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The identification of specific partner organizations and adaptation of other delivery-of-care elements to community needs and customs are undertaken in close consultation with local wisdom keepers. Community elders, social workers, ER workers, spiritual leaders, union representatives, local business owners, and others may all possess distinctive knowledge of common trauma patterns, recirculatory gaps in community systems, and sources of resource depletion and extraction. The integration of such wisdom with more generalized knowledge of therapeutic techniques and psychedelic medicines optimizes the delivery of care in a given community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Governance Principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ownership and governance of wellness centers under the Pollination Approach also support the production of wellness through the renewal and recirculation of community resources. Two core principles inform choices in this area. The first is &lt;mark&gt;stakeholder inclusivity, the notion that an organization should operate for the explicit benefit of its stakeholder groups including customers, employees, community members, and others&lt;/mark&gt;. The principle of stakeholder inclusivity naturally supports the inherently inclusive process of wellness production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The principle of stakeholder inclusivity contrasts sharply with the creed of shareholder primacy guiding most corporate decision-making.&lt;/mark&gt; The latter ascended in conjunction with the divisive economic conceptions discussed above. It holds that the sole purpose of a corporation is to serve the interests of shareholders by maximizing financial profits, as reflected in the pharmaceutical approach’s emphasis on managing symptoms. The production of wellness is less lucrative for pharmaceutical shareholders because it reduces the need for ongoing medical intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second principle informing the ownership and governance of wellness centers under the Pollination Approach is &lt;mark&gt;distributed local ownership&lt;/mark&gt;. Local ownership supports the health of community economic systems by promoting the recirculation of income, creating an economic multiplier effect from the local (re)investment that such recirculation enables. Local ownership also promotes the sustainable use of a community’s human, natural, and other productive resources because owners and managers participate directly in the local ecosystem, attuning them to local conditions. &lt;mark&gt;Distributed local ownership–ownership that is spread widely among local community members from different stakeholder groups&lt;/mark&gt;–amplifies these benefits by dispersing financial returns and diversifying the information sources contributing to decision-making. Collaborative ties between wellness centers and non-local organizations in the psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare ecosystem, such as MAPS and MAPS PBC, complement local ownership by promoting the circulation of global resources, such as knowledge gained through experiential learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Cooperative Organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The organizational form that most naturally supports the principles of stakeholder inclusivity and distributed local ownership is a cooperative structure, which distributes ownership and control among the members of stakeholder groups such as workers or customers&lt;/mark&gt;. Treatment sites enacting the Pollination Approach may distribute ownership and control most widely by adopting a &lt;mark&gt;multi-stakeholder cooperative structure&lt;/mark&gt;, in which the cooperative’s owners include members of both of these groups as well as other community stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooperatives are typically organized as corporations or LLCs, legal forms that distribute the financial returns from community wellness centers among stakeholder-owners. Though non-profit organizations are more commonly associated with the production of social returns, &lt;mark&gt;existing legal classifications do not readily accommodate entities producing both types of return because they reflect an ingrained assumption that the two are incompatible.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An organization’s legal form also does not by itself guarantee a given behavior pattern. For example, &lt;mark&gt;some non-profit hospitals have been criticized for accumulating large cash reserves that are not being used to benefit the community&lt;/mark&gt;, while the Business Roundtable–an association of corporate CEOs that has traditionally endorsed shareholder primacy–recently proclaimed that a corporation’s purpose is to promote “an economy that serves all Americans.” &lt;mark&gt;The extent to which a wellness center’s specific incentive and decision-making structures support the mission objectives and governance principles discussed above is thus more consequential than its legal form.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Financial Structures for Sharing Prosperity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed above, multi-stakeholder cooperative organization enables community stakeholders to share in the financial returns generated by local wellness centers enacting the Pollination Approach. Symmetrically, wellness centers may finance their ongoing operations by sharing in the economic prosperity they enable for patients and communities. &lt;mark&gt;Mechanisms such as deferred payment plans linked to patients’ post-treatment income, employer-sponsored insurance coverage of consciousness-focused healthcare, and government grant funding based on reduced public welfare spending facilitate the collection of revenues from the provision of psychedelic-assisted therapy.&lt;/mark&gt; Similarly, the performance of contract research for entities such as MAPS, and the provision of therapy sessions and apprenticeships to trainees in external credentialing programs, create revenues and control costs by tapping into shared value co-created with other participants in the psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial funders play a critical role in this ecosystem. &lt;mark&gt;The equitable sharing of jointly enabled prosperity between funders and other stakeholders requires innovation because traditional funding structures reflect the dichotomy between the production of social and economic returns embodied in the legal distinction between non-profit and for-profit enterprise.&lt;/mark&gt; On the one hand, philanthropic funders may be unwilling to contribute to wellness centers organized as for-profit entities due to the ingrained belief that non-profits specialize in the production of social returns, an assumption that is reinforced by the favorable tax treatment of non-profit donations under the U.S. federal tax code. On the other hand, conventional venture-style mechanisms for the external funding of for-profit startups focus on the production of concentrated financial returns for the benefit of shareholders who retain a long-term equity stake, which conflicts with the governance principles discussed above. Wellness centers funded with such mechanisms would be deterred from generating wider social and economic returns through the renewal and recirculation of community resources, and also from engaging in the prototyping necessary for continual learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financing mechanisms that transcend these institutionalized trade-offs are currently under development. One example is a structure that builds on recent innovations in venture capital financing intended to align the long-term incentives of founders and funders. It works by paying initial funders a &lt;mark&gt;capped return&lt;/mark&gt; drawn from wellness centers’ operating cash flows; transferring funders’ original equity claim to a stakeholder pool; and distributing or selling shares in this pool to workers, patients, and members of other local stakeholder groups. Ultimately, these local owners would go on to pollinate additional local economic activity by investing their financial dividends (and perhaps their knowledge, labor, and social capital) into other community enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare holds revolutionary potential for treating various forms of mental distress. In order to fully realize this potential, it should be delivered using an equally revolutionary economic approach.&lt;/mark&gt; The Pollination Approach outlined above seeks to meet this aspiration by serving as more than a conventional business model, and as a source of healing itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Pollination Approach focuses on the intrinsically interdependent production of individual and community wellness</summary></entry></feed>