<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-19T19:48:27+01:00</updated><id>/blog/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Searching for the Anti-Virus: Covid-19 as Quantum Phenomenon</title><link href="/blog/2020/10/19/searching-for-the-anti-virus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Searching for the Anti-Virus: Covid-19 as Quantum Phenomenon" /><published>2020-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/10/19/searching-for-the-anti-virus</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/10/19/searching-for-the-anti-virus.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tamera.org/martin-winiecki/&quot;&gt;Martin Winiecki&lt;/a&gt;, first published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kosmosjournal.org/kj_article/searching-for-the-anti-virus-covid-19-as-quantum-phenomenon/&quot;&gt;Kosmos Journal&lt;/a&gt;. Highlights my own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve struggled to make sense of what is going on. My suspicious mind wandered around restlessly, examining all theories and possible explanations, yet I must admit: I don’t know what is happening. I do know this is a crucial moment of choice for humanity. In this essay, I will not suggest or discuss “what is going on.” I rather want to invite you into a realm transcending the dichotomy of “objective reality” vs “subjective thoughts/feelings,” which underlies most theories, predictions and calls to action in this crisis. &lt;mark&gt;Coming from a spiritually-informed holistic worldview, I entertain the possibility that we as humanity – or some deeper part of ourselves, whether conscious or not – have dreamed this moment into existence as a catalyst for our collective evolution.&lt;/mark&gt; If that were true, how might we engage and respond? Covid-19 could actually present an unlikely possibility for collective awakening and far-reaching system change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Neither real nor unreal, but dreamlike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This place is a dream. Only a sleeper considers it real. Then death comes like dawn, and you wake up laughing at what you thought was your grief.”
– Rumi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For over a hundred years, physicists and philosophers have tried to wrap their heads around the manifold wonders of quantum physics. Subatomic entities, such as electrons, they saw, behave in awe-striking and magical ways. They do not simply exist “as such,” as fixed and finished entities; they can appear as a wave in one instant or as a particle in another, depending on whether or not they are observed. This is true. &lt;mark&gt;Our perception of the world isn’t just passive, it is creative – it literally in-forms its very being and reality. Quantum physics invites us into a view of reality in which the seeming “objective” reality out there and the “subjective” experience “in here” become inseparably intertwined.&lt;/mark&gt; Just as the characters and events in dreams aren’t separate from the dreamer, the world, according to the great psychoanalyst Carl Jung, is but a living symbol, the embodiment of deeper parts of ourselves, which we collectively dream into existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing reality in this way, how would we make sense of Covid-19?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through spiritual experiences and studies, I’ve learned that &lt;mark&gt;diseases rarely appear for no reason. They often carry deeper messages&lt;/mark&gt;. For example, conflicts, longings, and vital drives our minds suppress may resurface in bodily symptoms. &lt;mark&gt;Healing often occurs in the moment we realize what we have suppressed.&lt;/mark&gt; Such insights have the possibility to make us more whole and may, in fact, change our lives. In this way, we can say the healing antidote – or, in this case, the anti-virus – lies hidden within the disease as the treasure of transformative realization. &lt;mark&gt;If we exclusively fight the symptoms without exploring the deeper root, we might survive the disease but other symptoms are still likely to materialize.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is true for an individual disease may also be true for epidemic or pandemic outbreaks. In his provocative book, Selbstzerstörung aus Verlassenheit [Self-Destruction due to Abandonment], the psychotherapist Franz Renggli ascribes the outbreak of the Great Plague in Christian Europe in the 14th century, which killed 30%–60% of the continent’s population, to an “eruption of mass psychosis.” He writes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My psycho- or rather socio-somatic model is psycho-neuro-immunology: neither a bacterium nor a virus is the core problem, but rather the people within a society who have been shaken by a crisis. &lt;mark&gt;If this crisis lasts too long, is too severe or too traumatic, the immune system of the population is slowly weakened and finally collapses.&lt;/mark&gt; The people become vulnerable to illnesses and finally to death. This model is valid for any epidemic and can serve as a key for a new understanding of history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the century preceding the Black Death, he argues, the Catholic Church began advising mothers to separate from their babies during day and night. Children growing up in the 13th and 14th centuries thus suffered a collective trauma of primal abandonment. Renggli shows that regions in which mothers continued to practice close physical contact with their children were spared from the plague. Might we be experiencing something similar right now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;How has the specter of Covid-19 been able to haunt 7.5 billion people and bring the world to a standstill in no time at all? Because the narrative massively resonates with something latent that is both teeming and deeply suppressed in people’s subconscious.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “mental” coronavirus spread earlier, faster and much more powerfully than its biological counterpart. Covid-19 began to make headlines and &lt;mark&gt;people suddenly found an “objective” justification for the fear and despair which had been gathering unconsciously within them for a long time.&lt;/mark&gt; &lt;mark&gt;The feedback loop between the hourly onslaught of fear-inducing headlines in the media and the growing anxious expectations in people’s minds trapped humanity in a vicious neurotic cycle.&lt;/mark&gt; Every new “case” in our neighborhood or region, every cough in the subway, every stranger coming too close doubled-down on an eerie sense of ubiquitous danger. The more we think about illness, the more afraid we are. The more fear we experience, the weaker our immune system gets. The weaker our immune system, the more likely we’ll develop symptoms. Try not to think of a pink elephant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The psycho-spiritual dimension has been proven to have a very concrete effect on the material realm. The astonishingly far-reaching physical impacts of the placebo effect are well documented, and likewise, many studies show how emotional stress, chronic fear and loneliness can dangerously weaken our immune system and corrode our health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Please bear with me. I’m not suggesting Covid-19 is just a hoax, nor am I trying to downplay or deny the tragedy so many people are experiencing.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m suggesting we look at it from a different angle: What if Covid-19 weren’t a danger independent from our minds and souls but, in fact, a quantum phenomenon – &lt;mark&gt;a shared dream character we’ve collectively summoned into existence?&lt;/mark&gt; An embodiment of something buried deeply in the realms of the collective subconscious that we haven’t, so far, been able to comprehend? &lt;mark&gt;A living symbol of a much deeper infection?&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Mind viruses and the magic of fear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reaching back to the oral traditions of several First Nations, Native American scholar Jack D. Forbes writes in Columbus and Other Cannibals, “For several thousands of years human beings have suffered from a plague, a disease worse than leprosy, a sickness worse than malaria, a malady much more terrible than smallpox.” The Algonquin and other Indigenous First Nations identified the mental illness of the white man, upon his arrival to their native homelands in the 15th and 16th centuries, as “&lt;mark&gt;Wetiko&lt;/mark&gt;,” literally translating as cannibalism: &lt;mark&gt;“the consuming of another’s life for [one’s] own private purpose or profit.”&lt;/mark&gt; Forbes concludes by saying, &lt;mark&gt;“This disease is the greatest epidemic sickness known to man.”&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wetiko – often referred to as a mind virus – propagates the deep-seated illusion of seeing oneself desperately confined to the cage of a separated ego. From this perspective of isolation, others appear either as competitors or as prey. In a worldview in which fear is the basic condition, fight and exploitation seem rational, empathy ridiculous and sentimental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;After 5000 years of patriarchy, 500 years of capitalism and 50 years of neoliberalism, Wetiko has come to define nearly every area of our (Western) world and lives.&lt;/mark&gt; The reason we can accept an economic system celebrating the biggest-possible devastation of the natural world as “success” is due to our own infection with the virus. &lt;mark&gt;Wetiko has numbed our hearts, blurring our ability to perceive both the sacredness and the pain of life, both outside and inside ourselves. Innumerable beings are perishing due to this chronic inability to feel empathy.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the compulsive fixation on maximizing artificial values in the economy all the way down to the pandemic of broken and abusive love relationships, &lt;mark&gt;the Wetiko sickness has become so normalized it’s no longer even recognized as such&lt;/mark&gt;. A miserable cult of self-obsession has eroded the social tissue of humanity and desecrated the Earth. As a result, fear is everywhere – fear of abandonment, fear of death, fear of life, fear of sexuality, fear of punishment, fear of the coming collapse… &lt;mark&gt;The benign front of bourgeois decency conceals a psychological basement in which the children of fear roam freely: permanent anger, general mistrust, addiction, depression, boredom, perversion, compulsive consumption and control and the secret or open fascination with violence.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 narrative has been able to infect humanity at such record speed because fear is so deep-seated and unconscious in humanity that we’re no longer aware of what is happening within us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragedy is that the virus operates in the shadows of our consciousness. We infect ourselves and others unknowingly. As Forbes writes, we’re conditioned by the disease through “authoritarian family structures,” “male dominance,” “subjugating women” and “extremely negative attitudes towards sex” – and on an ideological level, through “notions of racial and cultural superiority.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once stuck in this box, we mindlessly perpetuate the disease in our day-to-day interactions, by feeding off and into each other’s blind spots and pain points. As we project what we fear internally onto others or external events, we validate our fear while suppressing where it comes from. We believe danger to be outside of us, so we try to protect ourselves from it and, thereby, often act in ways that perpetuate the very danger we try to protect ourselves from. Jung describes this mechanism as “shadow projection.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the extent we’re unconsciously driven by fear, we become susceptible to manipulation. &lt;mark&gt;When millions of people project their unconscious shadows onto others, they conjure up the very danger everyone is trying to escape from.&lt;/mark&gt; Wilhelm Reich made these dynamics explicit during the rise of Hitler (see his 1933 book, The Mass Psychology of Fascism) and they’re the premise of all totalitarian regimes to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 9/11, we were told that our enemy was the Muslim world; now the “enemy” is invisible and might await us at every door handle, or creep into us as we kiss, hug or even breathe. The more extravagant the neurotic cinema that’s playing in our minds, the easier it is for external powers to control and use us for their interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The great unveiling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much more than just a difficult trial for humanity, the Covid-19 outbreak also holds the possibility for collective healing from the predatory mass infection of Wetiko. We can make sense of it as a global somatization – or symbolic simulation – of the underlying Wetiko disease. As with every outbreak of severe disease, the deeper patterns are now coming unstuck in plain sight at the global level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’re now witnessing a simultaneous unveiling, breakdown and intense exaggeration of Wetiko:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On an ecological level, Covid-19 originated as a direct result of our civilization’s insatiable greed for exponential growth. Probably wild animals transmitted the virus to people after the natural ecosystems which were home to them were destroyed by the ecocidal steamroller of civilizational “progress.” And now we’re equally astonished to see how quickly the air can clear in China, the speed at which wildlife returns to urban areas, and how suddenly old ecocidal endeavors collapse before our eyes (e.g. the S. fracking industry).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On an economic level, Covid-19 has been the straw that’s broken the camel’s back, setting off the chain reaction of a long overdue financial collapse. The lockdown has sent our globalized economy into a full-blown, rapid “evaporation,” with entire industries halting, millions of workers being laid off from one day to the next and stock markets crashing. The fossil fuel industry faces its “gravest challenge in its 100-year history,” from which it may never recover. The Federal Reserves are currently lending big banks an additional $1 trillion a day, which is to say, we’re now barely keeping the economic system on life support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the social and psychological levels, we see both a collective frenzy of extreme Wetiko behaviors and also many people breaking free. On one hand, social atomization, the desire for control and egoistic panic are reaching surreal pinnacles. We are seeing a massive surge in domestic abuse and the rapid conversion of liberal societies into police states; even leftists are praising the strengthening of top-down government and restrictions on civil liberties. On the other hand, thousands of local grassroots initiatives practicing mutual aid have popped up from one day to the next. Millions are entering a rare moment of reflection and of asking “what’s essential?” While locked down in quarantine, we’re confronted with ourselves, our longings and our lives. And &lt;mark&gt;many recognize how deeply we’ve been “socially distanced” all along&lt;/mark&gt; – divided up by the competitive ideals of a precarious labor market and our own inability to engage in authentic interpersonal connection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A parting of ways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will happen next is uncertain, but we can predict that the chain reaction of economic devastation may be inevitable. The global emergency may have come to stay. In other words, &lt;mark&gt;we may not go back to normal anytime soon, or perhaps ever again.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What will happen in the next few weeks and months will likely shape the world for many years to come. Rather than resisting the forces of entropy and indulging in faint hopes of a return to normality, &lt;mark&gt;the future will be on the side of those who are able to embrace chaos and disruption as an opportunity to propose a different vision for global society.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naomi Klein, author of The Shock Doctrine, says: “If there is one thing history teaches us, it’s that moments of shock are profoundly volatile. We either lose a whole lot of ground, get fleeced by elites, and pay the price for decades, or we win progressive victories that seemed impossible just a few weeks earlier. This is no time to lose our nerve.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burdened by astronomical debt and commanded by the imperative for exponential growth, the globalized capitalist system has come to an irreversible breaking point. The powers that be will either have to make way for system change or will stubbornly continue to prop up the old order with ever-more brutal force. While there may be many possible futures in front of us, I want to highlight the stark contrast of the historic choice we’re facing, in two contrasting future scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario #1: Surveillance capitalism&lt;/strong&gt;
After many months of lockdown, people have accepted the new era of quarantined existence. Governments have dismantled civil liberties, human rights and environmental protections and, under the pretext of health and safety, deployed unprecedented levels of surveillance technology. Mobile apps are used not only to track people’s physical movements but also their biochemical reactions. As Gideon Lichfield writes, “intrusive surveillance [is] considered a small price to pay for the basic freedom to be with other people.” In the background of a daily onslaught of fear-invoking messages, governments further redistribute wealth from the bottom 99% to the elites. Banks, fossil fuel and airline industries are bailed out with taxpayer’s money, while social security and public health systems are further dismantled. Austerity measures and the abolition of cash further marginalize working people, the poor and the homeless. General apathy and numbness have reached a dimension where the daily shooting of migrants at the borders and other atrocities no longer provoke any moral outcry. Locked into their flats, afraid of infection, monitored by digital body sensors, the powers that be have almost entirely crippled people’s ability to organize themselves and resist. Should protests or strikes still occur, the mass media can report on new dangerous infections spreading so that governments can swiftly impose new curfews to “keep our communities safe.” At some point, with climate breakdown, water crises and food shortages worsening, the system is no longer able to disguise its collapse. Chaos and violence can no longer be contained. The rich retreat to their gated compounds in remote areas, while masses of people find themselves trapped in disintegrating urban centers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario #2: Ecological and social emancipation&lt;/strong&gt;
In the months of uncertainty and economic disintegration, millions of people begin to organize themselves at the local grassroots levels to cover their basic needs. In this time of hardship, they rediscover the power of community, solidarity and localism. As people help each other through sickness and challenge, a spirit of empathy and interdependence spreads. After many months of unemployment, public chaos and food shortages, hopes for strong government and a return to normality have finally faded. &lt;mark&gt;Many realize that either we live out collapse alone or we get through this together.&lt;/mark&gt; The emergency initiatives of neighborhood aid now turn into more long-term initiatives of social, economic and ecological re-organization. People start collective gardens and food cooperatives to supply themselves with local organic crops and open solar energy task forces to decentralize and democratize their energy supply. More and more people leave the cities to found communities in the countryside, where they engage in restoring ecosystems and radical social experimentation for a more trust-based and loving way of living. People work together with progressive governments on large-scale ecological rehabilitation in response to the climate crisis, while governments support citizens’ agency through introducing Universal Basic Income. In the background of this astonishing social and ecological movement, a profound cultural and spiritual transformation takes place – a shift of consciousness from the Wetiko drive for domination to cooperation with all living beings, from atomizing mass societies to communities of trust, from the patriarchal condemnation of Eros and the feminine to a culture that celebrates sensual love in its freedom and dignity, from subduing the Earth to honoring her inherent sacredness, from fearing death to acknowledging our eternal existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;System change: the time is now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dangers of totalitarianism are dire and real and are becoming concretized in many countries already. But we mustn’t forget that those measures are the last resort in prolonging the death of a system that’s already on its way out. &lt;mark&gt;At this point, globalized capitalism is only being kept alive by our fearful projections and our inability to imagine something new, which is to say, if people can leave fear behind and unify around a shared vision of the future they want, nothing can stop the inevitable transition.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see the keys to system change lying in three essential realms of our lives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The spiritual sphere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having exaggerated Wetiko to unthinkably surreal heights, Covid-19 strangely invites us into a dimensional shift of being. As Paul Levy, the author of Dispelling Wetiko, maintains, the anti-virus hidden within the Wetiko disease is the awakening to its dream-like nature – a realization which has the potential to radically change our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we continue to react to the embodiments of Wetiko outside of us (e.g. viruses, external enemies or the dangers of totalitarianism…) as if they were separate from us, we will continue to act in ways that feed the very dynamic we’re afraid of. But if we begin to see Wetiko playing out within ourselves, it loses its grip on us. Compassion opens our eyes to understanding that which we previously could only fear, judge or hate. Trust reconciles us with the world and our fellow beings. &lt;mark&gt;Compassion and trust are the ultimate anti-viruses of Wetiko.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may suddenly wake up and realize how all systems of domination have never been “real” as such, their “reality” has always only existed through our consent. &lt;mark&gt;Money, authority, society, pandemics – we can now see the dreamlike nature of what we believed to be rock-solid and unchangeable.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To awaken from the fearful web of Wetiko is to simultaneously awaken to the interdependent web of Life. This is such a profound shift from where we come from in the Western world that it’s hard to even find words for it. The fear-stricken mind always asks for immediate conclusions, solutions, fixes. But maybe there is no such “fix” right now. Maybe, what this moment calls for is for us to let go of all our notions of self-importance, superiority and domination and to surrender to a greater-than-human intelligence and guidance, to inquire for orientation from the Earth and the Indigenous wisdom of cultures centered around the Earth. In this experience of communion lies a truth that is unambiguous, absolute and deeply healing: &lt;mark&gt;all life is sacred&lt;/mark&gt;. This isn’t only a private experience, but an insight into the inherent matrix of Life. In alignment with this matrix we stand outside the vicious cycles of fear, infection and violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The social sphere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Wetiko plays out relationally, its dissolution is a collective endeavor; a historic project of developing ways of living together in which we can heal our broken relationship to the Earth and each other, and develop deep trust among ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build trust, we need conditions which no longer force us to lie, disguise or protect ourselves. We need ways of living, loving, working and relating in which we can truly recognize each other and dare to show what we actually think and feel, love and desire. “Trust” is a word often used, but what does it mean in the delicate realms of our souls, such as love, sexuality and spirituality, where our vulnerabilities tend to be the greatest? This entails nothing short of a social revolution. Dieter Duhm, a mentor and teacher of mine, and author of The Sacred Matrix, writes, “Trust is not only classified as psychological; it is above all a political term – the most revolutionary of all – for &lt;mark&gt;we need to renew the entire societal structure to bring about sustainable, systemic trust&lt;/mark&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This revolution may not occur in mass movements immediately, but it can begin in small groups – wells of coherence – and extend across society from there, by virtue of raising a new field of consciousness. Based on 40 years of radical experimentation, the “Healing Biotopes Plan” offers a respective vision for such comprehensive transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The political and economic sphere&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freedom in the long-term requires our capacity to resist any restriction to civil and human rights in the short-term. In this time of social distancing, let us stand in solidarity together, especially with all those who are marginalized, rejecting any narrative of “us versus them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the globalized system crumbles, localization will be the key to the future. Now is the moment to decentralize supply systems for water, food and energy, to invest in regenerative agriculture and practices of ecosystem restoration, to create seed banks and exchange, and to establish networks and economic mechanisms of mutual aid, resource sharing and reciprocal gifting. &lt;mark&gt;Localization not only offers food sovereignty but also a path to political autonomy – as we take charge of our own basic needs, we can come together to make collaborative decisions from the bottom up.&lt;/mark&gt; From various ecosystem restoration practices to the permaculture, seed saving and ecovillage movements, all the way to large-scale social movements like Extinction Rebellion and experiments of radical grassroots democracy like Rojava and the Zapatistas, the world offers a thousand examples showing that this path is viable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the spiritual, social, and economic-political spheres are so inseparably intertwined, successful system change will rely on profound structural transformations in these three realms in parallel. It doesn’t mean we must all do everything at once, it means we must support each other. May we each listen deeply for what we’re now called to do and be, while remaining aware of each other. &lt;mark&gt;As much as narratives of isolation and social distancing threaten to keep us afraid and separate, our ability to go through this crisis relies on our ability to organize and build alliances, remembering that we are community.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever we may do, may we remember that this is a moment of unique historic possibility. As Julian Assange told Yanis Varoufakis from his prison cell by phone, “Anything goes… Everything is now possible.” And if there’s one thing that Covid-19 has taught us, it is that &lt;mark&gt;dramatic shifts of collective behavior can actually occur overnight.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Can we entertain the possibility that we as humanity – or some deeper part of ourselves, whether conscious or not – have dreamed this moment into existence as a catalyst for our collective evolution?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Pollination Approach</title><link href="/blog/2020/10/15/pollination-approach.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Pollination Approach" /><published>2020-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/10/15/pollination-approach</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/10/15/pollination-approach.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rhsmith.umd.edu/directory/bennet-zelner&quot;&gt;Bennet A. Zelner&lt;/a&gt;, first published in &lt;a href=&quot;https://maps.org/news/bulletin/articles/439-bulletin-spring-2020/8131-the-pollination-approach-to-delivering-psychedelic-assisted-mental-healthcare&quot;&gt;MAPS Bulletin Spring 2020: Vol. 30, No. 1&lt;/a&gt;. Highlights my own.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article I outline a novel economic approach for delivering psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare, the Pollination Approach. The Pollination Approach focuses on the intrinsically &lt;mark&gt;interdependent production of individual and community wellness&lt;/mark&gt;. It contrasts sharply with the current pharmaceutical-centered approach to mental healthcare, which focuses on the &lt;mark&gt;management of symptoms rather than the production of wellness&lt;/mark&gt;, and reflects divisive economic conceptions that have contributed to rising rates of mental distress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next section I describe the economic conceptions animating the pharmaceutical approach. In the following section I discuss the relationship among these conceptions, the disruption of community social and economic systems, and mental health. In the third section I present the Pollination Approach, describing how all of its facets–the design of treatment sites, the conduct of integration activities, the &lt;mark&gt;configuration of ownership and decision-making structures, and the financial structures used to create and allocate shared prosperity&lt;/mark&gt;–promote the production of wellness through the &lt;mark&gt;renewal and recirculation of community resources&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Pharmaceutical Approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pharmaceutical approach to mental healthcare portrays mental disorders as clusters of biologically-based symptoms susceptible to being treated primarily with drugs, much like a physical disease. This approach has benefited drug manufacturers, whose U.S. revenues from the sale of psychiatric drugs rose from $2.8 billion in 1987 (the year in which Prozac was introduced) to $34 billion in 2010. Yet despite the fact that antidepressants alone represent the most prescribed category of pharmaceuticals among the U.S. non-geriatric adult population, American mental health has reached a crisis state. &lt;mark&gt;The national suicide rate has increased to its greatest level in 50 years&lt;/mark&gt; and continues to rise. The U.S. also has the highest rate of death from mental health and substance abuse disorders among peer countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dire state of our collective mental health is linked to widely-held economic conceptions that have contributed to the pharmaceutical approach’s financial profitability. The first such conception is that of economic individualism. When psychiatric drugs were first introduced in the 1950s, patients were viewed as socially embedded individuals whose mental illness reflected &lt;mark&gt;both psychosocial and biological factors&lt;/mark&gt;, and for whom pharmaceutical treatment was considered an adjunct to psychological and social remedies. Pharmaceutical manufacturers actively promoted the reconceptualization of mental illness as a constellation of biologically-based symptoms, and of patients as atomized consumers devoid of psychological and social context. These shifts, which leveraged an ascendant cultural view of people as individualistic market participants, &lt;mark&gt;promoted the long-term consumption of medication as the primary modality for treating mental distress&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second widely-held economic conception that has contributed to the pharmaceutical approach’s financial profitability is the belief that unconstrained market processes produce the best economic outcomes. American drug manufacturers have leveraged and promoted this belief, sponsoring numerous economic studies intended to convince policymakers that a hands-off approach to the economic regulation of the industry would maximize innovation, with high drug prices representing the cost of progress. Prescription drug spending in the U.S. has increased dramatically as a result, rising more than 1,800% between 1980 and 2015 and outpacing that in other developed countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Disruption of Community Systems and the Impairment of Mental Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economic conceptions animating the pharmaceutical approach have impaired our collective mental health through their influence on an expanding array of policies and practices over the past four decades. Market competition is now widely regarded as the best and most natural organizing principle for all human relations, and economic individualism has come to represent not just independence and self-reliance, but the prioritization of self over relationships, and of individual success over the common good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason that these divisive conceptions have been so damaging is that they conflict with basic human nature. We possess an evolutionary drive to connect and cooperate with each other because doing so helped our ancestors survive. The primary structures in which we have traditionally expressed and fulfilled this drive are &lt;mark&gt;residential communities, complex systems of people and resources linked in interdependent social, economic, ecological, and other interrelated systems&lt;/mark&gt;. As in nature, healthy systems promote individual and collective well-being. However, the ascent of the economic conceptions discussed above has disrupted the functioning of community systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First consider community social systems. Americans no longer come together as they once did: They now have fewer interactions with friends and family, and are less likely to belong to organizations that provide opportunities for social interaction. This &lt;mark&gt;crisis of connection&lt;/mark&gt; is reflected in a loneliness epidemic that has fueled rising rates of depression, anxiety, and addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paralleling the crisis of connection in social systems is a &lt;mark&gt;crisis of extraction&lt;/mark&gt; in economic systems. In localities throughout the U.S., outposts of large corporations have displaced locally owned businesses. As a result, locally produced income is extracted by distant shareholders rather than being recirculated within the community to fund local (re)investment, contributing to economic inequality. Further, the extraction of decision-making authority by remote corporate managers with no direct connection to local ecosystems results in the &lt;mark&gt;unsustainable use of local resources&lt;/mark&gt;, depleting the human, natural, and other forms of productive capital available to provision ongoing local economic activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crises of disconnection and extraction in community social and economic systems have fueled rising rates of disorders such as depression and addiction. Disconnection is a core feature of depression and &lt;mark&gt;addiction represents an adaptive response to disconnection&lt;/mark&gt;. Economic stress increases vulnerability to both conditions. Large-scale statistical analysis supports these ideas, demonstrating that countries with greater income inequality – reflecting the promulgation of policies and practices embodying the individual-centric, hyper-competitive economic conceptions discussed above–exhibit higher rates of depression and illegal drug use (a proxy for addiction). &lt;mark&gt;A comprehensive approach to the delivery of mental healthcare must counteract these divisive conceptions’ damaging psychological influence by facilitating the repair of community systems, complementing and contributing to individual healing.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Pollination Approach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pollination Approach to delivering mental healthcare recognizes the &lt;mark&gt;mutually reinforcing relationship between individual and collective wellness&lt;/mark&gt;. It is rooted in the ecological principle that the production of wellness depends on the continual &lt;mark&gt;renewal and recirculation of system resources&lt;/mark&gt; (versus their extraction or depletion). &lt;mark&gt;Pollinator organizations facilitate the renewal and recirculation of resources in community systems as pollinator organisms do in natural systems&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Community Reconnection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delivery of psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare under the Pollination Approach facilitates, first and foremost, the renewal and recirculation of human resources. Psychedelic medicines possess a documented ability to foster connection, and the shift from disconnection to connection represents a key mechanism in the healing process. &lt;mark&gt;The Pollination Approach harnesses this shift by (re)connecting patients to social, economic, and other community systems, contributing to individual healing and the revitalization of the systems themselves.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Treatment sites enacting the Pollination Approach function as wellness centers&lt;/mark&gt;, gathering places where community members may participate in a range of healing and community-building activities in addition to psychedelic-assisted therapy. Explicit reconnection activities for those who have undergone therapy include &lt;mark&gt;group integration sessions&lt;/mark&gt; as well as &lt;mark&gt;community reintegration programs&lt;/mark&gt; conducted in partnership with local organizations, such as businesses, cultural institutions, civic organizations, religious organizations, and others. These organizations may also serve as points of access, especially in communities where psychedelic medicines are viewed with skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Local Wisdom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The identification of specific partner organizations and adaptation of other delivery-of-care elements to community needs and customs are undertaken in close consultation with local wisdom keepers. Community elders, social workers, ER workers, spiritual leaders, union representatives, local business owners, and others may all possess distinctive knowledge of common trauma patterns, recirculatory gaps in community systems, and sources of resource depletion and extraction. The integration of such wisdom with more generalized knowledge of therapeutic techniques and psychedelic medicines optimizes the delivery of care in a given community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Governance Principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ownership and governance of wellness centers under the Pollination Approach also support the production of wellness through the renewal and recirculation of community resources. Two core principles inform choices in this area. The first is &lt;mark&gt;stakeholder inclusivity, the notion that an organization should operate for the explicit benefit of its stakeholder groups including customers, employees, community members, and others&lt;/mark&gt;. The principle of stakeholder inclusivity naturally supports the inherently inclusive process of wellness production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The principle of stakeholder inclusivity contrasts sharply with the creed of shareholder primacy guiding most corporate decision-making.&lt;/mark&gt; The latter ascended in conjunction with the divisive economic conceptions discussed above. It holds that the sole purpose of a corporation is to serve the interests of shareholders by maximizing financial profits, as reflected in the pharmaceutical approach’s emphasis on managing symptoms. The production of wellness is less lucrative for pharmaceutical shareholders because it reduces the need for ongoing medical intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second principle informing the ownership and governance of wellness centers under the Pollination Approach is &lt;mark&gt;distributed local ownership&lt;/mark&gt;. Local ownership supports the health of community economic systems by promoting the recirculation of income, creating an economic multiplier effect from the local (re)investment that such recirculation enables. Local ownership also promotes the sustainable use of a community’s human, natural, and other productive resources because owners and managers participate directly in the local ecosystem, attuning them to local conditions. &lt;mark&gt;Distributed local ownership–ownership that is spread widely among local community members from different stakeholder groups&lt;/mark&gt;–amplifies these benefits by dispersing financial returns and diversifying the information sources contributing to decision-making. Collaborative ties between wellness centers and non-local organizations in the psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare ecosystem, such as MAPS and MAPS PBC, complement local ownership by promoting the circulation of global resources, such as knowledge gained through experiential learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Cooperative Organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The organizational form that most naturally supports the principles of stakeholder inclusivity and distributed local ownership is a cooperative structure, which distributes ownership and control among the members of stakeholder groups such as workers or customers&lt;/mark&gt;. Treatment sites enacting the Pollination Approach may distribute ownership and control most widely by adopting a &lt;mark&gt;multi-stakeholder cooperative structure&lt;/mark&gt;, in which the cooperative’s owners include members of both of these groups as well as other community stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooperatives are typically organized as corporations or LLCs, legal forms that distribute the financial returns from community wellness centers among stakeholder-owners. Though non-profit organizations are more commonly associated with the production of social returns, &lt;mark&gt;existing legal classifications do not readily accommodate entities producing both types of return because they reflect an ingrained assumption that the two are incompatible.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An organization’s legal form also does not by itself guarantee a given behavior pattern. For example, &lt;mark&gt;some non-profit hospitals have been criticized for accumulating large cash reserves that are not being used to benefit the community&lt;/mark&gt;, while the Business Roundtable–an association of corporate CEOs that has traditionally endorsed shareholder primacy–recently proclaimed that a corporation’s purpose is to promote “an economy that serves all Americans.” &lt;mark&gt;The extent to which a wellness center’s specific incentive and decision-making structures support the mission objectives and governance principles discussed above is thus more consequential than its legal form.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Financial Structures for Sharing Prosperity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As discussed above, multi-stakeholder cooperative organization enables community stakeholders to share in the financial returns generated by local wellness centers enacting the Pollination Approach. Symmetrically, wellness centers may finance their ongoing operations by sharing in the economic prosperity they enable for patients and communities. &lt;mark&gt;Mechanisms such as deferred payment plans linked to patients’ post-treatment income, employer-sponsored insurance coverage of consciousness-focused healthcare, and government grant funding based on reduced public welfare spending facilitate the collection of revenues from the provision of psychedelic-assisted therapy.&lt;/mark&gt; Similarly, the performance of contract research for entities such as MAPS, and the provision of therapy sessions and apprenticeships to trainees in external credentialing programs, create revenues and control costs by tapping into shared value co-created with other participants in the psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial funders play a critical role in this ecosystem. &lt;mark&gt;The equitable sharing of jointly enabled prosperity between funders and other stakeholders requires innovation because traditional funding structures reflect the dichotomy between the production of social and economic returns embodied in the legal distinction between non-profit and for-profit enterprise.&lt;/mark&gt; On the one hand, philanthropic funders may be unwilling to contribute to wellness centers organized as for-profit entities due to the ingrained belief that non-profits specialize in the production of social returns, an assumption that is reinforced by the favorable tax treatment of non-profit donations under the U.S. federal tax code. On the other hand, conventional venture-style mechanisms for the external funding of for-profit startups focus on the production of concentrated financial returns for the benefit of shareholders who retain a long-term equity stake, which conflicts with the governance principles discussed above. Wellness centers funded with such mechanisms would be deterred from generating wider social and economic returns through the renewal and recirculation of community resources, and also from engaging in the prototyping necessary for continual learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financing mechanisms that transcend these institutionalized trade-offs are currently under development. One example is a structure that builds on recent innovations in venture capital financing intended to align the long-term incentives of founders and funders. It works by paying initial funders a &lt;mark&gt;capped return&lt;/mark&gt; drawn from wellness centers’ operating cash flows; transferring funders’ original equity claim to a stakeholder pool; and distributing or selling shares in this pool to workers, patients, and members of other local stakeholder groups. Ultimately, these local owners would go on to pollinate additional local economic activity by investing their financial dividends (and perhaps their knowledge, labor, and social capital) into other community enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Psychedelic-assisted mental healthcare holds revolutionary potential for treating various forms of mental distress. In order to fully realize this potential, it should be delivered using an equally revolutionary economic approach.&lt;/mark&gt; The Pollination Approach outlined above seeks to meet this aspiration by serving as more than a conventional business model, and as a source of healing itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Pollination Approach focuses on the intrinsically interdependent production of individual and community wellness</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unplugging from Facebook</title><link href="/blog/2020/07/09/unplugging-from-facebook.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unplugging from Facebook" /><published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/07/09/unplugging-from-facebook</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/07/09/unplugging-from-facebook.html">&lt;p&gt;Hi friends,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m significantly changing how I use Facebook and other corporate social media. I&amp;#39;m not going to feed it, and I&amp;#39;m not going to let it feed me any longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#39;m not going to post on my Facebook profile or page. I may occasionally post in groups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#39;ve set it up so I can&amp;#39;t see my Facebook newsfeed on desktop or mobile (more on this below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially I&amp;#39;m just going to use Facebook as an &lt;strong&gt;address book/events discovery/search tool&lt;/strong&gt; from now on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also not be posting on Twitter, Instagram or YouTube. I already don&amp;#39;t use the newsfeeds on Twitter or Instagram. I will continue to follow a handful of channels on YouTube that aren&amp;#39;t available on Spotify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Where I will be posting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~daily: articles I read to my homepage (&lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.net/&quot;&gt;web&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.net/feed.rss&quot;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~weekly: blog posts to my blog (&lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.net/blog&quot;&gt;web&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.net/blog/feed&quot;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;), written with &lt;a href=&quot;https://typora.io/&quot;&gt;Typora&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~occasionally: episodes to my &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.net/podcast&quot;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;~monthly: newsletters to my &lt;a href=&quot;https://stephenreid.substack.com/&quot;&gt;Substack&lt;/a&gt;, which will feature a summary of content I&amp;#39;ve created since the previous newsletter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How I read/listen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discover articles via &lt;a href=&quot;https://feedly.com/&quot;&gt;Feedly&lt;/a&gt;, including following a few Twitter accounts/Facebook pages converted with &lt;a href=&quot;http://fetchrss.com/&quot;&gt;FetchRSS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listen to podcasts via Spotify and (reluctantly) YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Hiding your Facebook newsfeed on desktop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install Stylus (&lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylus/clngdbkpkpeebahjckkjfobafhncgmne?hl=en&quot;&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/addon/styl-us/&quot;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt;) or Stylish (&lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/stylish-custom-themes-for/fjnbnpbmkenffdnngjfgmeleoegfcffe?hl=en&quot;&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/addon/stylish/&quot;&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt;), then install &lt;a href=&quot;https://userstyles.org/styles/186176/facebook-desktop-by-stephen-reid&quot;&gt;this tiny script I wrote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Hiding your Facebook newsfeed on mobile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s no way of hiding the newsfeed in the mobile app, so uninstall it and train yourself to only access Facebook through Firefox. Install &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-GB/firefox/addon/stylish/&quot;&gt;Stylish&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://userstyles.org/styles/186175/facebook-mobile-by-stephen-reid&quot;&gt;this tiny script I wrote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Further reading/listening&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open.spotify.com/episode/6AMD8pCZzgsdoRvLxlqPJa&quot;&gt;Emerge: Zak Stein - American Culture&amp;#39;s Psychotic Break&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://humanetech.com/problem/&quot;&gt;Center for Humane Technology: The Problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dontgobacktonormal.uk/&quot;&gt;Don&amp;#39;t Go Back To Normal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I'm significantly changing how I use Facebook and other corporate social media</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sand Talk Dream Walk</title><link href="/blog/2020/04/14/sand-talk-dream-walk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sand Talk Dream Walk" /><published>2020-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/04/14/sand-talk-dream-walk</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/04/14/sand-talk-dream-walk.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A guided meditation (&amp;#39;dream walk&amp;#39;) featured in the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/45449501-sand-talk&quot;&gt;Sand Talk: How Indigenous Thinking Can Save the World&lt;/a&gt; by Indigenous Australian author Tyson Yunkaporta.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;He recommends reading it aloud to someone, or to a group of people, while they sit or lie down with their eyes closed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here now. Picture in your mind a campfire you have seen, from a time when you have felt safe and happy and connected. See the fire, see it clear, have no fear. See deep into the heart of the hearth to the flame in the hot coals. See it dance, see the rhythm of it flickering. Feel the heat on your hands and face. Rub your hands together, make them hot, then rest them on your belly just under your navel. Rest them warm on your belly and feel the heat there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Picture and feel the campfire in your mind. It is a real thing, this image. It exists, but where is it? Is it in your brain? No, it is in your mind. but where is your mind if not just in your brain? Imagine for a minute that your mind is not trapped only inside your skull; that it can move around your body. See the campfire in your head, crackling yellow and red. Feel the heat of it reach your face. Now try and move it down, that image, see it move and feel the warmth of it move, down your face and past your chin, down your neck and to your chest, see it and feel it move down past your liver, down over your stomach to your lower belly area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hold the image of the fire right there in your belly. It is not in your head now. Your mind is more than your brain and your sight is more than what your eyes provide. Your mind’s eye can see the fire there in your belly. See it, feel it burn. There is a power there, in your belly. This is your big power. It has energy, warmth and a rhythm, just like the fire you are seeing there with your mind’s eye. Feel it under your hands, burning bright. Now blow it to burn brighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a slow, deep breath. blow it gently out through lips that are almost closed, the way you blow on hot coals to make them glow. See the coals crackle and spark. Your hands are protecting the fire in your belly. See it as you breathe in again slowly and blow right into the heart of the hearth fire. breathe in, breathe out, see the coals glow and the flames flare. Keep breathing in and out now, fanning the flames. The air from this place, as it enters your lungs, is leaving small pieces of itself behind that enter your bloodstream and race through it to every part of your body. Those pieces are like sponges, mopping up tiny pockets of poison, poison left behind from a thousand sad feelings, bad memories, toxic events and attacks and accidents and damaged lands, stolen places, stolen things, corrupted waters, murders and massacres, fences and blocks and assaults and insults and injuries and hidden histories. let those poisons be mopped up by the little sponges of air in your blood, let them be taken in those sponges all through your body and back to your lungs, moving back from liquid to air and blown back out through your mouth and nose. blow the badness out, let it leave you and disintegrate in the air, rise up far above and blow away on the breeze.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The poisonous things leave behind dry areas, damaged areas, in your body. Imagine all through your limbs and torso and head, all this dry and crackly dead grass, snapped branches and grey, papery leaves. All this scrubby trash is blocking your mind from moving freely around your body. See the fire there in your belly. blow again on the hot coals, gently, seeing them glow and feeling the heat. blow again, harder this time, and see the sparks begin to spiral up from the fire as you blow. blow again, harder, and make the sparks fly further from the flames, fluttering upwards into the dry, dead grasses laying thick under your ribs. See them land there, settle in the feathery fronds, smoking softly in wisps that wind up through the itchy snarls of grasses and sticks on layers of leaves. See the tiny flames flare and climb and spiral and spread, and a sparrowhawk swoops in, wings in the rhythm of the flames, to take one of the smoking sticks in its talons, sweeping off inland to drop it smouldering in the knotted undergrowth of your chest. The fire forms a long line burning across your torso, dancing the same rhythm as the fire in your belly, bright yellow flames that burn briefly and not too hot, leaving soft, cool ash that crumbles into the soil, your flesh, and nourishes it, and will continue to nourish it each day as the dew drops fall and settle and sift inwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The line of fire spreads upwards. All the scars and injuries and brittle patches left by damage and loss and abuse are being swept into the fire and made into soft charcoal and ash, swirling together like crow and white cockatoo feathers. Soon it will spread to your throat, then your eyes, then your ears, then your hands. See the flames and smoke and feel the heat and hear the crackling and snapping through your ribs, your collarbones, your neck and throat, mouth and chin, nose and cheeks, eyes, forehead and scalp, ears, shoulders, arms and elbows, forearms and hands all burning and the smoke billowing out through your fingers and high into the sky. Dry, damaged areas are all made clean and new and warm and light. The fire spreads now, from your hands, past the campfire hearth in your belly, flames leaping across from your fingers to your hips, burning through the dry grass there and on through your loins and buttocks and thighs. The fire has a rhythm—feel it dance in your legs. Your knees pop and crackle as they go up in flame, your shins and calves, your ankles and feet, until smoke billows out of your toes and high into the sky, leaving you light and clean and new. Dew drops fall and cool everything down, dampening the ashes and soot and soaking it into the ground where heated seeds sprout and begin to take root. Country is becoming well. You are Country. You are becoming well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of somebody you love unconditionally, no matter what. If you can’t do this you need to stop now and go take care of your life. If you can, picture that person in your mind and let yourself feel that love for them, feel it like a sensation coming over you. Keep seeing the image of that person and feeling that love, then picture them in a special place. That place will be somewhere outdoors that is special to you both, a place where you have shared joy and love together, where you have connected deeply with the land and with each other. See every part of the landscape around you, the plants, trees, dirt or stones. See the person you love holding a big bucket of water. They tip it out onto the ground. They follow it where it flows, but let it ignore any civilised or synthetic barriers. Follow them, the loved one and the water, and pay attention to the way the water moves on the ground in that place, where it goes, where it stops, where it sinks. Feel the love for that person and then stretch out with that feeling, and feel the same sensation for that place. let your love move all across it, through it and into it, the same way rainwater would if it fell there right now. Feel that love spreading all over that Country. Where do you feel it in your body? In your chest, head, belly? Is that all? Is that feeling just inside you, or does it go further? Can you feel that love outside yourself, a long way off, in that special place? It is right there, a part of you and a part of the one you love, a feeling, a part of your mind and spirit, right there in that place. Can you feel it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holding on to that feeling, let the picture of your loved one and that place fade gently into the background. Slowly replace it with an image of the place where you are now. Not a room or a building—allow all that to be transparent. See the land, the ground, the waters and landforms around you and beneath you. Hold the feeling of love. Imagine where the water would flow if it fell on that ground right now. let the love trickle out from you, lapping outwards in ripples or tinkling in streams through the earth, see it there all around you for that place, feel it in the place. Feel the place. love the place. There may be wounds or sickness there in the land that make you sad, but hold that loving feeling because it is unconditional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The love is not just a feeling in your body now, or in a distant place, or with another person. It is around you in the place where you sit, in the land, along with the feeling from all the old people who have been connecting the same way with that place for thousands of years. All the memories of those Ancestors are there. All your own Ancestors’ memories lie inside you in the same way, in your bones, in every part of you, in your cellular memory. Mind and memory are real things although they can’t be touched, measured, proven or even seen. They exist, but not only in your brain. They extend out, to your body, to the land and your relations. Your mind is infinite and extends as far as your attention and love can go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mind, brain, body, land, loved ones—all these things at the front of your thoughts at once; they make you heavy. Your body and spirit sinking, thinking, heaviness moving deep through you. Eyelids heavy, closed; hands heavy on your belly, back pressed into the ground—skull, shoulders, feet, legs, all heavy. The feeling, the loving in the land and the love in your body are the same thing, you and the earth the same thing now, so you sink right into it. Feel yourself going through the floor or ground like it’s quicksand, but transparent, the land, you, sinking slowly into the dirt or sand beneath you. There are layers of rock and water down here, and you pass through them, sifted and cleaned by them as they pass through you, cooling you as you fall deeper and deeper into the dark. You are not afraid. You are not alone. You begin to feel that loving feeling again, only now it is not coming from you, but coming into you, flowing through you and around you. There is a warmth and a rhythm to it. A deep rhythm sounding deep, deep down. You sink further, faster towards the loving rhythm and the warmth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see a soft glow, closer and closer, warmer and warmer, the rhythm thicker, thicker and older and stronger and deeper than anything else. It is familiar, comforting, and so is the glow. The glow is from a fire, a hearth fire or a heart-fire with hot coals and you know it. You’ve seen it before. Could it be the sun? It is the same as the fire in your belly, the image in your mind from before, only it is massive. Its power is made of the same stuff as the power you carry in your belly, your big power. As you feel the heat and rhythm you sense the same inside you, beneath your hands, thrumming and glowing. It feels like a fish sniffing at a line, deep beneath the sea. It is faint but real at your fingertips, stirring deep in your belly. You know this. You remember this place, the earth you came from, the big mother that bore you. You’re home. Now that big hearth fire under the earth stokes your own fire, the fire in your belly, replenishing your power, filling you up with endless love and energy. It is clean, warm and pure, and lifts you up. You feel lighter, and upwards you go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glow disappears beneath you but the rhythm and flame remain in your belly. They propel you up, up, up, up through miles of heat and rock and cold and earth and more rock and sand and water and earth, up, up, up until you reach the place where your body is sitting or lying there in the world. but you can’t stop. You keep drifting upwards now, lighter than burnt leaves on the breeze, stirring and rising up, up, up through any ceilings or tree tops, up, up through any clouds and into a shining blueness that stretches as far as you can see all around. Up and up still you rise, as the blue becomes deeper, richer, darker. Soon it falls away beneath you and you are into a clear black infinity all around. The earth is far below and you drift on through burning stars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Seven Sisters are here, burning bright. All the hero Ancestors are up here, sky camp, watching you, blazing, that same fire again. Your rhythm is pulsing out to them; they are pulsing back, light washing through you in waves, stoking up that fire inside you again, blazing those coals, washing you clean and clear. Can your mind even extend up here, to the patterns in the endless night sky? Can your mind possibly perceive all of these stars, shapes, gaps—forms made by those gaps, the stories and morality and rich knowledge here, thousands of parts, all at once? Can it know every part at once? What it does hold for sure are the patterns created by all these parts. It sees objects pulled towards a space and knows what must lie there out of sight. It is able to see the swirl and stories and positions and angles and times and seasons all at once, to read the big patterns these show together and therefore make predictions and judgments about land-based events, phenomena, weather, ritual, the timing of all things in your life throughout each cycle of seasons, the longer cycles of generations and the even longer cycles of deep time and story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would it take to free your mind, allow it to see these big patterns again? All the Ancestors up here, they left their traces in the earth and waters below as well, and you carry those traces within, those memories and knowledges and deep, deep love. Those things wait for you, below. They tug at you, begin to draw you down. You are no longer light, but not heavy either. You are in balance, and you return to your place of love below. You are a point of connection between the earth and sky camp, so go, be that. You drop, plummet through stars and darkness and blue-black and deep blue and light blue and maybe clouds and water drops and tree tops and ceilings and then softly, softly, softly settle back down, down to earth, into the feeling of your place and your body, the rhythm that never stops, the fire in your belly, your power and the infinite potential of your mind, within and without. &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A guided meditation ('dream walk') featured in the book Sand Talk by Indigenous author Tyson Yunkaporta.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Key concepts from Seeing That Frees</title><link href="/blog/2020/03/24/paticcasamuppada.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Key concepts from Seeing That Frees" /><published>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/03/24/paticcasamuppada</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/03/24/paticcasamuppada.html">&lt;p&gt;Key concepts from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25172403-seeing-that-frees&quot;&gt;Seeing That Frees&lt;/a&gt; by Rob Burbea&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anattā – not-self&lt;br /&gt;
Anicca – impermanence&lt;br /&gt;
Avijjā – ignorance&lt;br /&gt;
Bhava – becoming&lt;br /&gt;
Citta – heart/mind&lt;br /&gt;
Dukkha – suffering, unsatisfaction&lt;br /&gt;
Jarāmarana – decay-death&lt;br /&gt;
Jāti – birth&lt;br /&gt;
Nāmarūpa – mind-and-mattter, mentality-materiality&lt;br /&gt;
Papañca – conceptual proliferation&lt;br /&gt;
Phassa – contact&lt;br /&gt;
Salāyatana – six sense spheres&lt;br /&gt;
Sankhāra – fabrications, volitional formations&lt;br /&gt;
Tanhā – craving&lt;br /&gt;
Upādāna – clinging&lt;br /&gt;
Vedanā – feeling-tone&lt;br /&gt;
Viññāna – consciousness, knowing&lt;br /&gt;
Śūnyatā – emptiness&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dependently arising, and mutually empty!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Paticcasamuppada and related concepts</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My journey through life</title><link href="/blog/2020/03/20/karuna-journey.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My journey through life" /><published>2020-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2020/03/20/karuna-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2020/03/20/karuna-journey.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Me, age 1&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote this as part of my application to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.karuna-institute.co.uk/foundation-training.html&quot;&gt;Karuna Institute&amp;#39;s Foundation in Core Process Psychotherapy&lt;/a&gt;, which I completed last week. The prompt was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please write between two and four A4 sides on your journey through life. This should include significant life events, both difficult and expansive. Some information on your early years would be useful, as well as details of any psychotherapy/counselling, bodywork, group work and your spiritual journey. If you have a current spiritual practice of any form it is useful for us to know.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;d share it, but somehow in these strange times it feels appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a deep practice, and I invite you to consider giving it a go. This could be just for yourself, it could be something you share with a partner/close friend/family member (I did this first), or if it feels right you could share it more widely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of parts of this I might now change, but in the spirit of rawness and vulnerability, I&amp;#39;m sharing it unedited. Here it goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born in Croydon, London as the first child of my parents Ian and Liz, both in their late 20s, in a small home in the centre of the town. At the time my father, Ian, ran a removals company and my mother, Liz, was a teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also living in the house in my early years was my teenage uncle James, my father&amp;#39;s brother, who is strongly autistic. He moved in after the passing of my father&amp;#39;s father, and due to the unwillingness or inability of my father&amp;#39;s mother to care for him, which I believe was related to alcohol dependency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My sister Chloe was born 2 years after me, and my brother Michael 3 years after that. My memories of my very early years are that I was well-cared for and happy. My father studied for a degree in Computer Science and got a job as a programmer, which inspired in me a lifelong fascination with technology. Around the time of my brother&amp;#39;s birth we moved out of the centre to greener parts in the south of the town, without my uncle James, who moved into a care home some distance away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James would return to our family home for weeks at a time during the period when I was 5-10. His behaviour was often difficult or destructive, and I remember my father often becoming very angry with him and hitting him, which I found greatly upsetting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this time I also became aware that my father was drinking a lot on a near daily basis. He never seemed to become angry or agitated around his direct family, rather becoming low/withdrawn. At the same time, he could be an incredibly energetic and creative man - I believe at some point in future years he was formally diagnosed with bipolar disorder. In contrast, I remember my mother having a remarkably stable mood. I had the sense they loved each other and us, their children, very much, despite these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We moved home again when I was around 11. Around this time, my grandmother, who was a single parent to my mother who had no siblings, passed away from bowel cancer. This was my first significant experience of death, and was a challenging time for my mother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started at an all-boys state grammar school where I excelled academically. I had plenty of friends and enjoyed sports. There was a culture of teasing and &amp;#39;banter&amp;#39; at the school which often involved homophobic insults. When I was around 13, I was sexually abused by a peer who pressured me into touching his genitals and having mine touched. For some time after I remember feeling dirty and ashamed. These feelings dissipated after he and other peers came out as gay and attitudes towards homosexuality in my peer group changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my teenage years, I remember my father continuing to struggle with bipolar disorder, and I became aware of his addictive personality, which I believe was a consequence of abuse he suffered as a child. At various times he was addicted to spending, fast food, pornography, tobacco, alcohol and heroin. Several times I found burnt spoons and used syringes in our basement. I remember developing an attitude of anger and disapproval towards him, and sometimes shouting at him to pull himself together, which typically triggered withdrawal and low mood in him. He was a high-functioning addict, continued to hold down a well-paid job in the IT industry, and despite his challenges he continued to show the family a lot of love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left home to study Physics at the University of Oxford at 18. My father&amp;#39;s health deteriorated, and when I was 20 he was rushed to hospital with ruptured esophageal varices. He was in intensive care for 2 weeks before the doctors told us he wasn&amp;#39;t going to get better. I remember crying over him in the cubicle before we took the decision to turn off his life support. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His passing was an initiatory experience for me. I felt grief for his passing, also a sense of relief that he didn&amp;#39;t have to suffer any more, and relief for my devoted mother who had had to watch him destroy himself. Becoming the oldest male in the family inspired a sense of maturity and responsibility in me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less than 3 months later, my sister and brother returned home from school to find my mother collapsed and unresponsive. I rushed back to London from Oxford and made it to the hospital just in time to hear the doctor explain that she had a massive undetected brain tumour that had snapped her brain stem, and that she was brain-dead. I remember crying over her alone in the cubicle, before again- dreamlike- we made the decision to turn off the life support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My sister was about to go to university, my brother moved in with family friends and I continued my studies. We would return to live together in our family home during the holidays. Despite being quite different people, we bonded deeply over these experiences and continue to enjoy a profound connection. They both also excelled academically, my sister graduating in Music from the University of Oxford, and my brother in Medicine from the University of Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 22, I moved to Bristol to study a year-long Masters in Complexity Sciences. Whilst I was there I broke up with my partner who I had been in a relationship with from the age of 17. I was upset and somewhat resistant for a time, but soon enough I understood it was the right decision for both of us. I had funding to continue to PhD but decided not to take it up, so that in January of 2010 I had completed my studies and was single for the first time in years. I felt an enormous sense of freedom. Looking back, I see that time as a rebirth/entry into a new phase of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to study at a language school in Strasbourg, France for some months. When I returned to the UK, I moved back to London and got heavily involved in Climate Camp, an climate activism group taking direct action and civil disobedience. With friends from Climate Camp, I co-founded UK Uncut, an anti-austerity group using civil disobedience to protest the new Conservative government&amp;#39;s austerity programme. This group became very successful, frequently making the news. I was arrested twice in connection with it, the second time for being part of an occupation of the upmarket department store Fortnum &amp;amp; Mason on Piccadilly. This resulted in a two-week trial at the Crown Court for aggravated trespass, where we were ultimately found not guilty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around this time, I discovered psychedelic substances. I had always been wary of drugs due to the story of my father, but I had some amazing early experiences with psychedelics which inspired a real fascination. I found psychedelic experiences to be an excellent first-person complement to the third-person perspective of science in studying the nature of consciousness and reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, I set up the Psychedelic Society, initially focused on campaigning for the legal regulation of psychedelic substances. At the beginning of 2016, the Society started running Psychedelic Experience Retreats, taking groups of 10-15 people to beautiful properties in the Netherlands (where psilocybin truffles are legal) for facilitated group psychedelic experiences. I co-facilitated the first 6 or so retreats, though I am not currently involved in that part of the organisation, feeling my time and talents have been better spent elsewhere. The Psychedelic Society is now a workers&amp;#39; cooperative with 7 members and a space in Hackney, London that hosts events including dance, meditation and talks almost every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left London to go travelling at the end of 2017, during which time I drank ayahuasca for the first time as part of a 10-day dieta in the Peruvian Amazon. This helped me to reflect upon and celebrate the lives of my parents, which I realised I had not given myself much chance to do since their passings. I described my experience in a series of blog pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned to the UK in mid 2019 and made the decision to move to Totnes, where I am living now. I meditate regularly for 30 minutes each morning; participate in plant medicine ceremonies every few months; keep fit through dance, running and swimming; enjoy playing guitar and singing; listen regularly to podcasts; read plenty of books; and love spending time on the moor and at the coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@stephenreid321/dieta-with-noya-rao-part-1-welcome-to-the-jungle-23bdefec1dad&quot;&gt;Blog series describing the dieta&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acpponline.net/&quot;&gt;Find a Core Process Psychotherapist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I didn't think I'd share this, but somehow in these strange times it feels appropriate.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Relative Utopia</title><link href="/blog/2019/11/22/relative-utopia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Relative Utopia" /><published>2019-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/11/22/relative-utopia</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/11/22/relative-utopia.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chapter 1 of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/47157252-nordic-ideology&quot;&gt;Nordic Ideology&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=100015149321507&quot;&gt;Hanzi Freinacht&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Here’s the deal. The human soul doesn’t want to be advised or fixed or saved. It simply wants to be witnessed—to be seen, heard and companioned exactly as it is. When we make that kind of deep bow to the soul of a suffering person, our respect reinforces the soul’s healing resources, the only resources that can help the sufferer make it through.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: right&quot;&gt;—Parker Palmer &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, we’re living in our ancestors’ utopia. If they could have witnessed our lives today, they probably wouldn’t have believed their eyes: all the food you can eat, a minimum of hard manual labor, the expectation to see &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; your children reach adult age, and no drunken lords to abuse you—truly a paradise compared to what most of them had to put up with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have access to a large number of conveniences that in the past would have been the envy of even kings and nobles: modern healthcare, comfortable and speedy transportation, and safe, fresh food from all around the world, even during winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few of us would want to switch our pleasant modern lifestyle with that of Louis XIV 300 years ago. After all, not even the extravagant Sun King himself ever flew to the Canary Islands during his winter holiday and sat on a beach without catching malaria while enjoying his favorite show on Netflix. And we would presumably soon tire of court jesters and pheasant dinners in leaky castles anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have become accustomed to a standard of living so high not even Moses parting the Red Sea would impress us. Why wander to the land of milk and honey when we can cross the seas in comfortable jets to places with much more interesting cuisine? Jesus too would probably have needed to up his game if he were to make disciples out of us modern people. Turning water into wine hardly competes with the marvel of a good 3D-printer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in the social realm we have opportunities and privileges unimaginable in the past. A medieval farmer would not have believed it if he was told that his descendants would have voting rights, freedom of expression, property rights, police protection and the freedom to choose their religion. And a 19th century factory worker would have been dumbstruck by the life-conditions of common folks today: considerably shorter work hours, vacations, pensions, unemployment benefits and an abundance of cheap consumer goods that used to be considered luxuries. Lenin’s grandiose promise of peace, bread and land that made a generation of workers start a revolution is so modest and unambitious in comparison to all the things we take for granted today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are of course still people who struggle to make ends meet: single unemployed parents, paperless immigrants, people with mental illnesses, substance addicts, and so on. But overall, we must admit we have come very far. We may not live in a true utopia, but in comparison to the past, modern society is at least a &lt;strong&gt;relative utopia&lt;/strong&gt;; truly utopian relative to what used to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the word “utopia” actually means “nowhere”. It goes back to the proto-modern thinker Thomas More’s book Utopia from 1516. In this meaning of the word, we do actually live in yesterday’s Nowhereland, in a fairytale, a technological Shangri-La that in the past only could have existed as fiction. Yet, as things went on, the fictional became all the more factual. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, there is little reason to believe the metamodern society we are headed towards won’t be a relative utopia; that what is currently only conceivable as a fictional account one day will materialize and acquire ostensibly utopian properties—relative to what we’re putting up with today and take for self-evident conditions of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The “Both-And” of Development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if the argument &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be made that traditional society was “better” than the modern one (as so-called “integral traditionalists” like Frithjof Schuon and Réné Guénon have argued: less pollution, more spirituality, a more enchanted sense of the world, less destructive weapons, less mindless consumerism and alienation, more independence in having the skills to produce what you need, more humility, etc.); this should not blind us to the circumstance that modernity largely solved all of the major problems of pre-modern society. Yup, pretty much all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For most of recorded history, child mortality was high, starvation commonplace, slavery institutionalized, serfdom ubiquitous, wars frequent, violence a part of everyday life, monarchical oppression unquestioned, disease rampant, poverty the rule, literacy low, cruel norms limiting individual freedom prevailing—and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, all of these miseries exist in the modern world too. In absolute numbers, some of them are perhaps worse than ever as the world population is so much larger. On the other hand—and this is the point here—all of these problems have decreased dramatically in &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; terms. Indeed, if you look at the highly modernized, democratic parts of the world, there is an apparent decrease in all of these problems at least by a power of ten. Look at Sweden today: How many people are starving for each one hundred who starved in the 1700s? One? Probably not even that. When people are poor in the US today, they get food stamps and have to stand in line. In pre-modern times, they simply starved to death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So modernity, with all its technological and social advances, has practically solved all of the problems of all earlier societies: famine, disease, oppression, war, poverty, lack of education, slow and dangerous transportation, superstition. Yes, even war; even if we count the world wars, the risk of being killed by another human being was statistically smaller during the 20th century than at any time before. Steven Pinker wrote an often-cited book about it in 2011, &lt;em&gt;The Better Angels of Our Nature&lt;/em&gt;, and then another one in 2018, &lt;em&gt;Enlightenment Now&lt;/em&gt;. Since the millennium, the number of people killed globally in violent conflicts has been extremely low compared to any previous period (in &lt;em&gt;per capita&lt;/em&gt; terms).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, of course, modern life is no walk in the park; it is still incredibly cruel and full of suffering—something that granny’s granny probably would have had a hard time imagining if we went on for hours about all the awesome sauce (I imagine I’d pause for a long time to describe what I get to eat, where I have traveled and so forth).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, it’s a &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; utopia: It really is super-duper mega awesome not to starve, to have modern medicine, to be able to speak and think freely, to have dominant sex with hot young men if you’re an old guy (I suppose granny might have had a problem with that part), to choose how to live your life and what to do for a living, to have internet and all kinds of abundance (even when unemployed, you can eat well and have shelter and use many of the technologies). It really is nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time that doesn’t mean life has become “perfect”. So today’s developed societies really &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; utopian, but only in a &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; sense. This is the &lt;strong&gt;both-and&lt;/strong&gt; of development. They are utopian as &lt;em&gt;compared&lt;/em&gt; to what came before. But that doesn’t mean today’s society has no problems. In fact, it has two very distinct kinds of problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Residual problems&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New emergent properties problems&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;residual problems&lt;/strong&gt; are the percentages left here and there of the pre-modern stage of development: not all people are protected from curable diseases, some live in areas controlled by mobsters and are thereby still oppressed, some slavery still goes on (30 million &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; slaves is a figure people often bring up), and some people still starve or otherwise suffer from poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that the UN Development Goals were met in advance and abject poverty is withering away as economic growth and ambitious, far-reaching aid programs take effect. But still, there are some residuals here and there, and they should certainly be accounted for; they still define hundreds of millions of lives. They are, however, not quite the &lt;em&gt;products&lt;/em&gt; of modern society, as historical developments clearly indicate: Why else would they all be falling so sharply across the globe as the modern world-system progresses? Nay, amigo, they are &lt;em&gt;residuals&lt;/em&gt;, leftovers. The most modern countries have the least of these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other category, which concerns us more in this context, are the problems showing up as a direct &lt;em&gt;result&lt;/em&gt; of modern society: &lt;strong&gt;the new emergent properties problems&lt;/strong&gt;. At a bare minimum, there are three such problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ecological unsustainability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;excess inequality, and&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;alienation and stress.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding that these are, on an individual scale, preferable to the wars, droughts and pestilences of yore, they are still quite serious. Sustainability issues like climate change, ecological collapse, mass extinction—not to mention the looming threat of nuclear holocaust and other increasingly tangible doomsday scenarios (haywire AI or nanotech, biological warfare)—can potentially cause miseries worse and more irreparable than even the black plague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inequalities of the world may seem bearable compared to the poverty of pre-modern subsistence farming, but nowadays we all live in the proximity of wealth and abundance, knowing for instance the diseases that kill our kids in fact are curable. Such knowledge can make our relative poverty even more bitter and insufferable than the harshness of pre-modern life. Indeed, it is one of the most robust findings of social science that income inequality correlates with violent crime, within countries and even more so between countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And alienation—a pervading sense of estrangement and existential angst—causes young people to suffer depression and commit suicide to an unprecedented degree. It causes people to live meaningless and empty lives amidst what superficially looks like freedom and abundance; lives in which we become increasingly stressed out and often experience burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember spending seven years fending off suicidal thoughts, as a pervasive but unspecific anxiety haunted my young adulthood. This is not uncommon in developed, modern countries where the trends generally point towards rising mental health problems in adolescents and young adults. These are perhaps not as acute or severe as the challenges that people faced before modernity, but they still remain quite serious issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three of these problems are caused, in one way or another, by the dramatic expansion of our industrial productivity: sustainability because we produce and consume more than our ecosystems can endure, inequality because this wealth is distributed in a series of “scale free networks”, where the most central positions gain a larger proportion of the wealth, and alienation because of the abstractness and distance that shows up between our everyday activities and their benefits for ourselves and others: Many of us lose a sense of meaning, purpose and direction. (Of course, there’s a lot more to the story on each one of these, but we’re just sketching here to get on to the point).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have finally created a land that flows with milk and honey; literally, vast amounts of highly nutritional substances flow from the taps of industry—yet it’s making us and the planet sick. The paradise of yesterday is great, but it carries with it a number of unexpected pathologies that need to be dealt with in tomorrow’s relative utopia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Beauties Lost and New Heights Reached&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the two categories—residual and new emergent properties problems—we can add two more to the list of troubles of today’s society. The third category I’ve called “&lt;strong&gt;beauties lost&lt;/strong&gt;”. It entails all the good things that were prevalent in pre-modern societies, but for different reasons diminished as societies became modern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good example is “community”, or what the classical 19th century sociologist Ferdinand Tönnies called &lt;em&gt;Gemeinschaft&lt;/em&gt; (modern life, at least in its later urbanized stages, generally offers little cozy, genuine community in which you continuously relate to a wider group of family and neighbors).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example of &lt;em&gt;Gemeinschaft&lt;/em&gt; lost, compare the expansion of electronically available music—millions of bands, artists and orchestras available online to be played with marvelous sound systems—to the fact that most of us have stopped singing. In all pre-modern societies, people got together and sang, pretty often too. The individualism and performance oriented attitudes of modern life somehow nudge us to shut up, unless we’re alone in the shower or partake in a formally organized choir. Music gained, but singing lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example of a beauty lost is “simplicity”; that life had a kind of directness and straightforwardness which allowed a certain modest satisfaction. Other such beauties lost are the “connection to the soil”, appreciation of the small things—perhaps a well-crafted tool—or the &lt;em&gt;via contemplativa&lt;/em&gt; of monastic life; the calm, ascetic life in service of spiritual goals. You get the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These “beauties lost” have been brought up by many reactionary movements and romantics of all kinds (I mentioned the integral traditionalists, for instance). With each beauty lost, a part of us is left empty and aching. But the romantic and nostalgic longing lends itself to exaggeration—to overvaluing an imagined past, a yesteryear that never quite happened. What we should do instead is simply to acknowledge that all societal progression into later and “more advanced” stages entails some beauties lost, and that there may be good reasons to figure out how some of these can be regained and reincorporated without trying to turn the clock back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth category of problems is more important. We can call it &lt;strong&gt;“new heights reached”&lt;/strong&gt;. There are problems that are perhaps not directly &lt;em&gt;caused&lt;/em&gt; by modern life, but whose solutions only now come within reach. Only when we acquire greater capabilities can we begin to see them and direct our attention towards them. In the old days, we simply didn’t have the luxury to worry about these problems; now we can. We have reached new heights and hence we can begin to tackle &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; issues. The soul always wants more; it is never contented. You never get to the end; there is always a new horizon after this one, and another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are these new issues then, these “new heights”? I would like to mention four of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; “new-heights issue” is tied to alienation, but still distinct from it: the lack of meaning and fulfillment. What happens in a society where you already have food, shelter and abundance? People begin to worry that they might be squandering their lives; that they may not be making the best of it; that something is still lacking; that life has become boring and too predictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;second&lt;/em&gt; new-heights issue has to do with struggle and heroism; how can we align our own petty lives with the overarching story about humanity, the world and even the cosmos? How can we be something else, something more, than just an average Jane or Joe consumer? Now that we have relative safety and autonomy, how can we make it worthwhile? Once we have achieved a comfortable villa life, there is still, lingering in our hearts, a visceral longing for greatness within us. How can we transcend ourselves; how can we serve something greater so that our lives become imbued with crisp, clear moments of intense aliveness?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;third&lt;/em&gt; higher issue pertains to gender equality and freedom of identity: Can we be sexually emancipated, not only in the sense that we can be women with equal rights as men, but that we can be truly sexually and emotionally fulfilled? Can we experience erotic fulfillment and intimacy both at once? Can we be gay, transgender, or otherwise experiment with and create our sexual and gender identities? Women’s liberation and the other gender/sexuality issues have come within our grasp in modern societies, but they are not conclusively solved by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;fourth&lt;/em&gt; and last higher issue is animal rights. Of course, a big part of the problem with the abuse of animals has to do with modern phenomena such as industrial farming. Animal suffering is exacerbated by modernity, even with the increased legislations for “animal welfare”. There have been some pre-modern examples of principled concern for animals in the Eastern traditions (Buddhism and Jainism), but even these have not quite resembled the modern-day animal rights movement. In Jainism, for instance, concern with animals grew from a general non-violence principle, which is not quite the same as a modern philosophy of “rights”. In modern life, we can now create an abundance of vegan and synthetic solutions that allow us to live without animal slavery and exploitation. Hence, veganism becomes a new issue within our reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, sorry for tricking you into thinking we had only two categories of problems under modernity. We have four, these being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Residual problems&lt;/strong&gt; (left-overs from before modernity). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New emergent properties problems&lt;/strong&gt; (caused by modernity). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beauties lost&lt;/strong&gt; (qualities from earlier societies lost under modernity).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New heights reached&lt;/strong&gt; (problems that simply weren’t viable to try to solve before, but now have come within our reach). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep, that’s it. Modern society is truly utopian, truly glorious. Except it has these four categories of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to the point we’ve been working our way towards. We live today in what to most earlier generations could only be described as sheer utopia. Yet, we hardly wake up every morning to what we feel is a utopian society. It is a utopia only in a &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; sense: The problems of old have all but vanished, just as new ones have appeared—as dark clouds on the horizon, growing cracks in the walls, and new subtle knots within our hearts and minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about metamodern society; is it a utopian project? Yes. It is unapologetically utopian. &lt;strong&gt;A society can be described as metamodern if, and only if, all of the problems of modernity have been more or less resolved, meaning that they have been reduced by at least a power of ten.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, metamodern society is defined as one in which the problems that emerged in modernity—lack of sustainability, excess inequality, alienation and stress—have been resolved. So that’s what we’re going for. Fucking utopia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fucking &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; utopia, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;New Miseries Worth Fighting For&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metamodern society can and will follow the same pattern of relative utopia as modern society has. There will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;residuals&lt;/strong&gt; of the modern problems: still &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; inequality, environmental issues and alienation (whereas the pre-modern residuals are reduced by yet another order of magnitude);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and yes, there will be &lt;strong&gt;new, emergent problems&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;caused&lt;/em&gt; by metamodern society itself (some of which we will discuss in this book in an attempt to preempt them);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and yes, some &lt;strong&gt;beauties of modern life will be lost&lt;/strong&gt; along the way;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and yes, new dark clouds will form on the horizon, new bold challenges to civilization that &lt;strong&gt;come within our grasp&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, in some sense, these new problems will be preferable to what we have today; but strangely, they are likely to somehow be &lt;strong&gt;even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; serious&lt;/strong&gt; than the challenges of modern society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s the notion of “relative utopia” for you. We are trying to achieve a self-organization of society that is happier, in a profound sense of the word, than anything that has gone before it. But we’re not saying it’s going to be a perfect world. In fact, we’re saying it’s going to be as messy and risky as ever. More complex. Why should we expect anything else, when history—cultural, geological and astronomical—has thus far meant explosive increases of complexity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It shouldn’t surprise us that future society will manage issues that today may seem insoluble, out of reach, or downright impossible. That’s what modern society did. It let steel float and fly, it saved us from disease, it conquered the moon, it brought peace—and so forth. Is it really wrong to think that future society, the one that comes after the modern, industrial one, could do what seems unimaginable today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow, modern life—and its relative utopia—&lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; possible. Perhaps metamodern life can be too. A simple reason to assume this is the fact that so many intelligent people are working so hard, in so many different ways, to solve the problems of modernity: sustainability, inequality, alienation. Pretty much every smart and idealistic person is grappling with at least some aspect of one of these issues. It’s all over the sciences, all over policy making, in the arts, even on the market—whoever can solve these problems is most cherished, most appreciated, even well-paid. Are we being pulled in some direction, towards a new great attractor point, upon which a series of attractors converge?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ll say it again. We go ahead with sincere irony, pragmatic idealism, informed naivety and magical realism—to entertain the &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; of a relative utopia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we still live in a tragic universe; as we noted in Book One, existence has us “eternally by the balls”. But there are new miseries on the horizon, miseries worth fighting for. And there is fun to be had along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relishing in cow dung really is a hundred times better than banging one’s head against the invisible barrier of the window. It really is. But it’s still cow dung, and we’re still flies, with our controls set for the heart of the sun.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The problems of old have all but vanished, just as new ones have appeared—as dark clouds on the horizon, growing cracks in the walls, and new subtle knots within our hearts and minds. A metamodern society is one in which the problems that emerged in modernity—lack of sustainability, excess inequality, alienation and stress—have been resolved.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ethics is responsibility for the lively relationalities of becoming</title><link href="/blog/2019/11/19/relationalities-of-becoming.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ethics is responsibility for the lively relationalities of becoming" /><published>2019-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/11/19/relationalities-of-becoming</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/11/19/relationalities-of-becoming.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very nature of materiality is an entanglement. Matter itself is always already open to, or rather entangled with, the &amp;quot;Other.&amp;quot; The intra-actively emergent &amp;quot;parts&amp;quot; of phenomena are co-constituted. Not only subjects but also objects are permeated through and through with their entangled kin; the other is not just in one&amp;#39;s skin, but in one&amp;#39;s bones, in one&amp;#39;s belly, in one&amp;#39;s heart, in one&amp;#39;s nucleus, in one&amp;#39;s past and future. This is as true for electrons as it is for brittlestars as it is for the differentially constituted human... What is on the other side of the agential cut is not separate from us&amp;ndash; agential separability is not individuation. Ethics is therefore not about right response to a radically exterior/ized other, but about responsibility and accountability for the lively relationalities of becoming of which we are a part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;― Karen Barad, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/work/quotes/724258&quot;&gt;Meeting the Universe Halfway: Quantum Physics and the Entanglement of Matter and Meaning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The very nature of materiality is an entanglement. Matter itself is always already open to, or rather entangled with, the &quot;Other.&quot; The intra-actively emergent &quot;parts&quot; of phenomena are co-constituted.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Nordic Ideology: political metamodernism</title><link href="/blog/2019/11/17/nordic-ideology-political-metamodernism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Nordic Ideology: political metamodernism" /><published>2019-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/11/17/nordic-ideology-political-metamodernism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/11/17/nordic-ideology-political-metamodernism.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A couple of sections from the introduction of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/47157252-nordic-ideology&quot;&gt;Nordic Ideology&lt;/a&gt; (sequel to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36107916-the-listening-society&quot;&gt;The Listening Society&lt;/a&gt;) by Hanzi Freinacht of &lt;a href=&quot;https://metamoderna.org/&quot;&gt;Metamoderna&lt;/a&gt;, which act as a decent teaser/summary&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Last Book and This One&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t read the first book, don’t let it haunt you at night; you’ll still get plenty of bang for the buck in this one, even if some of the wider context may be lost on you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s begin where we left off in Book One, &lt;em&gt;The Listening Society&lt;/em&gt;. The final words were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We can go ahead to create a Green Social Liberalism 2.0, working non-linearly, co-developing ourselves towards a listening society. We go ahead with pragmatic idealism, with magical realism and informed naivety. At the crossroads of fact and fiction, we work and play with religious fervor, keeping an ironic smile at our own self-importance.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot to unpack in a few sentences. Here’s what it means:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Green Social Liberalism” is the dominant “meta-ideology” in the Nordic countries today. Here, environmental and social-liberal values have become so widespread in the general population that more or less all the major political parties compete to be the most trustworthy advocate of this ideology. Since there is a wide consensus that the best model for society is a competitive market economy with a universal welfare system, the traditional ideological struggle between Left and Right has waned in favor of a rhetorical spectacle that conceals just how similar the political parties have actually become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a uniquely Nordic phenomenon. If things run smoothly long enough, Green Social Liberalism is where every liberal democracy with an industrial capitalist economy and publicly financed welfare is heading. It’s just because Scandinavia has been exceptionally stable and prosperous for such a long time that we see the tendency most clearly here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the same reason it’s also here we find some vague but substantial bids for what lies beyond this “modern” equilibrium; the 2.0 version of Green Social Liberalism. This new updated meta-ideology is a synthesis that, by today’s standards, would be perceived as far Left, far (libertarian) Right and very Green. And if you look closely, it is taking shape in the Nordic countries as we speak, hence the name “Nordic ideology”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The listening society” is the name for a vision of the future welfare system which expands and deepens the current universal welfare programs by addressing the higher psychological needs of human beings such as belonging, esteem and self-actualization—a welfare system determined to ensure that as many as possible don’t feel lonely, socially inferior or trapped in meaningless lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The listening society is a welfare society that considers the emotional wellbeing of people just as important as their economic welfare; a society that takes into account the more intimate psychological needs of human beings: good relationships, inner security, meaning, self-knowledge. This would be a society where depression, stress and alienation have become political issues in the same vein as security, jobs and housing are today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metamodern activists are unafraid of putting forward such visions; of exposing our necks—although we hold these with a “sincere irony”, always admitting that we are probably, after all, mistaken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think that society needs to move in some kind of direction; and if we play with fictions, make experiments, and combine these with sound factual analyses of our time, there is a likelihood that something good will come out of it. Hence such “both-and” concepts as “pragmatic idealism”, “magical realism”, “informed naivety”, and working at “the crossroads of fact and fiction”. These concepts are central to metamodernism. They put us in the space where we can play and be creative around large and serious issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last book we offered a view of &lt;strong&gt;developmental psychology&lt;/strong&gt;, which explains how people grow “more conscious”—i.e. how we become more complex thinkers, become “happier” (long story, that one), come to adopt more universalistic or progressive values, and relate to more profound aspects of life and reality. A large part of this has been firmly established through psychological research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This developmental perspective was linked to the vision of the aforementioned “listening society”. &lt;strong&gt;The central idea is that by cultivating a listening society, we can not only create much happier human lives, but also dramatically spur the psychological development of larger parts of the population into the higher stages.&lt;/strong&gt; Such development is necessary for people to create, participate in, and uphold functional societies in this increasingly complex world—an endeavor that has both incredible potentials and great risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is the time to make it happen. It is time to achieve this goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Map, The Plan and The Proof&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the last book gave you an introduction to developmental psychology, this book presents you with a &lt;strong&gt;developmental sociology&lt;/strong&gt;, and then links it to a concrete political plan of how you change society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book has three parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Map&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Proof &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of this book is The Map. First I guide you through an understanding of what it means to be a realistic utopian, one who seeks to change and evolve the everyday games of life. Then I go on to argue that there is a certain kind of evolution of society going on—that we can see where things are going; again, a developmental sociology, i.e. a view of how society itself develops. So I present you with a number of “attractor points”, or “attractors”. These constitute evolutionary steps: How do state and governance evolve, what’s the next step? What is freedom, and what is a higher freedom than the one we experience in the “free world” of today? What is equality, and how can it become deeper? Most people, still today, living in societies committed to freedom and equality, cannot answer these questions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed with this map, you may then reap the rewards: The second part of this book is a large-scale strategy being rolled out before you—The Plan for how to fundamentally transform modern society into a metamodern (relative) utopia. I’d like to underscore that &lt;strong&gt;this plan fills a void&lt;/strong&gt;: I can’t think of anyone else who has a plan like it—a plan for the design of global politics, for a new political system, and how to enact it. If you understand the plan, I hold, you are morally obliged to act upon it, to make it happen. If you see where this is going, you’re either obliged to act, or to come up with something better. It’s a bit vulgar, I suppose, to straightforwardly put a plan out there, not a very scholarly or respectable thing to do. But on the other hand, people reading the first book all wondered: What’s the plan? What do we do? I’ll tell you what I think. We need a political program. This is a political program that constitutes, all said and done, the Nordic ideology. It includes six new forms of politics, all explained in detail: &lt;strong&gt;Democratization Politics, Gemeinschaft Politics, Existential Politics, Emancipation Politics, Empirical Politics—and Politics of Theory&lt;/strong&gt;. It ends with zooming out and viewing &lt;strong&gt;the Master Pattern&lt;/strong&gt; that connects all six forms of politics, including some tactical observations for how to make it happen.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this plan make sense? Does the Nordic Ideology work? Shouldn’t we subscribe to one of the existing political ideologies instead? This is where The Proof comes in. This third part of the book is, admittedly, perhaps a bit self-celebratory: It shows you how the Nordic ideology—or political metamodernism—eats all of the existing ideologies alive. It beats them on their own terms. Part Three presents you with the proof for why you can’t just skip metamodernism and stay with one of the old ideologies. Having this understanding helps you organize a transnational metamodernist movement and to outmaneuver all the modern political forces: socialists, libertarians, conservatives, anarchists and ecologists alike—while still helping each of them achieve their respective goals. So you get armed with some well-needed tactics to go along with your strategy. At the very end, we discuss our three evil cousins, the totalitarian specters of the 20th century: communism, fascism and the New Age. All of these dangerous dreams have uncanny but important lessons to teach us. So let us listen.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We can go ahead to create a Green Social Liberalism 2.0, working non-linearly, co-developing ourselves towards a listening society. We go ahead with pragmatic idealism, with magical realism and informed naivety. At the crossroads of fact and fiction, we work and play with religious fervor, keeping an ironic smile at our own self-importance.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bohm’s Gnosis: The Implicate Order</title><link href="/blog/2019/11/15/bohms-gnosis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bohm’s Gnosis: The Implicate Order" /><published>2019-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/11/15/bohms-gnosis</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/11/15/bohms-gnosis.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bizint.com/stoa_del_sol/plenum/plenum_3.html&quot;&gt;Beatrix Murrell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article discusses the vision David Bohm intuited from his insight (gnosis) into the quantum world. This vision discerns the characteristics of an evolving cosmos in process; and, also, it ponders upon the implications for humanity. Bohm&amp;#39;s scientific presentations are not in this article; however, they can be found in his books listed in the Reference Section at the end of these series of articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Bohm and the Implicate Order: An Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Bohm, an American, was one of the leading quantum physicists of our age. He died recently. Following a venerable career at the University of California (Berkeley) and at Princeton&amp;#39;s Institute of Advanced Studies, he moved to become Professor of Theoretical Physics at Birkbeck College of the University of London. During his later years he linked a formidable knowledge of the history and philosophy of science to his keen experience as a physicist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, Bohm attempted to explain an ontological basis for quantum theory. The basis of quantum theory can be summarized in three propositions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the subatomic world, few things can be predicted with 100 percent precision; however, accurate predictions can be made about the probability of any particular outcome.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One has to work with the probabilities rather than certainties, because it is impossible (for an observer) to describe all aspects of a particle at once (speed and location).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Electromagnetic energy (such as light or heat) does not always behave like a continuous wave--rather it is grainy, because energy can be transferred only in quantum packages. Therefore, light has a dual character. Under certain circumstances, it may display wavelike aspects; and in other circumstances, it may have the characteristics of particles.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Referring to quantum theory, Bohm&amp;#39;s basic assumption is that &amp;quot;elementary particles are actually systems of extremely complicated internal structure, acting essentially as amplifiers of &lt;em&gt;information&lt;/em&gt; contained in a quantum wave.&amp;quot; As a conseqence, he has evolved a new and controversial theory of the universe--a new model of reality that Bohm calls the &amp;quot;Implicate Order.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory of the Implicate Order contains an ultraholistic cosmic view; it connects everything with everything else. In principle, any individual element could reveal &amp;quot;detailed information about every other element in the universe.&amp;quot; The central underlying theme of Bohm&amp;#39;s theory is the &amp;quot;unbroken wholeness of the totality of existence as an undivided flowing movement without borders.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the early 1980s Bohm developed his theory of the Implicate Order in order to explain the bizarre behavior of subatomic particles--behavior that quantum phyicists have not been able to explain. Basically, two subatomic particles that have once interacted can instantaneously &amp;quot;respond to each other&amp;#39;s motions thousands of years later when they are light-years apart.&amp;quot; This sort of particle interconnectedness requires superluminal signaling, which is faster than the speed of light. This odd phenomenon is called the EPR effect, named after the Einstein, Podolsky, and Rosen thought experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm believes that the bizarre behavior of the subatomic particles might be caused by unobserved subquantum forces and particles. Indeed, the apparent weirdness might be produced by hidden means that pose no conflict with ordinary ideas of causality and reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm believes that this &amp;quot;hiddeness&amp;quot; may be reflective of a deeper dimension of reality. He maintains that space and time might actually be derived from an even deeper level of objective reality. This reality he calls the Implicate Order. Within the Implicate Order everything is connected; and, in theory, any individual element could reveal information about every other element in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borrowing ideas from holographic photography, the &lt;em&gt;hologram&lt;/em&gt; is Bohm&amp;#39;s favorite metaphor for conveying the structure of the Implicate Order. Holography relies upon wave interference. If two wavelengths of light are of differing frequencies, they will interfere with each other and create a pattern. &amp;quot;Because a hologram is recording detail down to the wavelength of light itself, it is also a dense &lt;em&gt;information&lt;/em&gt; storage.&amp;quot; Bohm notes that the hologram clearly reveals how a &amp;quot;total content--in principle extending over the whole of space and time--is enfolded in the movement of waves (electromagnetic and other kinds) in any given region.&amp;quot; The hologram illustrates how &amp;quot;information about the entire holographed scene is enfolded into every part of the film.&amp;quot; It resembles the Implicate Order in the sense that every point on the film is &amp;quot;completely determined by the overall configuration of the interference patterns.&amp;quot; Even a tiny chunk of the holographic film will reveal the unfolded form of an entire three-dimensional object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proceeding from his holographic analogy, Bohm proposes a new order--the Implicate Order where &amp;quot;everything is enfolded into everything.&amp;quot; This is in contrast to the explicate order where things are unfolded. Bohm puts it thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;The actual order (the Implicate Order) itself has been recorded in the complex movement of electromagnetic fields, in the form of light waves. Such movement of light waves is present everywhere and in principle enfolds the entire universe of space and time in each region. This enfoldment and unfoldment takes place not only in the movement of the electromagnetic field but also in that of other fields (electronic, protonic, etc.). These fields obey quantum-mechanical laws, implying the properties of discontinuity and non-locality. The totality of the movement of enfoldment and unfoldment may go immensely beyond what has revealed itself to our observations. We call this totality by the name &lt;em&gt;holomovement.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm believes that &lt;em&gt;the Implicate Order has to be extended into a multidimensional reality;&lt;/em&gt; in other words, the holomovement endlessly enfolds and unfolds into infinite dimensionality. Within this milieu there are independent sub-totalities (such as physical elements and human entities) with relative autonomy. The layers of the Implicate Order can go deeper and deeper to the ultimately unknown. It is this &amp;quot;unknown and undescribable totality&amp;quot; that Bohm calls the holomovement. The holomovement is the &amp;quot;fundamental ground of all matter.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the manifest world is part of what Bohm refers to as the &amp;quot;explicate order.&amp;quot; It is secondary, derivative; it &amp;quot;flows out of the law of the Implicate Order.&amp;quot; Within the Implicate Order, there is a &amp;quot;totality of forms that have an approximate kind of recurrence (changing), stability, and separability.&amp;quot; It is these forms, according to Bohm, that make up our manifest world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summarizing, Bohm uses analogies most ingeniously as he attempts to simplify his theory. Bohm suggests that instead of thinking of particles as the fundamental reality, the focus should be on discrete particle-like quanta in a continuous field. On the basis of this quantum field, Bohm breaks down the Implicate Order into three categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first category is the original, &amp;quot;continuous field&amp;quot; itself along with its movement. Bohm likens this continuous field to a television screen displaying an infinite variety of explicate forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second category is obtained by considering superquantum wave function acting upon the field. (&amp;quot;This is related to the whole field as the original quantum wave is related to the particle.&amp;quot;) More complex and subtle, this second category applies to a &amp;quot;superfield&amp;quot; or &lt;em&gt;information&lt;/em&gt; that guides and organizes the original quantum field. Bohm considers it to be similar to a computer which supplies the information that arranges the various forms--in the first category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last, Bohm believes that there is an underlying cosmic intelligence that supplies the information--the &lt;em&gt;Player&lt;/em&gt; of this game who is the third category. Folling this analogy, Bohm sees the whole process as a closed loop; it goes from the screen to the computer to the Player and back to the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm&amp;#39;s theory of the Implicate Order stresses that the cosmos is in a state of process. Bohm&amp;#39;s cosmos is a &amp;quot;feedback&amp;quot; universe that continuously recycles forward into a greater mode of being and consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm believes in a special cosmic interiority. It &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the Implicate Order, and it implies enfoldment into everything. Everything that is and will be in this cosmos is enfolded within the Implicate Order. There is a special cosmic movement that carries forth the process of enfoldment and unfoldment (into the explicate order). This process of cosmic movement, in endless feedback cycles, creates an infinite variety of manifest forms and mentality. Bohm is of the opinion that a fundamental Cosmic Intelligence is the &lt;em&gt;Player&lt;/em&gt; in this process; it is engaged in endless experimentation and creativity. This Player, the Cosmic Mind, is moving cyclically onward and onward accruing an infinity of experienced being!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The structural outline of Bohm&amp;#39;s cosmic model is as follows: the Ground of All Existence, Matter, Consciousness, and the Cosmic Apex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Ground of All Existence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very depths of the ground of all existence Bohm believes that there exists a special energy. For Bohm it is the plenum; it is an &amp;quot;immense background of energy.&amp;quot; The energy of this ground is likened to one whole and unbroken movement by Bohm. He calls this the &amp;quot;holomovement.&amp;quot; It is the holomovement that carries the Implicate Order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm also refers to a law in the holomovement. He theorizes that the &amp;#39;order in every immediately perceptible aspect of the world is to be regarded as coming out of a more comprehensive Implicate Order, in which all aspects ultimately merge in the undefinable and immeasurable holomovement. Holonomy, through a wide range of aspects, can be considered a &amp;quot;movement in which new wholes are emerging.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it that emerges from this ultimate ground, this &amp;quot;unknown totality of the universal flux?&amp;quot; It is the extension of the Implicate Order into a multidimensional reality. It is the interplay between the implicate and the explicate orders. It is the flow of matter, manifested and interdependent, towards consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Matter: Inanimate and Animate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right off Bohm refers to the particle, the most essential building- block of matter. He considers the particle, fundamentally, to be only an &amp;quot;abstraction that is manifest to our senses.&amp;quot; Basically, for Bohm, the whole cosmos is matter; in his own words: &amp;quot;What &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; is always a totality of ensembles, all present together, in an orderly series of stages of enfoldment and unfoldment, which intermingle and interpenetrate each other in principle throughout the whole of space.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm&amp;#39;s explicate order, however, is secondary--derivative. It flows out of the law of the Implicate Order, a law that stresses the relationships between the enfolded structures that interweave each other throughout cosmic space rather than between the &amp;quot;abstracted and separate forms that manifest to the senses.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm&amp;#39;s explanation of &amp;quot;manifest&amp;quot; is basically that in certain sub-orders, within the &amp;quot;whole set&amp;quot; of Implicate Order, there is a &amp;quot;totality of forms that have an approximate kind of recurrence, stability and separability.&amp;quot; These forms are capable of appearing tangible, solid, and thus make up our manifest world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm also declares that the &amp;quot;implicate order has to be extended into a multidimensional reality.&amp;quot; He proceeds: &amp;quot;In principle this reality is one unbroken whole, including the entire universe with all its fields and particles. Thus we have to say that the holomovement enfolds and unfolds in a multidimensional order, the dimensionality of which is effectively infinite. Thus the principle of relative autonomy of sub-totalities--is now seen to extend to the multi-dimensional order of reality.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm illustrates this higher-dimensional reality by showing the relationship of two televised images of a fish tank, where the fish are seen through two walls at right angles to one another. What is seen is that there is a certain &amp;quot;relationship between the images appearing on the two screens.&amp;quot; We know, Bohm notes, that the two fish tank images are interacting actualities, but they are not two independently existent realities. &amp;quot;Rather, they refer to a single actuality, which is the common ground of both.&amp;quot; For Bohm this single actuality is of higher dimensionality, because the television images are two-dimensional projections of a three-dimensional reality, which &amp;quot;holds these two-dimensional projections within it.&amp;quot; These projections are only abstractions, but the &amp;quot;three-dimensional reality &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; neither of these--rather it is something else, something of a nature beyond both.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is apparent evolution in the universe, it is &lt;em&gt;because the different scales or dimensions of reality are already implicit in its structure.&lt;/em&gt; Bohm uses the analogy of the seed being &amp;quot;informed&amp;quot; to produce a living plant. The same can be said of all living matter. &amp;quot;Life is enfolded in the totality and--even when it is not manifest, it is somehow implicit.&amp;quot; The holomovement is the ground for both life and matter. There is no dichotomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What lies ahead? For Bohm it is the development of consciousness!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Consciousness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm conceives of consciousness as more than information and the brain; rather it is information that enters into consciousness. For Bohm consciousness &amp;quot;involves awareness, attention, perception, acts of understanding, and perhaps yet more.&amp;quot; Further, Bohm parallels the activity of consciousness with that of the Implicate Order in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consciousness, Bohm notes, can be &amp;quot;described in terms of a series of moments.&amp;quot; Basically, &amp;quot;one moment gives rise to the next, in which context that was previously implicate is now explicate while the previous explicate content has become implicate.&amp;quot; Consciousness is an interchange; it is a feedback process that results in a growing accumulation of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm considers the human individual to be an &amp;quot;intrinsic feature of the universe, which would be incomplete--in some fundamental sense&amp;quot; if the person did not exist. He believes that individuals participate in the whole and consequently give it meaning. Because of human participation, the &amp;quot;Implicate Order is getting to know itself better.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm also senses a new development. The individual is in total contact with the Implicate Order, the individual is part of the whole of mankind, and he is the &amp;quot;focus for something beyond mankind.&amp;quot; Using the analogy of the transformation of the atom ultimately into a power and chain reaction, Bohm believes that the individual who uses inner energy and intelligence can transform mankind. The collectivity of individuals have reached the &amp;quot;principle of the consciousness of mankind,&amp;quot; but they have not quite the &amp;quot;energy to reach the whole, to put it all on fire.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing with this theme on the transformation of consciousness, Bohm goes on to suggest that an intense heightening of individuals who have shaken off the &amp;quot;pollution of the ages&amp;quot; (wrong worldviews that propagate ignorance), who come into close and trusting relationship with one another, can begin to generate the immense power needed to ignite the whole consciousness of the world. In the depths of the Implicate Order, there is a &amp;quot;consciousness, deep down--of the whole of mankind.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is this collective consciousness of mankind that is truly significant for Bohm. It is this collective consciousness that is truly one and indivisible, and it is the responsibility of each human person to contribute towards the building of this consciousness of mankind, this noosphere! &amp;quot;There&amp;#39;s nothing else to do--there is no other way out. That is absolutely what has to be done and nothing else can work.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm also believes that the individual will eventually be fulfilled upon the completion of cosmic noogenesis. Referring to all the elements of the cosmos, including human beings, as projections of an ultimate totality, Bohm notes that as a &amp;quot;human being takes part in the process of this totality, he is fundamentally changed in the very activity in which his aim is to change that reality, which is the content of his consciousness.&amp;quot; Bohm is intuiting that the human person and mankind collectively, upon accomplishing a successful noogenesis, will come to fullness within that greater dimension of reality--the Cosmic Apex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Cosmic Apex&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm refers to this ultimate level--the source of the nonmanifest--as the Subtle Nonmanifest, something akin to spirit, a mover, but still matter in the sense that it is a part of the Implicate Order. For Bohm, the Subtle Nonmanifest is an &lt;em&gt;active intelligence&lt;/em&gt; beyond any of the &amp;quot;energies defined in thought.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to describe the Subtle Nonmanifest, Bohm states that the &amp;quot;subtle is what is basic and the manifest is its result.&amp;quot; T îve intelligence &amp;quot;directly transforms matter.&amp;quot; And finally, Bohm says it straight: &amp;quot;there&amp;#39;s a truth, an actuality, a being beyond what can be grasped in thought, and this is intelligence, the sacred, the holy.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm poetically thinks of this cosmic Subtle Nonmanifest in a state of meditation. But what is it doing? Meditation means &amp;quot;to reflect, to turn something over in the mind, and to pay close attention.&amp;quot; Without explanation, Bohm wonders aloud that while we meditate on that which we term the subtle nonmanifest, does the Subtle Nonmanifest concentrate on &lt;em&gt;its&lt;/em&gt; Subtle Nonmanifest?&amp;quot; Does this mean that the Cosmic Apex ponders upon something beyond or outside of itself? Possibly Bohm is considering the infinite potential of what he terms &amp;quot;multidimensional reality.&amp;quot; He might also be thinking of the possibility of Something Separate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Bohm, the Cosmic Apex is a Holy Intelligence. It is a Player who operates in a feedback universe. The Player &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the Impicate Order. Bohm provides the analogy of the &amp;quot;continuous field,&amp;quot; the information, and the Player of the whole game. This process is ever endless, ever expanding or evolving, as the Player gathers all to itself. The player continuously grasps itself. &lt;em&gt;This is the Play of the Cosmic Process!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are certain characteristics that can be discerned from Bohm&amp;#39;s cosmic model. They are Order, Intelligence, Personalization, Creativity, and a sense of Holiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Order&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm believes that a special cosmic energy holds the All together, and this cosmic energy follows a cosmic law (order). Bohm refers to it as the law in the holomovement. His viewpoint is that of &amp;quot;wholeness.&amp;quot; The law of his holographic cosmic system is simply a movement which enables new &amp;quot;wholes&amp;quot; to emerge. These new holistic aspects may appear possibly to have some autonomy, but ultimately they are all aspects of the All.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Intelligence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before consciousness there is information; it is information, an inwardness, according to Bohm, that enters into consciousness. Bohm speculates that this inwardness in consciousness may be likened to an &lt;em&gt;insight&lt;/em&gt; which could, if refined, be used as an instrument for letting the &amp;quot;energies (of the Subtle Nonmanifest) come through.&amp;quot; Bohm refers to this as an &amp;quot;active intelligence.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm considers thought as basically mechanical in its operation. What makes the mechanical thought process relevant is intelligence. Bohm puts it thus: &amp;quot;The perception of whether or not any particular thoughts are relevant or fitting requires the operation of an energy that is not mechanical, an energy that we shall call intelligence.&amp;quot; He continues: &amp;quot;For example, one may be working on a puzzling problem for a long time. Suddenly, in a flash of understanding, one may see the irrelevance of one&amp;#39;s whole way of thinking about the problem, along with a different approach--such a flash is essentially an &lt;em&gt;act of perception.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm believes that if intelligence is an &amp;quot;unconditioned act of perception,&amp;quot; than the intelligence cannot be grounded in &amp;quot;structures such as cells, molecules, atoms, and elementary particles.&amp;quot; The operation of intelligence, for Bohm, has to be beyond any factors that can be included in any knowable law. The &amp;quot;ground of intelligence must be in the undetermined and unknown flux, that is also the ground of all definable forms of matter.&amp;quot; For Bohm, intelligence has always been at the very core of the Implicate Order!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Personalization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm is somewhat reserved about the theoretical prospects of cosmic personalization; nonetheless, he points to such a possibility in vague, cyclic terminology about human projections: &amp;quot;each of these elements is a projection, in a sub-totality of yet higher dimension. So it will be ultimately misleading and indeed wrong to suppose, for example, that each human being is an independent actuality who interacts with other human beings and with nature. Rather, all these are projections of a single totality. As a human being takes part in the process of this totality, he is fundamentally changed in the very activity in which his aim is to change that reality which is the content of his consciousness.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm considers that consciousness is an exchange between the explicate and implicate orders. Consciousness is part of the play of the cosmic process, grasping itself (through its sub-totalities) into higher and higher levels of consciousness. Logically, if cosmic sub-totalities (such as human beings) can be considered to be persons (of which only a few are developing toward higher levels of Personhood), than through the feedback interchange, the cosmos is becoming progressively personalized as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Creativity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Cosmic Knower, the &lt;em&gt;Player of the Cosmic Process,&lt;/em&gt; is pure energy. It is intelligent. It is conscious. It is a Person. And this Player is also creative!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering cosmic creativity, Bohm introduces a new concept in which he describes the Implicate Order as a kind of &lt;em&gt;generative order.&lt;/em&gt; He notes that &amp;quot;This order is primarily concerned not with the outward side of development, and evolution in a sequence of successions, but with a deeper and more inward order out of which the manifest form of things can emerge &lt;em&gt;creatively.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm believes that the generative order &amp;quot;proceeds from an origin in free play which then unfolds into ever more crystallized forms.&amp;quot; Generative order can be seen in the work of an artist. Bohm uses the example of Mandelbrot&amp;#39;s mathematically-derived fractals to illustrate more scientifically this cosmic generativity. &amp;quot;Fractals involve an order of similar differences which include changes of scale as well as other possible changes.&amp;quot; Bohm notes that &amp;quot;By choosing different base figures and generators, but each time applying the generator on a smaller and smaller scale, Mandelbrot is able to produce a great variety of shapes and figures--All are filled with infinitesimal detail and are evocative of the types of complexity found in natural forms.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Holiness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Bohm the Holy is a &amp;quot;being beyond what can be grasped in thought.&amp;quot; and Bohm calls the Subtle Nonmanifest &amp;quot;holy&amp;quot; in the sense that it is whole. It is a Presence within cosmic energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bohm cosmic model also suggests that this &amp;quot;holiness&amp;quot; has existed since the foundation of the cosmos. It is present in the cyclical process of the universe. It is pure, active intelligence from which all that is manifest in the cosmos comes. It acts through an inwardness in consciousness. It enfolds information into the many levels of consciousness, into all of life. It is the Implicate Order which is the Ground of All Existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Cosmic Pilgrim&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humanity is the pilgrim in this cosmic process. What does Bohm have to say about the human condition?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What of Evil? For Bohm there are the evils of disorder (which causes suffering) and death. Bohm does not believe that there is disorder at the level of the non-human universality, rather it is at the level of humanity--mainly because of ignorance. Nature has allowed humanity the luxury to make mistakes, because humankind must have the &amp;quot;possibility of being creative.&amp;quot; It is our fledgling ranking in this cosmic process that places us in these circumstances of choice and possible chaos. Disorder, and its consequent suffering, will prevail as long as all the different elements (of any given system, whether a human body or human society) &amp;quot;chaotically grow independently of each other, don&amp;#39;t work together.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm is dispassionate about Life and Death. He uses the analogy of a live oak tree. Creation-dissolution-creation all coexist in that live oak tree. The &amp;quot;leaves are continually forming and some are dropping off at the same time, so that it looks as if it&amp;#39;s a constant tree.&amp;quot; Bohm continues, noting that &amp;quot;its from the nonmanifest that the tree is continually forming and into the nonmanifest that it is dying.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What of the evil of Ignorance? The ignorance of humanity, in Bohm&amp;#39;s opinion, is a matter of closed mindedness. He considers it the &amp;quot;darkness in the human brain.&amp;quot; It is a matter of the human ego closed to the Universal Mind, to the supreme intelligence who communicates through the mode of insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Bohm, insight is pure perception. Because of the low level of our ego development (manifested by our grandiosity, our emotional fears and pressures, our ignorant worldviews, and our gross extraversion), this insight is more than often deflected by a closed mind. The opposite of the closed mind is the openness to interiority. Human beings must look within in order to meet and scrutinize universal insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does Bohm think of human Consciousness and Creativity? For Bohm unfolded creative intelligence originated in the depths of the generative order (the Implicate Order). &amp;quot;In the free play of thought,&amp;quot; Bohm says that the &amp;quot;creative intelligence responds to opposition and contradiction with new proposals.&amp;quot; He believes that every aspect of human experience, whether physical or mental, emotional or intellectual, can be &amp;quot;profoundly affected by creative intelligence, wherever this is able to act.&amp;quot; And &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; in Bohm&amp;#39;s mind is a &lt;em&gt;breakthrough&lt;/em&gt; experience, because through the action of cosmic creative intelligence &amp;quot;everything may take on a new meaning.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What of Human Destiny, how does Bohm consider this? Bohm&amp;#39;s overall vision of human destiny is short and straightforward: &amp;quot;The consciousness of mankind is one and not truly divisible.&amp;quot; Each person ha s a responsibility to achieve this and nothing else. &amp;quot;There is no other way out. That is absolutely what has to be done and nothing else can work.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm believes that only through collective cooperation can man accrue the high degree of energy required to &amp;quot;reach the whole of the consciousness of mankind.&amp;quot; Bohm believes that the individual is in total contact with the Implicate Order. In that sense, the individual &amp;quot;is part of the whole of mankind and in another sense he can get beyond it.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bohm goes no further. It can only be speculated that Bohm is thinking of a kind of ascension, of a new way of being, perhaps of a New Being?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Bohm, WHOLENESS AND THE IMPLICATE ORDER.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Bohm and B.J. Hiley, THE UNDIVIDED UNIVERSE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Bohm and J. Krishnamurti, THE ENDING OF TIME.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Bohm and J. Krishnamurti, THE FUTURE OF HUMANITY.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Bohm and F. David Peat, SCIENCE, ORDER, AND CREATIVITY.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ken Wilber (ed.), THE HOLOGRAPHIC PARADIGM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Articles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Bohm, &amp;quot;Quantum Theory as an Indication of a New Order in Physics--Implicate and Explicate Order in Physical Law,&amp;quot; PHYSICS (GB), 3.2 (June 1973), pp. 139-168.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David Bohm, B.J, Hiley, and P.N. Kaloyerou, &amp;quot;Ontological Basis for the Quantum Theory,&amp;quot; PHYSICS REPORTS (Netherlands) 144.6 (January 1987), pp. 323-348.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">At the very depths of the ground of all existence Bohm believes that there exists a special energy. The energy of this ground is likened to one whole and unbroken movement by Bohm. He calls this the &quot;holomovement.&quot; It is the holomovement that carries the Implicate Order.</summary></entry></feed>